About Moose and Moose-Hunting

It is a vast and lonely region in Northern Canada where the moose roams and lives, and the huge size of this monstrous creature—it is the largest of the whole deer family—makes hunting it a very exciting business. Accustomed to dwell all its life in the deepest recesses of primæval forest, the powers of sight in the moose are not highly developed. Sometimes, when the wind was in the right direction, and the creature got no telltale scent of my approach, I have almost walked right up under his very nose without his seeing me.

It is upon their unrivalled powers of smell that these gigantic deer depend chiefly for their safety. Nature has provided them with a proboscis of enormous proportions, as you may see by going to any natural history museum, and in the wide nostrils gaping at the end of that expansive muzzle the faintest odour is quickly registered, and the owners are off at top speed in less than a second.

With their heads lowered, and in spite of the bull’s spreading horns, they charge through the woods at full tilt, crashing through the densest underbrush as if it were merely hay, and smashing young tree stems as if they were the stalks of sunflowers. Everywhere, in these northern woods, beyond Quebec and south of James Bay, can be seen traces of their passage: trunks with the bark scraped off where they rubbed their horns; broken saplings: tufts of coarse brown hair caught on pointed branches, and the print of their great hoofs and tremendous stride everywhere on the ground.

Accustomed to the dim twilight of the great woods, the eyeballs of these creatures are oblique, as with deer, and do not seem to be specially sensitive. They never turn their heads at shadows. Provided the wind is right, as I said, you can approach a moose to within a few feet, if you go perfectly straight in front of him, and he will never see you. If he does raise his head, it will mean that his ears have warned him of your approach. If you can fool his ears, you can put salt on his tail, say the hunters. But wind and rain are the best aids. Noisy weather is good hunting weather. The roar of the branches, the rattle of the rain, and the constant dripping from the trees combine to drown the sounds of your approach. Then there is a good chance of success.

The front legs of moose are much longer than the hind ones, and to drink, if the bank be steep, or to crop the sweet shoots of the wild rice, they are obliged to kneel. Their food, however, consists chiefly of the ground hemlock, whose low bushes cover the ground in the neighbourhood of the big hemlock-trees, and can be easily got at in winter by scraping away the surface snow; but they are also very fond of the topmost leaves of the young maples, which their great height enables them to pull down and devour with ease. On all sides, where moose have been travelling in the autumn, the maple saplings can be seen bent double to the ground; and when the earth is too hard to show a track, an experienced hunter can follow the path of a moose for miles and miles by observing where he has cropped the hemlock and swept maple-leaves on both sides as he sauntered slowly along, enjoying his vegetarian meal.

In the great heats of July and August these animals suffer terribly from the sun, owing to the thickness of a hairy skin that also serves to keep them warm when the thermometer is 40 below zero. In these months they often wade into the cool lakes and ponds, and stand up to their necks in water, where the Indians, to their shame, used to slaughter them without mercy. They offer a large target, and, though splendid swimmers, they cannot get away from the bullet in time. These same Indians always say that the bear is the shyest animal of the woods. Bruin certainly is a very wary and shy beast; but the moose, in my opinion, comes in an uncommonly close second.

On all sides you can see rotten logs torn open by the bears in their search for ants and honey, and the deep trail leading up to the log and away from it again; but the old bear himself is probably miles away by the time you come upon the scene, covering the ground in that rolling, tumbling gait of his that carries him along at incredible speed. It is no uncommon sight to surprise a bear among the low fruit-bushes, no matter which way the wind is. When berries are thick you may stumble upon bear quite frequently, standing on their hind legs among the blueberry-bushes with front paws round some nice rich clump, and gluttonously devouring the ripe fruit with much grunting. But whoever came upon a moose in the middle of his dinner, unless wind, weather, and all else too were against him?

Moose move generally in groups of four or five, or less. Several groups of this size travel in the same direction, and cover practically the same country at the same time. In this sense they may be described as moving in widely scattered herds. They get over vast distances, moving with great speed, and the enormous territory at their disposal, of course, makes difficult hunting. You must have iron muscles, and be tireless. A fresh moose track—that is, one with no water or cobwebs in it—may be followed for fifty miles, the creature always keeping half a dozen miles ahead of the hunter. If, meanwhile, it chooses to take to the water, the tracks, of course, are lost, and so much time has been wasted, that’s all!

The utmost caution has to be observed. Their ears are sharper than those of a deer, and their scent keener than that of almost any creature in the woods. If a twig snaps beneath your moccasin, or your coat brushes noisily against a branch, especially in damp weather, when noises are sharper, they will put another mile or two to their credit before you have gone a hundred yards.

The usual way of hunting moose is to find a fresh track—and then follow it. To find a track at all is a matter of some training. It is easy enough, of course, when the ground is soft and muddy, to see the great hoof-mark of a bull moose, or the more pointed impression of the cow’s pad, but when the earth is hard and the light poor (as often is the case in the dense Canadian forests), you may search for days and find nothing encouraging. An Indian, or an experienced woodsman, will see a track in a second, where you or I might pass over the ground as untouched and useless. Often have I followed a good strong track for miles, and then suddenly lost it on coming to a stretch of hard earth, whereas the woodsman with me has gone straight ahead without hesitation as though he were following a pathway marked with white stones. It is extraordinary, however, to note how the senses improve after a few weeks in the woods, and how much keener the sight gets, and the power of hearing. Men who live entirely in cities are always astonished at the powers of vision and hearing of the backwoodsman; but after a little practice you soon become far more expert.

The silence of these woods, for one thing, is extraordinarily deep. I have often sat at my tent door when the others have already rolled up and gone to sleep in their blankets, and listened intently in order to train my ears to catch the lightest sound. Dense trees and underbrush on all sides, stretching for hundreds of miles, full of moving, running life—and yet hardly a sound reached me. There is a sort of low humming murmur. The woods emit a sort of whispering, made up of a thousand-and-one little tiny voices and sounds. But in vain you listen for any distinct, unmistakable noise.

The deep silence of the forest at night is more to be wondered at when you reflect that everything alive in the woods travels at night and rests by day. The woods “travel” in the darkness, to use the hunters’ term, and the animals prowl and hunt. Moose, deer, bear, foxes, wolves, everything, in fact, moves then, either in pursuit of prey or to change their hunting-grounds. Yet hardly a sound of all this reaches you. I have sat at my tent door, with the dying embers of the fire at my feet, and peered out into the darkness, knowing well that there was not a hundred yards in any direction in which some living creature was not moving. Eyes were watching me on all sides, and had I moved to aim my rifle, or stood up to poke the logs into a blaze, numbers of little furry feet would everywhere have scuttled off a little farther into the shadows. Yet there was no sound—not the breaking of a twig or the crackling of a dry leaf beneath the lightest paw.

It is curious, too, how a man who loves the woods and dwells in them soon learns to imitate the habits of the animals. He learns, for one thing, to move silently. When hunting moose this is of great value, and the man who can tread on a twig with out making it snap has a great advantage over the clumsy fellow who goes along snapping and cracking at every step.

I have followed a backwoodsman step by step for miles, going after moose, treading exactly in his tracks, and choosing my way most carefully, yet have noticed that, whereas he moved soundlessly, or nearly so, it seemed impossible for me to put my foot down without making enough noise to frighten any animal who was downwind within a hundred yards.

By degrees one learns, of course, so to distribute the weight of the body that the twig is pressed into the earth without snapping. The method is difficult to describe, but you gradually learn it. The moccasins are soft under the feet, and never slip, and you find out after a bit—if you have it in you at all—how to move with the branches and underbrush, instead of against them. This is the secret of stealthy moving, and a good hunter picks it up in time, though he can never hope to attain to the absolute soundlessness of the snakelike Indian motion.

At first, after you strike a fresh moose track and follow it, the stride is fairly regular, and you can see how the creature has ambled along in a leisurely fashion, nibbling the hemlock branches off the ground, or going to one side or the other to pull down some maple sapling and eat the juicy top leaves. Then, perhaps, the stride lengthens, and you know he has begun to move faster. His great legs are stretching out a bit.

Presently, you see a spot where the hoof marks become a little confused and pointing in all directions, and you know that he has scented danger, and has paused to listen, turning his body to catch the wind, and ploughing up the ground as he turns. After that the length of the stride gets bigger and bigger, and you know he is on the run. He has got wind of you, either by scent or hearing, and is off at that long, loping gallop which carries him through the woods at a tremendous pace.

Pursuit is then useless. He may run for twenty miles without stopping. He may come to water and swim over to the other shore, or he may dive and double in such a confusing way through the dense tangle that it is hopeless to follow him with any chance of catching up for a shot. The distance between the hoof-marks gives you a good idea of the size of their owner, and the ease with which he takes a striding jump over fallen trees thrills you with the knowledge that you are after no ordinary deer.

Deer, by the way, it is interesting to note, are not so plentiful as the hunter might expect in these regions; and the man who goes into camp with light provisions, relying upon venison for his meat supply, may find more trouble in keeping his larder filled than he likes. The wolves keep their ranks thin. No wolf can catch a deer in the woods, if the conditions of the chase be equal; but in the winter, ferocious with long fasting, wolves chase the deer on the ice of the frozen lakes and rivers, and soon get their teeth into the tender flanks. Wolves move more easily than deer on the slippery surface, and, being lighter, do not sink so deeply into the patches of soft snow. The barking of a few wolves in pursuit of a deer sounds like the fighting and snarling of a lot of angry dogs. It must be an unpleasant sound to have at your heels at any time, and the poor deer makes the most frantic efforts to escape, but only slips from side to side, growing weaker every minute, till at length it is overhauled and torn to pieces.

I was once in camp in this region, moose hunting, and a friend and his wife cccupied a little tent just behind my own. The lady held the wolves in special abhorrence. She hated to hear them bark at night. During the first week in camp some animal had been heard snuffing and prowling round their tent during the night. The ground was too bare and hard to show any tracks, and the opinion of our party was divided as to whether it was a bear, a porcupine, or a wolf.

“It seems to be a largish animal,” she said, “judging by the sound.”

Just as I was dozing off one night, after a hard day’s hunting, I heard voices in the tent next to me.

“There’s that animal again,” said the lady’s voice, speaking to her sleepy husband. “You really must get up and see what it is. I believe it’s a wolf.”

“Oh, it’s nothing but a silly porcupine looking for grub,” declared the husband, who did not want to get out of his warm blankets, for it was a cold night, and camp-beds are difficult to make up again.

“But it’s rubbing against my side of the tent. It’s trying to get in,” she said, getting more excited.

“But that’s no reason why I should get out!” growled the husband.

However, the wife thought it was a very good reason, so, after a little more growling, the husband got up and peeped through the opening of the tent very cautiously. The moon shone brightly, but only seemed to make the shadows beneath the trees darker than ever.

“Take the rifle,” I heard her whisper.

“I’ve got it,” he said. “Give me the lantern. I hope the beast won’t go for my legs. “I’ve got nothing on.”

“Put on your top boots,” advised the practical wife.

A sound of laughter came from the men’s tent beyond. Evidently they were listening and enjoying the situation as much as I was. There were manifold sounds of preparation, and, in due course, the husband issued forth into the cold night arrayed in top boots, pea-jacket, and striped pyjamas. The lantern swung over his arm, and the rifle was loaded and pointed at full cock.

I heard his footsteps going cautiously round the tent, and, as I lay in my sleeping bag, I hoped devoutly that he would be careful how he fired, and not aim too low, or in my direction. I think the wife and the men had the same uncomfortable thoughts. Suddenly there was a shout.

“I see it!” he cried, and the next instant the rifle cracked.

“It’s a skunk, I do declare!” he cried, with a roar of laughter.

And a skunk it was, and nothing more. But we others thought a good deal of that skunk, for the wind was blowing our way, and the whole benefit of the penetrating and offensive odour of that harmless but terrible little animal was wafted into our tents. The guides burnt the body, but you cannot burn the smell of a skunk, and next day it was so bad that we were obliged, at great trouble, to pitch our tents in another part of the woods altogether.

About the Moravians

The history of the Moravian Church is a history of the grand triumph of an earnest brotherhood over the effects of persecution, banishment, and many other difficulties. It tells how a little company of Christians fought, not only to keep their own particular Church and creed unspotted from the world, but how when numbering only six hundred unhappy exiles, they commenced a series of missionary efforts which have been abundantly blessed of God—missions which have been so energetically carried out that they now number over seventy-six thousand converts, and which for the zeal and courage shown by the workers have won the respect of all the civilized world.

The early history of the United Brethren—as the Moravians were first called—is one of peculiar interest, showing as it does, from what small beginnings God can produce the mightiest results.

In the sixteenth and seventeenth centuries there existed a religious community to the number of, perhaps, two hundred thousand, called the “Bohemian Brethren.”They were scattered throughout Bohemia and certain parts of Poland, and were remarkable for the zeal and general purity of their lives.

In the beginning of the seventeenth century, however, they were scattered, and to all appearances ceased to exist. Yet there still existed a “hidden seed”which kept alive the tenets and usages of former years. This remnant used to hold their services with as much zeal and more prudence than ever, and in secret crypts and private houses, prayed for a reawakening of their ancient Church. This was eventually granted; and the manner in which it was brought about leads us up to the actual commencement of the so-called Moravian Church.

Let us glance at the early history of the man who was so instrumental in bringing this about.

Count Zinzendorf was the son of parents who were eminently distinguished for their piety and Christian example, and he him self as a child exhibited signs of a precocious piety which has rarely been equalled in one so young. Not only was the Saviour over present in the events of his daily life, but the young Count even “wrote letters to Him, in which he poured out his religious feelings,”and threw these letters out of the window, “confident that the Lord would receive and read them.”

This religious fervour manifested itself still further in his school-life. At his first school we find him at the head of a society which he founded for the purpose of spreading the Gospel and cultivating personal piety amongst his school-fellows. It was called “The Order of the Grain of Mustard Seed,” and through its means an excellent moral tone was spread throughout the school On leaving school the Count entered the University of Wittenberg, and since his pious inclinations led him to prefer the Church as his life-work, he began to study theology. Here, however, he met with opposition from an unexpected quarter. His relatives and many of his most intimate friends strenuously opposed such a course; they would not for a moment entertain the idea of a German Count in their family becoming a preacher; it could not be.

So strong, indeed, was the feeling against it, that the Count gave up the idea of becoming that for which he was obviously most fitted, and began to study law. His course at the university ended, he started on a course of travels through Europe, which was considered part of every young nobleman’s education. Study of the law had by no means quenched the fire of religious zeal within his heart; so we find that an occurrence of no unusual magnitude was sufficient to fan it into a flame again. In a picture gallery in Düsseldorf, on the Rhine, he came across a picture that was destined to lead him again into that path whence he had allowed himself so easily to be turned aside. It was an “Ecce Homo,” with the words underneath:

“Hoc feci pro te; quid facis pro me?”

“This I did for thee. What hast thou done for Me?”

This picture had such an effect on him that he stood before it for hours, wrapt in oblivion of all else around him. It reawakened in him all his old zeal and fervour in the cause he loved so well; and from that moment he never lost an opportunity to boldly confess his Saviour.

Soon after, in the year 1722, he married, and it is at this point we find bim so wonderfully brought into contact with the persecuted remnants of the “Bohemian Church.”Just when these were almost despairing of infusing, in any successful degree, new life and vigour into their old Church, or of giving to it a public existence again, we find them mysteriously brought into contact with the man who above all others seemed best fitted to carry out and embody such a resuscitation. Count Zinzendorf was just then moving to a large estate which he had recently bought from his grandmother in Lusatia when he met two families, by name Neisser, refugees from the persecuted and suppressed sect of the Bohemian Brethren. Without entertaining any further intentions than to show kindness to devout fellow creatures in trouble, the Count at once invited them to come and settle on the broad lards of his estate, Bertholsdorf. Knowing little or nothing about their former history or creed, he had at the time no ideas of joining with them in any way; and the gradual manner in which he was brought to see that his line of work and scope for his energy lay in the reawakening of the old Church must be ascribed to the guidance of the Spirit of God.

In the meantime, that between the years 1722 and 1729, over three hundred more Brethren had migrated to the estate of the Count, and these were soon joined by the members of other Protestant communities, and under their united direction a town was built, which they called Herrnhut, or the “Watch of the Lord.” The origin of this name is thus given by Dr. Abel Stevens in his History of Methodism:

“Christian David, an earnest-minded carpenter, led ten persons of like mind from Schlen, in Moravia, to Bertholsdorf, in Lusatia; a domain of which Count Zinzendorf, a derout young nobleman, was then lord. He was absent, but welcomed them by Heitz, his major-domo. Heitz led the little band to a piece of land near a mound, the Hutberg, or watch-hill, where, Christian David, lifting his axe, cleaved a tree, exclaiming, “Here hath the sparrow found a house and the swallow a nest for herself, even Thine altars, O Lord of hosts.”

Two years later, Count Zinzendorf resigned the office he then held, and deeply impressed by a certain book of one of the Bohemian Brothers, he resolved to devote all his energy to the revival of the ancient Church. He said of Herrnhut that he was convinced it was “the parish to which he had from all eternity been ordained.”

Henceforth we find the Count devoting all his time and labour to the Moravians, whose leader he thus became. As a result, in the year 1736, he was banished from Saxony. He then started on a long course of travels, everywhere preaching the Gospel and founding branches of the Moravian Church. In 1741 he visited America, and established a school at Bethlehem, Pennsylvania, where is still a Moravian community, as also at Letitz and Nazareth. At length the Count died peacefully in Herrnhut, in the year 1760, and on his grave-stone may still be read the legend, “He was ordained to bring forth fruit,” and “that his fruit should remain.”

Such was the origin of the Moravian Church, and from this source sprung the mighty stream of mission workers and mission schemes ever associated with its name. Although the death of Count Zinzendorf deprived the Moravians of a splendid worker and an active leader, the Church was too firmly established to again fall into decline. The life in it was strong, vigorous and aggressive.

In 1738 the Moravians had crossed into Great Britain and a flourishing settlement had there been founded; and it was in this same year that John Wesley first came under the influence of the Brotherhood. In crossing from America he found himself in the same vessel with a party of Moravians, and “amid the storms of the Atlantic he had seen in them a resignation and a piety which he possessed not himself. ” The man, however, who seems to have made the most lasting impression on John Wesley’s mind was Peter Böhler. They first met in 1738 in London, and Wesley says in his diary,”It was a day much to be remembered,”adding, “From this time I did not willingly lose an opportunity of conversing with him.”Again, later on he writes, “By Bühler, in the band of the great God, I was convinced of unbelief, of the want of that faith whereby alone we are saved. ” His brother, Charles Wesley, after attending one of the small assemblies of the Moravians, said, “I thought myself in a choir of angels.”

Thus it was that Moravianism played no small part in connection with the history of early Methodism, and had no inconsiderable influence on the wonderful after-lives of the two Wesleys.

At the present day, more especially in its missions, has the Moravian Church been blessed; and although these have not always been successful, the zeal and love of souls which inspired them is ever worthy of the highest admiration. From Lapland and Labrador to the Islands of the East Indies the Moravian missionaries have spent their lives and strength in spreading the Gospel they loved so well.

At the present day the Church has four hundred and fourteen bishops or ministers, over seventy-six thousand converts, besides numerous deacons, deaconesses and assistants. Their schools, which are as much noted for the thoroughness of their education as they are for the wholesome spirit of their religious life, have been long established at several places in Europe. The head school is at Herrnhut, and others are at Neuwied, on the Rhine; Montmirail, on Lake Neuchâtel; Niesky, in Prussia; at Nyon, near Lausanne; and at Königsfeld, in the Black Forest.

To the visitor axious to see a Moravian settlement to its best advantage, no place offers greater attractions than Königsfeld. Remote from the world, it is a perfect model for its earnest, active life and at the same time its perfect peacefulness. Here the round of life goes on undisturbed from year to year. Such a thing as a law-suit is unheard of; all the inhabitants call themselves brothers or sisters, and are indeed such in the best and truest meaning of the words. All Moravian settlements have certain institutions for the well-being of their older members; houses where, at a very nominal rate, widows and impoverished old ladies can be boarded, and at the same time furnished with work suitable for their years. For the men there is a similar establishment. Even the inn is the property of the Brotherhood, who give to a salaried man the charge of the house and guests.

At Königsfeld, where the writer lived for a year, are two schools—one for boys, numbering about 80, the other for girls, 60. They are situated at opposite sides of the village, and much of the internal life of the Moravian Brotherhood may be seen from the method of conducting their schools. A long day of hard study is commenced at six o’clock with a reading out of the Bible, the same portion being read in all Moravian settlements all the world over at the same time. After a short prayer, all the boys and masters combined with great heartiness in singing a hymn of Luther or Zinzendorf’s. No day passed without a practice of an hour or so in miniature army drill—though this was, perhaps, more a German than a Moravian custom, as was also the very fair orchestra maintained by the little place. The day was ended as begun, with prayer and a hymn; but most of us thought that 8.30 was a somewhat early hour for bed, and we all agreed that 5.30 was far too early an hour at which to rise in the morning.

Nothing was more conspicuous in this school, as in all their other ones, than the beautiful spirit of gentleness and merciful justice, tempered by true brotherly sympathy, with which the boys of as many temperaments as nationalities were taught to live. They learned thus to have regard for the patriotic sentiments and so on of others, and, forgetting national animosities, to live in an atmosphere of real fraternity. Occasionally the most bitter feuds would arise between the banded members of different nationalities, but these were rare and of short duration. When football or rounders were rendered impossible modes of exercise by the state of the weather, the different divisions of the school went for long tramps in the forest, and explored many a lovely glade and deep recess that everywhere surrounded the village. The inmates of the girls’ school also indulged in this form of exercise; but if ever the contingent from the one met that from the other, the boys were instantly ordered “right about,” and it became a case of “distance lending enchantment to the view. ”

There are several feast days peculiar to the Church, which are of very ancient origin and of no little interest. Foremost among these is the agape, or love-feast of apostolic times. The whole community assembles in the little church-one of ultra Puritan plainness—and, after certain prayers and hymns, cups of very sweet tea are handed round to each member of the congregation in turn. This is repeated to those who desire a second cup, and then, in a huge basket, are distributed large currant buns, which are supposed to be eaten outside the church. The religious exercises of the meeting consist of extempore prayers, readings from the New Testament, and short addresses from one of the “Brothers”and the “Preacher”of the community. Several hymns are sung, and as all the women sit on one side and all the men on the other side of the church, with a broad aisle between them, the musical effect is very striking. There is no inharmonious mingling of voices, but two distinct volumes of sound; on one side the rich soprano notes of the women, and on the other the deep basses of the men. Music forms a considerable feature of this service. In the organ loft, trumpets and bugles mingle with violins and an occasional flute; and the effect of the whole on a stranger must be, to say the least, surprising. After this service the boys’ school were never allowed to rise and leave the church until the last of the girls had disappeared through their door on the other side of the building. This love-feast is observed about once in two or three months. In the Catacombs of Rome the agape is also represented as a somewhat substantial meal.

Another old custom is the pedilavium, or feet washing, but this is now very rarely if ever practised, though in certain circles it used formerly to be quite common.

Just before Christmas the schools were in the custom of observing a feast called the “gift feast,”when, in commemoration of the greatest Gift the world has ever known, the schools divided into pairs, and each member presented the other with a handsome present. At Easter, too, the whole community would proceed at sunrise to the cemetery, and there, with trumpets and choir, perform an inspiriting service of praise for the resurrection of our Lord.

Another old custom, now abolished, used to be the appointment of ministers by means of the “lot; ” marriages, too, were contracted in the same way.

So hurried a glimpse into the inner life of this most unuorldly little Church cannot do justice to the many virtues of its members, nor depict with any degree of fulness the other interesting characteristics of the Brotherhod. A visit to one of their settlements will give the visitor an insight into the working of a Church whose record and example should be an inspiration to mankind.

Algernon Blackwood

The Sherlock Holmes of Ghostland

Almost stealthily, out of the unknown, there has stepped into the foreground a new English writer who challenges comparison with Edgar Allan Poe and E. T. A. Hoffmann. Altho the author of eight or nine strange books, all written with a subtle but insistent suggestion of the uncanny, the name of Algernon Blackwood has been mentioned in the literary journals only in the last three or four years. The book that made his reputation, John Silence, Physician Extraordinary, has just been published in this country by Vaughan & Gomme, who intend to bring out his other books as well. Four or five of his books have already been published by Macmillan.

Modern science reaffirms many of the miracles of the Middle Ages. Obsession is a real thing to the modern psychologist. Spiritualism finds its exponents among the scientific leaders of the world. The transmutation of metals seems no longer an idle dream. Algernon Blackwood is the first writer who effectively avails himself of this renaissance of wonder in the light of modern science. He writes of the occult in terms of the psychology of the twentieth century. His hero, John Silence, is a Sherlock Holmes of the soul, hunting down the ghosts of prenatal obsession. And John Silence, by the testimony of the author’s other books, is Algernoon Blackwood himself. The secret lore of the Rosicrucians is at his fingers’ ends.

Familiar spirits, fire elementals, malignant forces of nature, the posthumous subsistence of desire, are the commonplaces of Blackwood’s fiction. In one of his stories, “A Psychic Invasion,” he has hit upon the ingenious device of bringing the souls of lower animals, a dog and a cat, into contact with the spirit world of evil. Neither Poe nor Hoffmann, both laureates of the occult, excel the masterful interpretation of animal psychology in Blackwood’s tale. He introduces here a note into fiction which is absolutely original. This overworked term, as a writer in the Evening Post remarks, is undoubtedly deserved by one who writes ghost stories like a poet. John Silence, the writer goes on to say, is a psychical doctor, and his cases are those involving the rescue of patients’ souls from the perils that beset them, not in the sense in which the alienist and the moralist would speak of psychic perils, but the dangers that lie beyond the normal threshold of our senses, a world of discarnate malignant spirits. We are concerned with haunted houses, devil-worship, sorceries, a form of material which, in unskilled hands, makes the worst of shilling shockers, but which, given artistic handling, becomes, as in the present volume, literature that tempts comparison with the best of the literature of fantasy and horror.

Blackwood, remarks a writer in the London Times Literary Supplement, is a master of the horrible—perhaps the terrible is a better word. “He writes beautiful English, he creates an atmosphere of suspense and terror that thrills the most jaded reader, his plots are strikingly novel, and he varies the exciting action with delightfully humorous dialog and descriptive passages of lyrical charm.” If he uses the occult terror as a charm, adds another British literary authority, The Athenaeum, in a review of Blackwood’s most recent book, Ten-Minute Stories, his reader is constantly reminded that “magic” is a child’s word for unknown law. He provides, in short, “a nursery for the teachable materialist.” Mr. Blackwood, Public Opinion (London) remarks, has the great gift of seeing the invisible and the intangible. The same paper goes on to say: “He is a man who lives on the hilltops, and loves the wind, and believes that the whole world is apant with life—closer than hands and feet—if we could but see it.”

Mr. Blackwood’s own career, according to The Bookman (New York), has been wildly adventurous. He was educated in a Moravian Brotherhood School in the Black Forest, which furnishes the background for one of his stories. He worked on a farm in Canada, edited a Methodist magazine, and superintended a dairy. His wanderings led him penniless to New York. He made a living by posing for Gibson, Cox and Zogbaum, went through the newspaper mill, working both on the Sun and the Times, and at one time was private secretary to Mr. James Speyer, the banker. Since 1905—he must be nearly forty now—Blackwood has taken up writing and traveling. He claims no abiding-place and no possessions, not even a room in London. All he owns, we are told, three trunks can hold, and snail-like he takes his home about with him—in the winter to Switzerland and Egypt; and in summer wandering somewhere—to the Caucasus (where he wrote The Centaur), to the Jura Mountains (Pan’s Garden and The Humane Chord), to the Dorsetshire pine woods of England (Education and Uncle Paul), and to the Alps (A Prisoner in Fairyland).

Current Opinion, May 1914

A Continuous Performance

While the Great Man was reading from his own Works to the ladies in the Duchess’s blue drawing-room, O’Malley slipped out unnoticed and made his way into the garden. The Great Man’s vanity, the collective pose of the adoring ladies, the elaborate parade and artifice of the human attitude generally, invited the sweetness of unadvertised open air. O’Malley, old poet whom lack of craft left inarticulate, so that he had never written a line, slipped past the roses towards the trees that fringed the ducal lawn. With him went an echo of the rotund period his exit had interrupted; a picture, too, of the human animal preening itself upon its hind legs in black coat and stiff white collar.

“That rubbidge!” came a gruff voice, as he passed a toolshed. “Why, I cleaned it up long ago—lars’ noight, if you want to know exact!” The under-gardener spat on his hands, as he poured out some aggrieved explanation to the Head. … The voices died away. O’Malley entered the stillness of the pinewood, where only the murmur of the summer wind was audible. “It’s rude of me,” he reflected: “possibly it’s affected. But, anyhow, my disappearance for half an hour won’t be noticed …” He flung himself down in a sunny patch where a meadow, swinging its flowers gaily in the breeze, ran round the little copse. An old thatched summerhouse, neglected, to judge by its state of decay, stood on his right. “I can slip in again before the end,” he finished his reflection, “and stand behind the chairs at the back. …”

He lay and watched the world of sun and shade about him, the unselfconscious, lovely wealth of colour, outline, graceful movement, mystery, and wonder. Not “wasting its sweetness on the desert air,” he chuckled, “because I’m here to see it all!”

A momentary memory rose to jar the enjoyment of watching a bee, both clumsy and adept, bear down a head of golden blossom into a lovely curve the wind at once made lovelier—a memory of the Great Man’s answer to a question recently: “They are tiresome, yes, I admit, these Readings; but a man must keep himself before the public, you know. One must adapt oneself to the Age one lives in. Money? Oh, no, of course not; yet—well, it does help one’s sales a bit. When I was lecturing in America last spring, my publisher told me …”

The bee, happily loaded, had issued from the golden bell, and O’Malley watched it bear the pollen unconsciously to another honeyed blossom, then, presently, rise into the air, take several circles in a spiral flight before, finally, it darted off swiftly in a line due south. For some minutes he watched other bees behave similarly, and excitement grew in him. It was with difficulty, then, that he caught some half-dozen, one after another, in his coloured handkerchief, released them, watched their spiral flight of observation, and, noting the line all took due south, resisted the desire to be up and after them himself—in a beeline to the nest in some old tree or broken wall. Many a wild-bees’ nest had he tracked in this way as a boy. The old, first wonder, the enthusiasm, with a touch of worship added now, came back upon him. The gathering of honey, the carrying of pollen, the infallible sense of direction to a nest perhaps a mile or two away … the Great Man’s words were all forgotten. In their place he heard the siren voice of Shelley:

“O follow, follow
Through the caverns hollow,
As the song floats thou pursue,
Where the wild-bee never flew …”

while, behind him, the pinewood murmured with its delicate music “like the farewell of ghosts,” as he turned to listen and to watch.

Nothing stirred, it seemed at first, so peaceful was the summer afternoon, but he remembered that Panthea, too, had heard this faint music in the Indian Caucasus—“kindling aeolian modulations in the waved air” ’—and had whispered her secret into Shelley’s ear. Leaning on one elbow motionless, merged in the scene by the imaginative sympathy of his poet’s heart, he watched and listened. … The ground, he saw, was alive with gentle, silent, unobtrusive movement, where half a million ants were busy upon their mysterious, communal purposes, while yet there was none to bid them labour, in ceaseless constructive activity that, beginning with sunrise, ends only with the dusk. He watched them lifting, pushing, piling up their burdens as though their lives depended on it, tiny, mighty engines of energy, each of which could drag 500 times its own weight, while a man, panting with effort, could barely move five of his own kind. The wonder of the insect world swept over him, and a fugitive memory flashed Blake’s picture, The Spirit of the Flea, across his mind, a flea that can leap a thousand times its own height … with the artist’s explanation that God made it tiny lest its power and bloodthirsty nature might destroy the planet. …

Plop! Something dropped upon the carpet of needles, and O’Malley, looking up, discerned two brilliant peeping eyes upon a branch, a bushy tail that twitched, and heard a squeaking voice that seemed to mock him. The squirrel was already making plans for its winter apartment, its winter store of food, its small head busily calculating months ahead. The human watcher moved cautiously to obtain a better view. Whisht! It was gone! An audacious leap through midair to another tree, perfect distribution of weight, consummate balance, precise relation between impetus and distance—powers no trained acrobat could ever hope to master. …

A few scraps of bark fell slowly downwards through the air, but the squirrel was safely perched on a tree some twenty yards away. One scrap of bark, it seemed, caught on a floating spider’s thread—a spider that unconsciously constructs a geometrical design a scholar can only make with the help of many instruments, and whose thread is the finest filament known, so that astronomers use it to map the heavens across the mouths of their huge telescopes. … No, it was neither bark nor spider’s web after all, but a fly, apparently stationary, yet actually moving its wings with such rapidity that no eye could distinguish the separate strokes. How many times per second O’Malley could not remember. He could flap his own arms three or four times per second—that he knew. … !

The minutes, meanwhile, were slipping away, while he watched a hundred marvels, unadvertised, performed daily, hourly, without Agents, without sales, without applause, mostly, indeed, without recognition. There, over a distant field, fell the tumbling plover under the very eye of a soaring hawk that made no attempt against them, knowing that their skill must ever elude its best endeavour. There, by chance, was the solitary wasp that stings exactly where paralysis, but not death, shall follow, so that its young shall feed on living food. There was the little trap-door spider, peeping, darting, cleverest of ingenious tiny carpenters. There was the beetle feigning death, as its enemy approached. There, again …

A new movement suddenly caught his eye, as he lay motionless, rapt with the wonder of it all. What was it? In the summerhouse, along the darkened floor, a rat—yes, a rat—was advancing slowly and with utmost caution. O’Malley watched keenly, as closely as he dared. The bright-eyed creature was dragging a wisp of straw along the decaying boards. Another rat, tentatively rather, as though with uncertain movements, seemed following it, its nose ever against the tip of the drawn straw. The first rat, evidently, was leading the way, showing its companion where to go. But why? Was it a game? Improving his position for observation with extreme caution, O’Malley discovered the meaning of the strange pantomime: the second rat was blind; its companion was leading it to food. …

O’Malley sprang up. The rats, the squirrel, the bees, ants, fly, wasp, spider, doubtless the plover and the distant hawk as well, all saw him move. The various processes of mysterious Nature, for the fraction of a second, paused. The perfect performers desired no audience, certainly no applause; recognition, praise, admiration, meant nothing to them. They were not even aware that they were wonderful. O’Malley left them. The Continuous Performance went on. He left Nature and returned to Human Nature. The gardeners, as he passed the toolshed, were still arguing together. In the Duchess’s blue drawing-room, when he stole back cautiously behind the chairs, the Great Man was still reading from His Own Works, to the assembled ladies, and some of the ladies were still listening, while all would presently tell him how wonderful he was.

Outside, in fragrant wood and meadow, the other performances, unadmired and unadvertised, went on as usual, and the Earth, nourishing all alike, turned calmly, faithfully, on her axis, continuing her journey at eighteen miles a second round a gigantic incandescent fire, some 93,000,000 miles away, that was too commonplace to call for remark as a rule, yet without which the entire Show would be snuffed out in a fraction of a second.

He got back just in time to be deafened by the applause, and to see the Great Man smile and bow.

A Descent Into Egypt

I

He was an accomplished, versatile man whom some called brilliant. Behind his talents lay a wealth of material that right selection could have lifted into genuine distinction. He did too many things, however, to excel in one, for a restless curiosity kept him ever on the move. George Isley was an able man. His short career in diplomacy proved it; yet, when he abandoned this for travel and exploration, no one thought it a pity. He would do big things in any line. He was merely finding himself.

Among the rolling stones of humanity a few acquire moss of considerable value. They are not necessarily shiftless; they travel light; the comfortable pockets in the game of life that attract the majority are too small to retain them; they are in and out again in a moment. The world says, “What a pity! They stick to nothing!” but the fact is that, like questing wild birds, they seek the nest they need. It is a question of values. They judge swiftly, change their line of flight, are gone, not even hearing the comment that they might have “retired with a pension.”

And to this homeless, questing type George Isley certainly belonged. He was by no means shiftless. He merely sought with insatiable yearning that soft particular nest where he could settle down in permanently. And to an accompaniment of sighs and regrets from his friends he found it; he found it, however, not in the present, but by retiring from the world “without a pension,” unclothed with honours and distinctions. He withdrew from the present and slipped softly back into a mighty Past where he belonged. Why; how; obeying what strange instincts—this remains unknown, deep secret of an inner life that found no resting-place in modern things. Such instincts are not disclosable in twentieth-century language, nor are the details of such a journey properly describable at all. Except by the few—poets, prophets, psychiatrists and the like—such experiences are dismissed with the neat museum label—“queer.”

So, equally, must the recorder of this experience share the honour of that little label—he who by chance witnessed certain external and visible signs of this inner and spiritual journey. There remains, nevertheless, the amazing reality of the experience; and to the recorder alone was some clue of interpretation possible, perhaps, because in himself also lay the lure, though less imperative, of a similar journey. At any rate the interpretation may be offered to the handful who realise that trains and motors are not the only means of travel left to our progressive race.

In his younger days I knew George Isley intimately. I know him now. But the George Isley I knew of old, the arresting personality with whom I travelled, climbed, explored, is no longer with us. He is not here. He disappeared—gradually—into the past. There is no George Isley. And that such an individuality could vanish, while still his outer semblance walks the familiar streets, normal apparently, and not yet fifty in the number of his years, seems a tale, though difficult, well worth the telling. For I witnessed the slow submergence. It was very gradual. I cannot pretend to understand the entire significance of it. There was something questionable and sinister in the business that offered hints of astonishing possibilities. Were there a corps of spiritual police, the matter might be partially cleared up, but since none of the churches have yet organised anything effective of this sort, one can only fall back upon variants of the blessed “Mesopotamia,” and whisper of derangement, and the like. Such labels, of course, explain as little as most other clichés in life. That well-groomed, soldierly figure strolling down Piccadilly, watching the Races, dining out—there is no derangement there. The face is not melancholy, the eye not wild; the gestures are quiet and the speech controlled. Yet the eye is empty, the face expressionless. Vacancy reigns there, provocative and significant. If not unduly noticeable, it is because the majority in life neither expect, nor offer, more.

At closer quarters you may think questioning things, or you may think—nothing; probably the latter. You may wonder why something continually expected does not make its appearance; and you may watch for the evidence of “personality” the general presentment of the man has led you to expect. Disappointed, therefore, you may certainly be; but I defy you to discover the smallest hint of mental disorder, and of derangement or nervous affliction, absolutely nothing. Before long, perhaps, you may feel you are talking with a dummy, some well-trained automaton, a nonentity devoid of spontaneous life; and afterwards you may find that memory fades rapidly away, as though no impression of any kind has really been made at all. All this, yes; but nothing pathological. A few may be stimulated by this startling discrepancy between promise and performance, but most, accustomed to accept face values, would say, “a pleasant fellow, but nothing in him much …” and an hour later forget him altogether.

For the truth is as you, perhaps, divined. You have been sitting beside no one, you have been talking to, looking at, listening to—no one. The intercourse has conveyed nothing that can waken human response in you, good, bad or indifferent. There is no George Isley. And the discovery, if you make it, will not even cause you to creep with the uncanniness of the experience, because the exterior is so wholly pleasing. George Isley today is a picture with no meaning in it that charms merely by the harmonious colouring of an inoffensive subject. He moves undiscovered in the little world of society to which he was born, secure in the groove first habit has made comfortably automatic for him. No one guesses; none, that is, but the few who knew him intimately in early life. And his wandering existence has scattered these; they have forgotten what he was. So perfect, indeed, is he in the manners of the commonplace fashionable man, that no woman in his “set” is aware that he differs from the type she is accustomed to. He turns a compliment with the accepted language of her textbook, motors, golfs and gambles in the regulation manner of his particular world. He is an admirable, perfect automaton. He is nothing. He is a human shell.

II

The name of George Isley had been before the public for some years when, after a considerable interval, we met again in a hotel in Egypt, I for my health, he for I knew not what—at first. But I soon discovered: archaeology and excavation had taken hold of him, though he had gone so quietly about it that no one seemed to have heard. I was not sure that he was glad to see me, for he had first withdrawn, annoyed, it seemed, at being discovered, but later, as though after consideration, had made tentative advances. He welcomed me with a curious gesture of the entire body that seemed to shake himself free from something that had made him forget my identity. There was pathos somewhere in his attitude, almost as though he asked for sympathy. “I’ve been out here, off and on, for the last three years,” he told me, after describing something of what he had been doing. “I find it the most repaying hobby in the world. It leads to a reconstruction—an imaginative reconstruction, of course, I mean—of an enormous thing the world had entirely lost. A very gorgeous, stimulating hobby, believe me, and a very entic—” he quickly changed the word—“exacting one indeed.”

I remember looking him up and down with astonishment. There was a change in him, a lack; a note was missing in his enthusiasm, a colour in the voice, a quality in his manner. The ingredients were not mixed quite as of old. I did not bother him with questions, but I noted thus at the very first a subtle alteration. Another facet of the man presented itself. Something that had been independent and aggressive was replaced by a certain emptiness that invited sympathy. Even in his physical appearance the change was manifested—this odd suggestion of lessening. I looked again more closely. Lessening was the word. He had somehow dwindled. It was startling, vaguely unpleasant too.

The entire subject, as usual, was at his fingertips; he knew all the important men; and had spent money freely on his hobby. I laughed, reminding him of his remark that Egypt had no attractions for him, owing to the organised advertisement of its somewhat theatrical charms. Admitting his error with a gesture, he brushed the objection easily aside. His manner, and a certain glow that rose about his atmosphere as he answered, increased my first astonishment. His voice was significant and suggestive. “Come out with me,” he said in a low tone, “and see how little the tourists matter, how inappreciable the excavation is compared to what remains to be done, how gigantic”—he emphasised the word impressively—“the scope for discovery remains.” He made a movement with his head and shoulders that conveyed a sense of the prodigious, for he was of massive build, his cast of features stern, and his eyes, set deep into the face, shone past me with a sombre gleam in them I did not quite account for. It was the voice, however, that brought the mystery in. It vibrated somewhere below the actual sound of it. “Egypt,” he continued—and so gravely that at first I made the mistake of thinking he chose the curious words on purpose to produce a theatrical effect—“that has enriched her blood with the pageant of so many civilisations, that has devoured Persians, Greeks and Romans, Saracens and Mamelukes, a dozen conquests and invasions besides—what can mere tourists or explorers matter to her? The excavators scratch their skin and dig up mummies; and as for tourists!”—he laughed contemptuously—“flies that settle for a moment on her covered face, to vanish at the first signs of heat! Egypt is not even aware of them. The real Egypt lies underground in darkness. Tourists must have light, to be seen as well as to see. And the diggers—!”

He paused, smiling with something between pity and contempt I did not quite appreciate, for, personally, I felt a great respect for the tireless excavators. And then he added, with a touch of feeling in his tone as though he had a grievance against them, and had not also “dug” himself, “Men who uncover the dead, restore the temples, and reconstruct a skeleton, thinking they have read its beating heart. …” He shrugged his great shoulders, and the rest of the sentence may have been but the protest of a man in defence of his own hobby, but that there seemed an undue earnestness and gravity about it that made me wonder more than ever. He went on to speak of the strangeness of the land as a mere ribbon of vegetation along the ancient river, the rest all ruins, desert, sun-drenched wilderness of death, yet so breakingly alive with wonder, power and a certain disquieting sense of deathlessness. There seemed, for him, a revelation of unusual spiritual kind in this land where the Past survived so potently. He spoke almost as though it obliterated the Present.

Indeed, the hint of something solemn behind his words made it difficult for me to keep up the conversation, and the pause that presently came I filled in with some word of questioning surprise, which yet, I think, was chiefly in concurrence. I was aware of some big belief in him, some enveloping emotion that escaped my grasp. Yet, though I did not understand, his great mood swept me. … His voice lowered, then, as he went on to mention temples, tombs and deities, details of his own discoveries and of their effect upon him, but to this I listened with half an ear, because in the unusual language he had first made use of I detected this other thing that stirred my curiosity more—stirred it uncomfortably.

“Then the spell,” I asked, remembering the effect of Egypt upon myself two years before, “has worked upon you as upon most others, only with greater power?”

He looked hard at me a moment, signs of trouble showing themselves faintly in his rugged, interesting face. I think he wanted to say more than he could bring himself to confess. He hesitated.

“I’m only glad,” he replied after a pause, “it didn’t get hold of me earlier in life. It would have absorbed me. I should have lost all other interests. Now,”—that curious look of helplessness, of asking sympathy, flitted like a shadow through his eyes—“now that I’m on the decline … it matters less.”

On the decline! I cannot imagine by what blundering I missed this chance he never offered again; somehow or other the singular phrase passed unnoticed at the moment, and only came upon me with its full significance later when it was too awkward to refer to it. He tested my readiness to help, to sympathise, to share his inner life. I missed the clue. For, at the moment, a more practical consideration interested me in his language. Being of those who regretted that he had not excelled by devoting his powers to a single object, I shrugged my shoulders. He caught my meaning instantly. Oh, he was glad to talk. He felt the possibility of my sympathy underneath, I think.

“No, no, you take me wrongly there,” he said with gravity. “What I mean—and I ought to know if anyone does!—is that while most countries give, others take away. Egypt changes you. No one can live here and remain exactly what he was before.”

This puzzled me. It startled, too, again. His manner was so earnest. “And Egypt, you mean, is one of the countries that take away?” I asked. The strange idea unsettled my thoughts a little.

“First takes away from you,” he replied, “but in the end takes you away. Some lands enrich you,” he went on, seeing that I listened, “while others impoverish. From India, Greece, Italy, all ancient lands, you return with memories you can use. From Egypt you return with—nothing. Its splendour stupefies; it’s useless. There is a change in your inmost being, an emptiness, an unaccountable yearning, but you find nothing that can fill the lack you’re conscious of. Nothing comes to replace what has gone. You have been drained.”

I stared; but I nodded a general acquiescence. Of a sensitive, artistic temperament this was certainly true, though by no means the superficial and generally accepted verdict. The majority imagine that Egypt has filled them to the brim. I took his deeper reading of the facts. I was aware of an odd fascination in his idea.

“Modern Egypt,” he continued, “is, after all, but a trick of civilisation,” and there was a kind of breathlessness in his measured tone, “but ancient Egypt lies waiting, hiding, underneath. Though dead, she is amazingly alive. And you feel her touching you. She takes from you. She enriches herself. You return from Egypt—less than you were before.”

What came over my mind is hard to say. Some touch of visionary imagination burned its flaming path across my mind. I thought of some old Grecian hero speaking of his delicious battle with the gods—battle in which he knew he must be worsted, but yet in which he delighted because at death his spirit would join their glorious company beyond this world. I was aware, that is to say, of resignation as well as resistance in him. He already felt the effortless peace which follows upon long, unequal battling, as of a man who has fought the rapids with a strain beyond his strength, then sinks back and goes with the awful mass of water smoothly and indifferently—over the quiet fall.

Yet, it was not so much his words which clothed picturesquely an undeniable truth, as the force of conviction that drove behind them, shrouding my mind with mystery and darkness. His eyes, so steadily holding mine, were lit, I admit, yet they were calm and sane as those of a doctor discussing the symptoms of that daily battle to which we all finally succumb. This analogy occurred to me.

“There is”—I stammered a little, faltering in my speech—“an incalculable element in the country … somewhere, I confess. You put it—rather strongly, though, don’t you?”

He answered quietly, moving his eyes from my face towards the window that framed the serene and exquisite sky towards the Nile.

“The real, invisible Egypt,” he murmured, “I do find rather—strong. I find it difficult to deal with. You see,” and he turned towards me, smiling like a tired child, “I think the truth is that Egypt deals with me.”

“It draws—” I began, then started as he interrupted me at once.

“Into the Past.” He uttered the little word in a way beyond me to describe. There came a flood of glory with it, a sense of peace and beauty, of battles over and of rest attained. No saint could have brimmed “Heaven” with as much passionately enticing meaning. He went willingly, prolonging the struggle merely to enjoy the greater relief and joy of the consummation.

For again he spoke as though a struggle were in progress in his being. I got the impression that he somewhere wanted help. I understood the pathetic quality I had vaguely discerned already. His character naturally was so strong and independent. It now seemed weaker, as though certain fibres had been drawn out. And I understood then that the spell of Egypt, so lightly chattered about in its sensational aspect, so rarely known in its naked power, the nameless, creeping influence that begins deep below the surface and thence sends delicate tendrils outwards, was in his blood. I, in my untaught ignorance, had felt it too; it is undeniable; one is aware of unaccountable, queer things in Egypt; even the utterly prosaic feel them. Dead Egypt is marvellously alive. …

I glanced past him out of the big windows where the desert glimmered in its featureless expanse of yellow leagues, two monstrous pyramids signalling from across the Nile, and for a moment—inexplicably, it seemed to me afterwards—I lost sight of my companion’s stalwart figure that was yet so close before my eyes. He had risen from his chair; he was standing near me; yet my sight missed him altogether. Something, dim as a shadow, faint as a breath of air, rose up and bore my thoughts away, obliterating vision too. I forgot for a moment who I was; identity slipped from me. Thought, sight, feeling, all sank away into the emptiness of those sunbaked sands, sank, as it were, into nothingness, caught away from the Present, enticed, absorbed. … And when I looked back again to answer him, or rather to ask what his curious words could mean—he was no longer there. More than surprised—for there was something of shock in the disappearance—I turned to search. I had not seen him go. He had stolen from my side so softly, slipped away silently, mysteriously, and—so easily. I remember that a faint shiver ran down my back as I realised that I was alone.

Was it that, momentarily, I had caught a reflex of his state of mind? Had my sympathy induced in myself an echo of what he experienced in full—a going backwards, a loss of present vigour, the enticing, subtle draw of those immeasurable sands that hide the living dead from the interruptions of the careless living … ?

I sat down to reflect and, incidentally, to watch the magnificence of the sunset; and the thing he had said returned upon me with insistent power, ringing like distant bells within my mind. His talk of the tombs and temples passed, but this remained. It stimulated oddly. His talk, I remembered, had always excited curiosity in this way. Some countries give, while others take away. What did he mean precisely? What had Egypt taken away from him? And I realised more definitely that something in him was missing, something he possessed in former years that was now no longer there. He had grown shadowy already in my thoughts. The mind searched keenly, but in vain … and after some time I left my chair and moved over to another window, aware that a vague discomfort stirred within me that involved uneasiness—for him. I felt pity. But behind the pity was an eager, absorbing curiosity as well. He seemed receding curiously into misty distance, and the strong desire leaped in me to overtake, to travel with him into some vanished splendour that he had rediscovered. The feeling was a most remarkable one, for it included yearning—the yearning for some nameless, forgotten loveliness the world has lost. It was in me too.

At the approach of twilight the mind loves to harbour shadows. The room, empty of guests, was dark behind me; darkness, too, was creeping across the desert like a veil, deepening the serenity of its grim, unfeatured face. It turned pale with distance; the whole great sheet of it went rustling into night. The first stars peeped and twinkled, hanging loosely in the air as though they could be plucked like golden berries; and the sun was already below the Libyan horizon, where gold and crimson faded through violet into blue. I stood watching this mysterious Egyptian dusk, while an eerie glamour seemed to bring the incredible within uneasy reach of the half-faltering senses. … And suddenly the truth dropped into me. Over George Isley, over his mind and energies, over his thoughts and over his emotions too, a kind of darkness was also slowly creeping. Something in him had dimmed, yet not with age; it had gone out. Some inner night, stealing over the Present, obliterated it. And yet he looked towards the dawn. Like the Egyptian monuments his eyes turned—eastwards.

And so it came to me that what he had lost was personal ambition. He was glad, he said, that these Egyptian studies had not caught him earlier in life; the language he made use of was peculiar: “Now I am on the decline it matters less.” A slight foundation, no doubt, to build conviction on, and yet I felt sure that I was partly right. He was fascinated, but fascinated against his will. The Present in him battled against the Past. Still fighting, he had yet lost hope. The desire not to change was now no longer in him. …

I turned away from the window so as not to see that grey, encroaching desert, for the discovery produced a certain agitation in me. Egypt seemed suddenly a living entity of enormous power. She stirred about me. She was stirring now. This flat and motionless land pretending it had no movement, was actually busy with a million gestures that came creeping round the heart. She was reducing him. Already from the complex texture of his personality she had drawn one vital thread that in its relation to the general woof was of central importance—ambition. The mind chose the simile; but in my heart where thought fluttered in singular distress, another suggested itself as truer. “Thread” changed to “artery.” I turned quickly and went up to my room where I could be alone. The idea was somewhere ghastly.

III

Yet, while dressing for dinner, the idea exfoliated as only a living thing exfoliates. I saw in George Isley this great question mark that had not been there formerly. All have, of course, some question mark, and carry it about, though with most it rarely becomes visible until the end. With him it was plainly visible in his atmosphere at the heyday of his life. He wore it like a fine curved scimitar above his head. So full of life, he yet seemed willingly dead. For, though imagination sought every possible explanation, I got no further than the somewhat negative result—that a certain energy, wholly unconnected with mere physical health, had been withdrawn. It was more than ambition, I think, for it included intention, desire, self-confidence as well. It was life itself. He was no longer in the Present. He was no longer here.

“Some countries give while others take away. … I find Egypt difficult to deal with. I find it …” and then that simple, uncomplex adjective—“strong.” In memory and experience the entire globe was mapped for him; it remained for Egypt, then, to teach him this marvellous new thing. But not Egypt of today; it was vanished Egypt that had robbed him of his strength. He had described it as underground, hidden, waiting. … I was again aware of a faint shuddering—as though something crept secretly from my inmost heart to share the experience with him, and as though my sympathy involved a willing consent that this should be so. With sympathy there must always be a shedding of the personal self; each time I felt this sympathy, it seemed that something left me. I thought in circles, arriving at no definite point where I could rest and say “that’s it; I understand.” The giving attitude of a country was easily comprehensible; but this idea of robbery, of deprivation baffled me. An obscure alarm took hold of me—for myself as well as for him.

At dinner, where he invited me to his table, the impression passed off a good deal, however, and I convicted myself of a woman’s exaggeration; yet, as we talked of many a day’s adventure together in other lands, it struck me that we oddly left the present out. We ignored today. His thoughts, as it were, went most easily backwards. And each adventure led, as by its own natural weight and impetus, towards one thing—the enormous glory of a vanished age. Ancient Egypt was “home” in this mysterious game life played with death. The specific gravity of his being, to say nothing for the moment of my own, had shifted lower, farther off, backwards and below, or as he put it—underground. The sinking sensation I experienced was of a literal kind. …

And so I found myself wondering what had led him to this particular hotel. I had come out with an affected organ the specialist promised me would heal in the marvellous air of Helouan, but it was queer that my companion also should have chosen it. Its clientele was mostly invalid, German and Russian invalid at that. The Management set its face against the lighter, gayer side of life that hotels in Egypt usually encourage eagerly. It was a true rest-house, a place of repose and leisure, a place where one could remain undiscovered and unknown. No English patronised it. One might easily—the idea came unbidden, suddenly—hide in it.

“Then you’re doing nothing just now,” I asked, “in the way of digging? No big expeditions or excavating at the moment?”

“I’m recuperating,” he answered carelessly. “I’ve have had two years up at the Valley of the Kings, and overdid it rather. But I’m by way of working at a little thing near here across the Nile.” And he pointed in the direction of Sakkhâra, where the huge Memphian cemetery stretches underground from the Dachûr Pyramids to the Giza monsters, four miles lower down. “There’s a matter of a hundred years in that alone!”

“You must have accumulated a mass of interesting material. I suppose later you’ll make use of it—a book or—”

His expression stopped me—that strange look in the eyes that had stirred my first uneasiness. It was as if something struggled up a moment, looked bleakly out upon the present, then sank away again.

“More,” he answered listlessly, “than I can ever use. It’s much more likely to use me.” He said it hurriedly, looking over his shoulder as though someone might be listening, then smiled significantly, bringing his eyes back upon my own again. I told him that he was far too modest. “If all the excavators thought like that,” I added, “we ignorant ones should suffer.” I laughed, but the laughter was only on my lips.

He shook his head indifferently. “They do their best; they do wonders,” he replied, making an indescribable gesture as though he withdrew willingly from the topic altogether, yet could not quite achieve it. “I know their books; I know the writers too—of various nationalities.” He paused a moment, and his eyes turned grave. “I cannot understand quite—how they do it,” he added half below his breath.

“The labour, you mean? The strain of the climate, and so forth?” I said this purposely, for I knew quite well he meant another thing. The way he looked into my face, however, disturbed me so that I believe I visibly started. Something very deep in me sat up alertly listening, almost on guard.

“I mean,” he replied, “that they must have uncommon powers of resistance.”

There! He had used the very word that had been hiding in me! “It puzzles me,” he went on, “for, with one exception, they are not unusual men. In the way of gifts—oh yes. It’s in the way of resistance and protection that I mean. Self-protection,” he added with emphasis.

It was the way he said “resistance” and “self-protection” that sent a touch of cold through me. I learned later that he himself had made surprising discoveries in these two years, penetrating closer to the secret life of ancient sacerdotal Egypt than any of his predecessors or co-labourers—then, inexplicably, had ceased. But this was told to me afterwards and by others. At the moment I was only conscious of this odd embarrassment. I did not understand, yet felt that he touched upon something intimately personal to himself. He paused, expecting me to speak.

“Egypt, perhaps, merely pours through them,” I ventured. “They give out mechanically, hardly realising how much they give. They report facts devoid of interpretation. Whereas with you it’s the actual spirit of the past that is discovered and laid bare. You live it. You feel old Egypt and disclose her. That divining faculty was always yours—uncannily, I used to think.”

The flash of his sombre eyes betrayed that my aim was singularly good. It seemed a third had silently joined our little table in the corner. Something intruded, evoked by the power of what our conversation skirted but ever left unmentioned. It was huge and shadowy; it was also watchful. Egypt came gliding, floating up beside us. I saw her reflected in his face and gaze. The desert slipped in through walls and ceiling, rising from beneath our feet, settling about us, listening, peering, waiting. The strange obsession was sudden and complete. The gigantic scale of her swam in among the very pillars, arches, and windows of that modern dining-room. I felt against my skin the touch of chilly air that sunlight never reaches, stealing from beneath the granite monoliths. Behind it came the stifling breath of the heated tombs, of the Serapeum, of the chambers and corridors in the pyramids. There was a rustling as of myriad footsteps far away, and as of sand the busy winds go shifting through the ages. And in startling contrast to this impression of prodigious size, Isley himself wore suddenly an air of strangely dwindling. For a second he shrank visibly before my very eyes. He was receding. His outline seemed to retreat and lessen, as though he stood to the waist in what appeared like flowing mist, only his head and shoulders still above the ground. Far, far away I saw him.

It was a vivid inner picture that I somehow transferred objectively. It was a dramatised sensation, of course. His former phrase “now that I am declining” flashed back upon me with sharp discomfort. Again, perhaps, his state of mind was reflected into me by some emotional telepathy. I waited, conscious of an almost sensible oppression that would not lift. It seemed an age before he spoke, and when he did there was the tremor of feeling in his voice he sought nevertheless to repress. I kept my eyes on the table for some reason. But I listened intently.

“It’s you that have the divining faculty, not I,” he said, an odd note of distance even in his tone, yet a resonance as though it rose up between reverberating walls. “There is, I believe, something here that resents too close inquiry, or rather that resists discovery—almost—takes offence.”

I looked up quickly, then looked down again. It was such a startling thing to hear on the lips of a modern Englishman. He spoke lightly, but the expression of his face belied the careless tone. There was no mockery in those earnest eyes, and in the hushed voice was a little creeping sound that gave me once again the touch of gooseflesh. The only word I can find is “subterranean”: all that was mental in him had sunk, so that he seemed speaking underground, head and shoulders alone visible. The effect was almost ghastly.

“Such extraordinary obstacles are put in one’s way,” he went on, “when the prying gets too close to the—reality; physical, external obstacles, I mean. Either that, or—the mind loses its assimilative faculties. One or other happens—” his voice died down into a whisper—“and discovery ceases of its own accord.”

The same minute, then, he suddenly raised himself like a man emerging from a tomb; he leaned across the table; he made an effort of some violent internal kind, on the verge, I fully believe, of a pregnant personal statement. There was confession in his attitude; I think he was about to speak of his work at Thebes and the reason for its abrupt cessation. For I had the feeling of one about to hear a weighty secret, the responsibility unwelcome. This uncomfortable emotion rose in me, as I raised my eyes to his somewhat unwillingly, only to find that I was wholly at fault. It was not me he was looking at. He was staring past me in the direction of the wide, unshuttered windows. The expression of yearning was visible in his eyes again. Something had stopped his utterance.

And instinctively I turned and saw what he saw. So far as external details were concerned, at least, I saw it.

Across the glare and glitter of the uncompromising modern dining-room, past crowded tables, and over the heads of Germans feeding unpicturesquely, I saw—the moon. Her reddish disc, hanging unreal and enormous, lifted the spread sheet of desert till it floated off the surface of the world. The great window faced the east, where the Arabian desert breaks into a ruin of gorges, cliffs, and flat-topped ridges; it looked unfriendly, ominous, with danger in it; unlike the serener sand-dunes of the Libyan desert, there lay both menace and seduction behind its flood of shadows. And the moonlight emphasised this aspect: its ghostly desolation, its cruelty, its bleak hostility, turning it murderous. For no river sweetens this Arabian desert; instead of sandy softness, it has fangs of limestone rock, sharp and aggressive. Across it, just visible in the moonlight as a thread of paler grey, the old camel-trail to Suez beckoned faintly. And it was this that he was looking at so intently.

It was, I know, a theatrical stage-like glimpse, yet in it a seductiveness most potent. “Come out,” it seemed to whisper, “and taste my awful beauty. Come out and lose yourself, and die. Come out and follow my moonlit trail into the Past … where there is peace and immobility and silence. My kingdom is unchanging underground. Come down, come softly, come through sandy corridors below this tinsel of your modern world. Come back, come down into my golden past. …”

A poignant desire stole through my heart on moonlit feet; I was personally conscious of a keen yearning to slip away in unresisting obedience. For it was uncommonly impressive, this sudden, haunting glimpse of the world outside. The hairy foreigners, uncouthly garbed, all busily eating in full electric light, provided a sensational contrast of emphatically distressing kind. A touch of what is called unearthly hovered about that distance through the window. There was weirdness in it. Egypt looked in upon us. Egypt watched and listened, beckoning through the moonlit windows of the heart to come and find her. Mind and imagination might flounder as they pleased, but something of this kind happened undeniably, whether expression in language fails to hold the truth or not. And George Isley, aware of being seen, looked straight into the awful visage—fascinated.

Over the bronze of his skin there stole a shade of grey. My own feeling of enticement grew—the desire to go out into the moonlight, to leave my kind and wander blindly through the desert, to see the gorges in their shining silver, and taste the keenness of the cool, sharp air. Further than this with me it did not go, but that my companion felt the bigger, deeper draw behind this surface glamour, I have no reasonable doubt. For a moment, indeed, I thought he meant to leave the table; he had half risen in his chair; it seemed he struggled and resisted—and then his big frame subsided again; he sat back; he looked, in the attitude his body took, less impressive, smaller, actually shrunken into the proportions of some minuter scale. It was as though something in that second had been drawn out of him, decreasing even his physical appearance. The voice, when he spoke presently with a touch of resignation, held a lifeless quality as though deprived of virile timbre.

“It’s always there,” he whispered, half collapsing back into his chair, “it’s always watching, waiting, listening. Almost like a monster of the fables, isn’t it? It makes no movement of its own, you see. It’s far too strong for that. It just hangs there, half in the air and half upon the earth—a gigantic web. Its prey flies into it. That’s Egypt all over. D’you feel like that too, or does it seem to you just imaginative rubbish? To me it seems that she just waits her time; she gets you quicker that way; in the end you’re bound to go.”

“There’s power certainly,” I said after a moment’s pause to collect my wits, my distress increased by the morbidness of his simile. “For some minds there may be a kind of terror too—for weak temperaments that are all imagination.” My thoughts were scattered, and I could not readily find good words. “There is startling grandeur in a sight like that, for instance,” and I pointed to the window. “You feel drawn—as if you simply had to go.” My mind still buzzed with his curious words, “In the end you’re bound to go.” It betrayed his heart and soul. “I suppose a fly does feel drawn,” I added, “or a moth to the destroying flame. Or is it just unconscious on their part?”

He jerked his big head significantly. “Well, well,” he answered, “but the fly isn’t necessarily weak, or the moth misguided. Over-adventurous, perhaps, yet both obedient to the laws of their respective beings. They get warnings too—only, when the moth wants to know too much, the fire stops it. Both flame and spider enrich themselves by understanding the natures of their prey; and fly and moth return again and again until this is accomplished.”

Yet George Isley was as sane as the head waiter who, noticing our interest in the window, came up just then and enquired whether we felt a draught and would prefer it closed. Isley, I realised, was struggling to express a passionate state of soul for which, owing to its rarity, no adequate expression lies at hand. There is a language of the mind, but there is none as yet of the spirit. I felt ill at ease. All this was so foreign to the wholesome, strenuous personality of the man as I remembered it.

“But, my dear fellow,” I stammered, “aren’t you giving poor old Egypt a bad name she hardly deserves? I feel only the amazing strength and beauty of it; awe, if you like, but none of this resentment you so mysteriously hint at.”

“You understand, for all that,” he answered quietly; and again he seemed on the verge of some significant confession that might ease his soul. My uncomfortable emotion grew. Certainly he was at high pressure somewhere. “And, if necessary, you could help. Your sympathy, I mean, is a help already.” He said it half to himself and in a suddenly lowered tone again.

“A help!” I gasped. “My sympathy! Of course, if—”

“A witness,” he murmured, not looking at me, “someone who understands, yet does not think me mad.”

There was such appeal in his voice that I felt ready and eager to do anything to help him. Our eyes met, and my own tried to express this willingness in me; but what I said I hardly know, for a cloud of confusion was on my mind, and my speech went fumbling like a schoolboy’s. I was more than disconcerted. Through this bewilderment, then, I just caught the tail-end of another sentence in which the words “relief it is to have … someone to hold to … when the disappearance comes …” sounded like voices heard in dream. But I missed the complete phrase and shrank from asking him to repeat it.

Some sympathetic answer struggled to my lips, though what it was I know not. The thing I murmured, however, seemed apparently well chosen. He leaned across and laid his big hand a moment on my own with eloquent pressure. It was cold as ice. A look of gratitude passed over his sunburned features. He sighed. And we left the table then and passed into the inner smoking-room for coffee—a room whose windows gave upon columned terraces that allowed no view of the encircling desert. He led the conversation into channels less personal and, thank heaven, less intensely emotional and mysterious. What we talked about I now forget; it was interesting but in another key altogether. His old charm and power worked; the respect I had always felt for his character and gifts returned in force, but it was the pity I now experienced that remained chiefly in my mind. For this change in him became more and more noticeable. He was less impressive, less convincing, less suggestive. His talk, though so knowledgeable, lacked that spiritual quality that drives home. He was uncannily less real. And I went up to bed, uneasy and disturbed. “It is not age,” I said to myself, “and assuredly it is not death he fears, although he spoke of disappearance. It is mental—in the deepest sense. It is what religious people would call soul. Something is happening to his soul.”

IV

And this word “soul” remained with me to the end. Egypt was taking his soul away into the Past. What was of value in him went willingly; the rest, some lesser aspect of his mind and character, resisted, holding to the present. A struggle, therefore, was involved. But this was being gradually obliterated too.

How I arrived gaily at this monstrous conclusion seems to me now a mystery; but the truth is that from a conversation one brings away a general idea that is larger than the words actually heard and spoken. I have reported, naturally, but a fragment of what passed between us in language, and of what was suggested—by gesture, expression, silence—merely perhaps a hint. I can only assert that this troubling verdict remained a conviction in my mind. It came upstairs with me; it watched and listened by my side. That mysterious Third evoked in our conversation was bigger than either of us separately; it might be called the spirit of ancient Egypt, or it might be called with equal generalisation, the Past. This Third, at any rate, stood by me, whispering this astounding thing. I went out on to my little balcony to smoke a pipe and enjoy the comforting presence of the stars before turning in. It came out with me. It was everywhere. I heard the barking of dogs, the monotonous beating of a distant drum towards Bedraschien, the singsong voices of the natives in their booths and down the dim-lit streets. I was aware of this invisible Third behind all these familiar sounds. The enormous night-sky, drowned in stars, conveyed it too. It was in the breath of chilly wind that whispered round the walls, and it brooded everywhere above the sleepless desert. I was alone as little as though George Isley stood beside me in person—and at that moment a moving figure caught my eye below. My window was on the sixth story, but there was no mistaking the tall and soldierly bearing of the man who was strolling past the hotel. George Isley was going slowly out into the desert.

There was actually nothing unusual in the sight. It was only ten o’clock; but for doctor’s orders I might have been doing the same myself. Yet, as I leaned over the dizzy ledge and watched him, a chill struck through me, and a feeling nothing could justify, nor pages of writing describe, rose up and mastered me. His words at dinner came back with curious force. Egypt lay round him, motionless, a vast grey web. His feet were caught in it. It quivered. The silvery meshes in the moonlight announced the fact from Memphis up to Thebes, across the Nile, from underground Sakkhâra to the Valley of the Kings. A tremor ran over the entire desert, and again, as in the dining-room, the leagues of sand went rustling. It seemed to me that I caught him in the act of disappearing.

I realised in that moment the haunting power of this mysterious still atmosphere which is Egypt, and some magical emanation of its mighty past broke over me suddenly like a wave. Perhaps in that moment I felt what he himself felt; the withdrawing suction of the huge spent wave swept something out of me into the past with it. An indescribable yearning drew something living from my heart, something that longed with a kind of burning, searching sweetness for a glory of spiritual passion that was gone. The pain and happiness of it were more poignant than may be told, and my present personality—some vital portion of it, at any rate—wilted before the power of its enticement.

I stood there, motionless as stone, and stared. Erect and steady, knowing resistance vain, eager to go yet striving to remain, and half with an air of floating off the ground, he went towards the pale grey thread which was the track to Suez and the far Red Sea. There came upon me this strange, deep sense of pity, pathos, sympathy that was beyond all explanation, and mysterious as a pain in dreams. For a sense of his awful loneliness stole into me, a loneliness nothing on this earth could possibly relieve. Robbed of the Present, he sought this chimera of his soul, an unreal Past. Not even the calm majesty of this exquisite Egyptian night could soothe the dream away; the peace and silence were marvellous, the sweet perfume of the desert air intoxicating; but all these intensified it only.

And though at a loss to explain my own emotion, its poignancy was so real that a sigh escaped me and I felt that tears lay not too far away. I watched him, yet felt I had no right to watch. Softly I drew back from the window with the sensation of eavesdropping upon his privacy; but before I did so I had seen his outline melt away into the dim world of sand that began at the very walls of the hotel. He wore a cloak of green that reached down almost to his heels, and its colour blended with the silvery surface of the desert’s dark sea-tint. This sheen first draped and then concealed him. It covered him with a fold of its mysterious garment that, without seam or binding, veiled Egypt for a thousand leagues. The desert took him. Egypt caught him in her web. He was gone.

Sleep for me just then seemed out of the question. The change in him made me feel less sure of myself. To see him thus invertebrate shocked me. I was aware that I had nerves.

For a long time I sat smoking by the window, my body weary, but my imagination irritatingly stimulated. The big sign-lights of the hotel went out; window after window closed below me; the electric standards in the streets were already extinguished; and Helouan looked like a child’s white blocks scattered in ruin upon the nursery carpet. It seemed so wee upon the vast expanse. It lay in a twinkling pattern, like a cluster of glowworms dropped into a negligible crease of the tremendous desert. It peeped up at the stars, a little frightened.

The night was very still. There hung an enormous brooding beauty everywhere, a hint of the sinister in it that only the brilliance of the blazing stars relieved. Nothing really slept. Grouped here and there at intervals about this dun-coloured world stood the everlasting watchers in solemn, tireless guardianship—the soaring Pyramids, the Sphinx, the grim Colossi, the empty temples, the long-deserted tombs. The mind was aware of them, stationed like sentries through the night. “This is Egypt; you are actually in Egypt,” whispered the silence. “Eight thousand years of history lie fluttering outside your window. She lies there underground, sleepless, mighty, deathless, not to be trifled with. Beware! Or she will change you too!”

My imagination offered this hint: Egypt is difficult to realise. It remains outside the mind, a fabulous, half-legendary idea. So many enormous elements together refuse to be assimilated; the heart pauses, asking for time and breath; the senses reel a little; and in the end a mental torpor akin to stupefaction creeps upon the brain. With a sigh the struggle is abandoned and the mind surrenders to Egypt on her own terms. Alone the diggers and archaeologists, confined to definite facts, offer successful resistance. My friend’s use of the words “resistance” and “protection” became clearer to me. While logic halted, intuition fluttered round this clue to the solution of the influences at work. George Isley realised Egypt more than most—but as she had been.

And I recalled its first effect upon myself, and how my mind had been unable to cope with the memory of it afterwards. There had come to its summons a colossal medley, a gigantic, coloured blur that merely bewildered. Only lesser points lodged comfortably in the heart. I saw a chaotic vision: sands drenched in dazzling light, vast granite aisles, stupendous figures that stared unblinking at the sun, a shining river and a shadowy desert, both endless as the sky, mountainous pyramids and gigantic monoliths, armies of heads, of paws, of faces—all set to a scale of size that was prodigious. The items stunned; the composite effect was too unwieldy to be grasped. Something that blazed with splendour rolled before the eyes, too close to be seen distinctly—at the same time very distant—unrealised.

Then, with the passing of the weeks, it slowly stirred to life. It had attacked unseen; its grip was quite tremendous; yet it could be neither told, nor painted, nor described. It flamed up unexpectedly—in the foggy London streets, at the Club, in the theatre. A sound recalled the street-cries of the Arabs, a breath of scented air brought back the heated sand beyond the palm groves. Up rose the huge Egyptian glamour, transforming common things; it had lain buried all this time in deep recesses of the heart that are inaccessible to ordinary daily life. And there hid in it something of uneasiness that was inexplicable; awe, a hint of cold eternity, a touch of something unchanging and terrific, something sublime made lovely yet unearthly with shadowy time and distance. The melancholy of the Nile and the grandeur of a hundred battered temples dropped some unutterable beauty upon the heart. Up swept the desert air, the luminous pale shadows, the naked desolation that yet brims with sharp vitality. An Arab on his donkey tripped in colour across the mind, melting off into tiny perspective, strangely vivid. A string of camels stood in silhouette against the crimson sky. Great winds, great blazing spaces, great solemn nights, great days of golden splendour rose from the pavement or the theatre-stall, and London, dim-lit England, the whole of modern life, indeed, seemed suddenly reduced to a paltry insignificance that produced an aching longing for the pageantry of those millions of vanished souls. Egypt rolled through the heart for a moment—and was gone.

I remembered that some such fantastic experience had been mine. Put it as one may, the fact remains that for certain temperaments Egypt can rob the Present of some thread of interest that was formerly there. The memory became for me an integral part of personality; something in me yearned for its curious and awful beauty. He who has drunk of the Nile shall return to drink of it again. … And if for myself this was possible, what might not happen to a character of George Isley’s type? Some glimmer of comprehension came to me. The ancient, buried, hidden Egypt had cast her net about his soul. Grown shadowy in the Present, his life was being transferred into some golden, reconstructed Past, where it was real. Some countries give, while others take away. And George Isley was worth robbing. …

Disturbed by these singular reflections, I moved away from the open window, closing it. But the closing did not exclude the presence of the Third. The biting night air followed me in. I drew the mosquito curtains round the bed, but the light I left still burning; and, lying there, I jotted down upon a scrap of paper this curious impression as best I could, only to find that it escaped easily between the words. Such visionary and spiritual perceptions are too elusive to be trapped in language. Reading it over after an interval of years, it is difficult to recall with what intense meaning, what uncanny emotion, I wrote those faded lines in pencil. Their rhetoric seems cheap, their content much exaggerated; yet at the time truth burned in every syllable. Egypt, which since time began has suffered robbery with violence at the hands of all the world, now takes her vengeance, choosing her individual prey. Her time has come. Behind a modern mask she lies in wait, intensely active, sure of her hidden power. Prostitute of dead empires, she lies now at peace beneath the same old stars, her loveliness unimpaired, bejewelled with the beaten gold of ages, her breasts uncovered, and her grand limbs flashing in the sun. Her shoulders of alabaster are lifted above the sand-drifts; she surveys the little figures of today. She takes her choice. …

That night I did not dream, but neither did the whole of me lie down in sleep. During the long dark hours I was aware of that picture endlessly repeating itself, the picture of George Isley stealing out into the moonlight desert. The night so swiftly dropped her hood about him; so mysteriously he merged into the unchanging thing which cloaks the past. It lifted. Some huge shadowy hand, gloved softly yet of granite, stretched over the leagues to take him. He disappeared.

They say the desert is motionless and has no gestures! That night I saw it moving, hurrying. It went tearing after him. You understand my meaning? No! Well, when excited it produces this strange impression, and the terrible moment is—when you surrender helplessly—you desire it shall swallow you. You let it come. George Isley spoke of a web. It is, at any rate, some central power that conceals itself behind the surface glamour folk call the spell of Egypt. Its home is not apparent. It dwells with ancient Egypt—underground. Behind the stillness of hot windless days, behind the peace of calm, gigantic nights, it lurks unrealised, monstrous and irresistible. My mind grasped it as little as the fact that our solar system with all its retinue of satellites and planets rushes annually many million miles towards a star in Hercules, while yet that constellation appears no closer than it did six thousand years ago. But the clue dropped into me. George Isley, with his entire retinue of thought and life and feeling, was being similarly drawn. And I, a minor satellite, had become aware of the horrifying pull. It was magnificent. … And I fell asleep on the crest of this enormous wave.

V

The next few days passed idly; weeks passed too, I think; hidden away in this cosmopolitan hotel we lived apart, unnoticed. There was the feeling that time went what pace it pleased, now fast, now slow, now standing still. The similarity of the brilliant days, set between wondrous dawns and sunsets, left the impression that it was really one long, endless day without divisions. The mind’s machinery of measurement suffered dislocation. Time went backwards; dates were forgotten; the month, the time of year, the century itself went down into undifferentiated life.

The Present certainly slipped away curiously. Newspapers and politics became unimportant, news uninteresting, English life so remote as to be unreal, European affairs shadowy. The stream of life ran in another direction altogether—backwards. The names and faces of friends appeared through mist. People arrived as though dropped from the skies. They suddenly were there; one saw them in the dining-room, as though they had just slipped in from an outer world that once was real—somewhere. Of course, a steamer sailed four times a week, and the journey took five days, but these things were merely known, not realised. The fact that here it was summer, whereas over there winter reigned, helped to make the distance not quite thinkable. We looked at the desert and made plans. “We will do this, we will do that; we must go there, we’ll visit such and such a place …” yet nothing happened. It always was tomorrow or yesterday, and we shared the discovery of Alice that there was no real “today.” For our thinking made everything happen. That was enough. It had happened. It was the reality of dreams. Egypt was a dreamworld that made the heart live backwards.

It came about, thus, that for the next few weeks I watched a fading life, myself alert and sympathetic, yet unable somehow to intrude and help. Noticing various little things by which George Isley betrayed the progress of the unequal struggle, I found my assistance negatived by the fact that I was in similar case myself. What he experienced in large and finally, I, too, experienced in little and for the moment. For I seemed also caught upon the fringe of the invisible web. My feelings were entangled sufficiently for me to understand. … And the decline of his being was terrible to watch. His character went with it; I saw his talents fade, his personality dwindle, his very soul dissolve before the insidious and invading influence. He hardly struggled. I thought of those abominable insects that paralyse the motor systems of their victims and then devour them at their leisure—alive. The incredible adventure was literally true, but, being spiritual, may not be told in the terms of a detective story. This version must remain an individual rendering—an aspect of one possible version. All who know the real Egypt, that Egypt which has nothing to do with dams and Nationalists and the external welfare of the falaheen, will understand. The pilfering of her ancient dead she suffers still; she, in revenge, preys at her leisure on the living.

The occasions when he betrayed himself were ordinary enough; it was the glimpse they afforded of what was in progress beneath his calm exterior that made them interesting. Once, I remember, we had lunched together at Mena, and, after visiting certain excavations beyond the Giza pyramids, we made our way homewards by way of the Sphinx. It was dusk, and the main army of tourists had retired, though some few dozen sightseers still moved about to the cries of donkey-boys and baksheesh. The vast head and shoulders suddenly emerged, riding undrowned above the sea of sand. Dark and monstrous in the fading light, it loomed, as ever, a being of nonhuman lineage; no amount of familiarity could depreciate its grandeur, its impressive setting, the lost expression of the countenance that is too huge to focus as a face. A thousand visits leave its power undiminished. It has intruded upon our earth from some uncommon world. George Isley and myself both turned aside to acknowledge the presence of this alien, uncomfortable thing. We did not linger, but we slackened pace. It was the obvious, inevitable thing to do. He pointed then, with a suddenness that made me start. He indicated the tourists standing round.

“See,” he said, in a lowered tone, “day and night you’ll always find a crowd obedient to that thing. But notice their behaviour. People don’t do that before any other ruin in the world I’ve ever seen.” He referred to the attempts of individuals to creep away alone and stare into the stupendous visage by themselves. At different points in the deep sandy basin were men and women, standing solitary, lying, crouching, apart from the main company where the dragomen mouthed their exposition with impertinent glibness.

“The desire to be alone,” he went on, half to himself, as we paused a moment, “the sense of worship which insists on privacy.”

It was significant, for no amount of advertising could dwarf the impressiveness of the inscrutable visage into whose eyes of stone the silent humans gazed. Not even the redcoat, standing inside one gigantic ear, could introduce the commonplace. But my companion’s words let another thing into the spectacle, a less exalted thing, dropping a hint of horror about that sandy cup: It became easy, for a moment, to imagine these tourists worshipping—against their will; to picture the monster noticing that they were there; that it might slowly turn its awful head; that the sand might visibly trickle from a stirring paw; that, in a word, they might be taken—changed.

“Come,” he whispered in a dropping tone, interrupting my fancies as though he half divined them, “it is getting late, and to be alone with the thing is intolerable to me just now. But you notice, don’t you,” he added, as he took my arm to hurry me away, “how little the tourists matter? Instead of injuring the effect, they increase it. It uses them.”

And again a slight sensation of chill, communicated possibly by his nervous touch, or possibly by his earnest way of saying these curious words, passed through me. Some part of me remained behind in that hollow trough of sand, prostrate before an immensity that symbolised the past. A curious, wild yearning caught me momentarily, an intense desire to understand exactly why that terror stood there, its actual meaning long ago to the hearts that set it waiting for the sun, what definite role it played, what souls it stirred and why, in that system of towering belief and faith whose indestructible emblem it still remained. The past stood grouped so solemnly about its menacing presentment. I was distinctly aware of this spiritual suction backwards that my companion yielded to so gladly, yet against his normal, modern self. For it made the past appear magnificently desirable, and loosened all the rivets of the present. It bodied forth three main ingredients of this deep Egyptian spell—size, mystery, and immobility.

Yet, to my relief, the cheaper aspect of this Egyptian glamour left him cold. He remained unmoved by the commonplace mysterious; he told no mummy stories, nor ever hinted at the supernatural quality that leaps to the mind of the majority. There was no play in him. The influence was grave and vital. And, although I knew he held strong views with regard to the impiety of disturbing the dead, he never in my hearing attached any possible revengeful character to the energy of an outraged past. The current tales of this description he ignored; they were for superstitious minds or children; the deities that claimed his soul were of a grander order altogether. He lived, if it may be so expressed, already in a world his heart had reconstructed or remembered; it drew him in another direction altogether; with the modern, sensational view of life his spirit held no traffic any longer; he was living backwards. I saw his figure receding mournfully, yet never sentimentally, into the spacious, golden atmosphere of recaptured days. The enormous soul of buried Egypt drew him down. The dwindling of his physical appearance was, of course, a mental interpretation of my own; but another, stranger interpretation of a spiritual kind moved parallel with it—marvellous and horrible. For, as he diminished outwardly and in his modern, present aspect, he grew within—gigantic. The size of Egypt entered into him. Huge proportions now began to accompany any presentment of his personality to my inner vision. He towered. These two qualities of the land already obsessed him—magnitude and immobility.

And that awe which modern life ignores contemptuously woke in my heart. I almost feared his presence at certain times. For one aspect of the Egyptian spell is explained by sheer size and bulk. Disdainful of mere speed today, the heart is still uncomfortable with magnitude; and in Egypt there is size that may easily appal, for every detail shunts it laboriously upon the mind. It elbows out the present. The desert’s vastness is not made comprehensible by mileage, and the sources of the Nile are so distant that they exist less on the map than in the imagination. The effort to realise suffers paralysis; they might equally be in the moon or Saturn. The undecorated magnificence of the desert remains unknown, just as the proportions of pyramid and temple, of pylons and Colossi approach the edge of the mind yet never enter in. All stand outside, clothed in this prodigious measurement of the past. And the old beliefs not only share this titanic effect upon the consciousness, but carry it stages further. The entire scale haunts with uncomfortable immensity, so that the majority run back with relief to the measurable details of a more manageable scale. Express trains, flying machines, Atlantic liners—these produce no unpleasant stretching of the faculties compared to the influence of the Karnak pylons, the pyramids, or the interior of the Serapeum.

Close behind this magnitude, moreover, steps the monstrous. It is revealed not in sand and stone alone, in queer effects of light and shadow, of glittering sunsets and of magical dusks, but in the very aspect of the bird and animal life. The heavy-headed buffaloes betray it equally with the vultures, the myriad kites, the grotesqueness of the mouthing camels. The rude, enormous scenery has it everywhere. There is nothing lyrical in this land of passionate mirages. Uncouth immensity notes the little human flittings. The days roll by in a tide of golden splendour; one goes helplessly with the flood; but it is an irresistible flood that sweeps backwards and below. The silent-footed natives in their coloured robes move before a curtain, and behind that curtain dwells the soul of ancient Egypt—the Reality, as George Isley called it—watching, with sleepless eyes of grey infinity. Then, sometimes the curtain stirs and lifts an edge; an invisible hand creeps forth; the soul is touched. And someone disappears.

VI

The process of disintegration must have been at work a long time before I appeared upon the scene; the changes went forward with such rapidity.

It was his third year in Egypt, two of which had been spent without interruption in company with an Egyptologist named Moleson, in the neighbourhood of Thebes. I soon discovered that this region was for him the centre of attraction, or as he put it, of the web. Not Luxor, of course, nor the images of reconstructed Karnak; but that stretch of grim, forbidding mountains where royalty, earthly and spiritual, sought eternal peace for the physical remains. There, amid surroundings of superb desolation, great priests and mighty kings had thought themselves secure from sacrilegious touch. In caverns underground they kept their faithful tryst with centuries, guarded by the silence of magnificent gloom. There they waited, communing with passing ages in their sleep, till Ra, their glad divinity, should summon them to the fulfilment of their ancient dream. And there, in the Valley of the Tombs of the Kings, their dream was shattered, their lovely prophecies derided, and their glory dimmed by the impious desecration of the curious.

That George Isley and his companion had spent their time, not merely digging and deciphering like their practical confrères, but engaged in some strange experiments of recovery and reconstruction, was matter for open comment among the fraternity. That incredible things had happened there was the big story of two Egyptian seasons at least. I heard this later only—tales of utterly incredible kind, that the desolate vale of rock was seen repeopled on moonlit nights, that the smoke of unaccustomed fires rose to cap the flat-topped peaks, that the pageantry of some forgotten worship had been seen to issue from the openings of these hills, and that sounds of chanting, sonorous and marvellously sweet, had been heard to echo from those bleak, repellent precipices. The tales apparently were grossly exaggerated; wandering Bedouins brought them in; the guides and dragomen repeated them with mysterious additions; till they filtered down through the native servants in the hotels and reached the tourists with highly picturesque embroidery. They reached the authorities too. The only accurate fact I gathered at the time, however, was that they had abruptly ceased. George Isley and Moleson, moreover, had parted company. And Moleson, I heard, was the originator of the business. He was, at this time, unknown to me; his arresting book on “A Modern Reconstruction of Sun-worship in Ancient Egypt” being my only link with his unusual mind. Apparently he regarded the sun as the deity of the scientific religion of the future which would replace the various anthropomorphic gods of childish creeds. He discussed the possibility of the zodiacal signs being some kind of Celestial Intelligences. Belief blazed on every page. Men’s life is heat, derived solely from the sun, and men were, therefore, part of the sun in the sense that a Christian is part of his personal deity. And absorption was the end. His description of “sun-worship ceremonials” conveyed an amazing reality and beauty. This singular book, however, was all I knew of him until he came to visit us in Helouan, though I easily discerned that his influence somehow was the original cause of the change in my companion.

At Thebes, then, was the active centre of the influence that drew my friend away from modern things. It was there, I easily guessed, that “obstacles” had been placed in the way of these men’s too close enquiry. In that haunted and oppressive valley, where profane and reverent come to actual grips, where modern curiosity is most busily organised, and even tourists are aware of a masked hostility that dogs the prying of the least imaginative mind—there, in the neighbourhood of the hundred-gated city, had Egypt set the headquarters of her irreconcilable enmity. And it was there, amid the ruins of her loveliest past, that George Isley had spent his years of magical reconstruction and met the influence that now dominated his entire life.

And though no definite avowal of the struggle betrayed itself in speech between us, I remember fragments of conversation, even at this stage, that proved his willing surrender of the present. We spoke of fear once, though with the indirectness of connection I have mentioned. I urged that the mind, once it is forewarned, can remain master of itself and prevent a thing from happening.

“But that does not make the thing unreal,” he objected.

“The mind can deny it,” I said. “It then becomes unreal.”

He shook his head. “One does not deny an unreality. Denial is a childish act of self-protection against something you expect to happen.” He caught my eye a moment. “You deny what you are afraid of,” he said. “Fear invites.” And he smiled uneasily. “You know it must get you in the end.” And, both of us being aware secretly to what our talk referred, it seemed bold-blooded and improper; for actually we discussed the psychology of his disappearance. Yet, while I disliked it, there was a fascination about the subject that compelled attraction. … “Once fear gets in,” he added presently, “confidence is undermined, the structure of life is threatened, and you—go gladly. The foundation of everything is belief. A man is what he believes about himself; and in Egypt you can believe things that elsewhere you would not even think about. It attacks the essentials.” He sighed, yet with a curious pleasure; and a smile of resignation and relief passed over his rugged features and was gone again. The luxury of abandonment lay already in him.

“But even belief,” I protested, “must be founded on some experience or other.” It seemed ghastly to speak of his spiritual malady behind the mask of indirect allusion. My excuse was that he so obviously talked willingly.

He agreed instantly. “Experience of one kind or another,” he said darkly, “there always is. Talk with the men who live out here; ask anyone who thinks, or who has the imagination which divines. You’ll get only one reply, phrase it how they may. Even the tourists and the little commonplace officials feel it. And it’s not the climate, it’s not nerves, it’s not any definite tendency that they can name or lay their finger on. Nor is it mere orientalising of the mind. It’s something that first takes you from your common life, and that later takes common life from you. You willingly resign an unremunerative Present. There are no half-measures either—once the gates are open.”

There was so much undeniable truth in this that I found no corrective by way of strong rejoinder. All my attempts, indeed, were futile in this way. He meant to go; my words could not stop him. He wanted a witness—he dreaded the loneliness of going—but he brooked no interference. The contradictory position involved a perplexing state of heart and mind in both of us. The atmosphere of this majestic land, today so trifling, yesterday so immense, most certainly induced a lifting of the spiritual horizon that revealed amazing possibilities.

VII

It was in the windless days of a perfect December that Moleson, the Egyptologist, found us out and paid a flying visit to Helouan. His duties took him up and down the land, but his time seemed largely at his own disposal. He lingered on. His coming introduced a new element I was not quite able to estimate; though, speaking generally, the effect of his presence upon my companion was to emphasise the latter’s alteration. It underlined the change, and drew attention to it. The new arrival, I gathered, was not altogether welcome. “I should never have expected to find you here,” laughed Moleson when they met, and whether he referred to Helouan or to the hotel was not quite clear. I got the impression he meant both; I remembered my fancy that it was a good hotel to hide in. George Isley had betrayed a slight involuntary start when the visiting card was brought to him at teatime. I think he had wished to escape from his former co-worker. Moleson had found him out. “I heard you had a friend with you and were contemplating further exper—work,” he added. He changed the word “experiment” quickly to the other.

“The former, as you see, is true, but not the latter,” replied my companion dryly, and in his manner was a touch of opposition that might have been hostility. Their intimacy, I saw, was close and of old standing. In all they said and did and looked, there was an undercurrent of other meaning that just escaped me. They were up to something—they had been up to something; but Isley would have withdrawn if he could!

Moleson was an ambitious and energetic personality, absorbed in his profession, alive to the poetical as well as to the practical value of archaeology, and he made at first a wholly delightful impression upon me. An instinctive flair for his subject had early in life brought him success and a measure of fame as well. His knowledge was accurate and scholarly, his mind saturated in the lore of a vanished civilisation. Behind an exterior that was quietly careless, I divined a passionate and complex nature, and I watched him with interest as the man for whom the olden sun-worship of unscientific days held some beauty of reality and truth. Much in his strange book that had bewildered me now seemed intelligible when I saw the author. I cannot explain this more closely. Something about him somehow made it possible. Though modern to the fingertips and thoroughly equipped with all the tendencies of the day, there seemed to hide in him another self that held aloof with a dignified detachment from the interests in which his “educated” mind was centred. He read living secrets beneath museum labels, I might put it. He stepped out of the days of the Pharaohs if ever man did, and I realised early in our acquaintance that this was the man who had exceptional powers of “resistance and self-protection,” and was, in his particular branch of work, “unusual.” In manner he was light and gay, his sense of humour strong, with a way of treating everything as though laughter was the sanest attitude towards life. There is, however, the laughter that hides—other things. Moleson, as I gathered from many clues of talk and manner and silence, was a deep and singular being. His experiences in Egypt, if any, he had survived admirably. There were at least two Molesons. I felt him more than double—multiple.

In appearance tall, thin, and fleshless, with a dried-up skin and features withered as a mummy’s, he said laughingly that Nature had picked him physically for his “job”; and, indeed, one could see him worming his way down narrow tunnels into the sandy tombs, and writhing along sunless passages of suffocating heat without too much personal inconvenience. Something sinuous, almost fluid in his mind expressed itself in his body too. He might go in any direction without causing surprise. He might go backwards or forwards. He might go in two directions at once.

And my first impression of the man deepened before many days were past. There was irresponsibility in him, insincerity somewhere, almost want of heart. His morality was certainly not today’s, and the mind in him was slippery. I think the modern world, to which he was unattached, confused and irritated him. A sense of insecurity came with him. His interest in George Isley was the interest in a psychological “specimen.” I remembered how in his book he described the selection of individuals for certain functions of that marvellous worship, and the odd idea flashed through me—well, that Isley exactly suited some purpose of his recreating energies. The man was keenly observant from top to toe, but not with his sight alone; he seemed to be aware of motives and emotions before he noticed the acts or gestures that these caused. I felt that he took me in as well. Certainly he eyed me up and down by means of this inner observation that seemed automatic with him.

Moleson was not staying in our hotel; he had chosen one where social life was more abundant; but he came up frequently to lunch and dine, and sometimes spent the evening in Isley’s rooms, amusing us with his skill upon the piano, singing Arab songs, and chanting phrases from the ancient Egyptian rituals to rhythms of his own invention. The old Egyptian music, both in harmony and melody, was far more developed than I had realised, the use of sound having been of radical importance in their ceremonies. The chanting in particular he did with extraordinary effect, though whether its success lay in his sonorous voice, his peculiar increasing of the vowel sounds, or in anything deeper, I cannot pretend to say. The result at any rate was of a unique description. It brought buried Egypt to the surface; the gigantic Presence entered sensibly into the room. It came, huge and gorgeous, rolling upon the mind the instant he began, and something in it was both terrible and oppressive. The repose of eternity lay in the sound. Invariably, after a few moments of that transforming music, I saw the Valley of the Kings, the deserted temples, titanic faces of stone, great effigies coifed with zodiacal signs, but above all—the twin Colossi.

I mentioned this latter detail.

“Curious you should feel that too—curious you should say it, I mean,” Moleson replied, not looking at me, yet with an air as if I had said something he expected. “To me the Memnon figures express Egypt better than all the other monuments put together. Like the desert, they are featureless. They sum her up, as it were, yet leave the message unuttered. For, you see, they cannot.” He laughed a little in his throat. “They have neither eyes nor lips nor nose; their features are gone.”

“Yet they tell the secret—to those who care to listen,” put in Isley in a scarcely noticeable voice. “Just because they have no words. They still sing at dawn,” he added in a louder, almost a challenging tone. It startled me.

Moleson turned round at him, opened his lips to speak, hesitated, stopped. He said nothing for a moment. I cannot describe what it was in the lightning glance they exchanged that put me on the alert for something other than was obvious. My nerves quivered suddenly, and a breath of colder air stole in among us. Moleson swung round to me again. “I almost think,” he said, laughing when I complimented him upon the music, “that I must have been a priest of Aton-Ra in an earlier existence, for all this comes to my fingertips as if it were instinctive knowledge. Plotinus, remember, lived a few miles away at Alexandria with his great idea that knowledge is recollection,” he said, with a kind of cynical amusement. “In those days, at any rate,” he added more significantly, “worship was real and ceremonials actually expressed great ideas and teaching. There was power in them.” Two of the Molesons spoke in that contradictory utterance.

I saw that Isley was fidgeting where he sat, betraying by certain gestures that uneasiness was in him. He hid his face a moment in his hands; he sighed; he made a movement—as though to prevent something coming. But Moleson resisted his attempt to change the conversation, though the key shifted a little of its own accord. There were numerous occasions like this when I was aware that both men skirted something that had happened, something that Moleson wished to resume, but that Isley seemed anxious to postpone.

I found myself studying Moleson’s personality, yet never getting beyond a certain point. Shrewd, subtle, with an acute rather than a large intelligence, he was cynical as well as insincere, and yet I cannot describe by what means I arrived at two other conclusions as well about him: first, that this insincerity and want of heart had not been so always; and, secondly, that he sought social diversion with deliberate and un-ordinary purpose. I could well believe that the first was Egypt’s mark upon him, and the second an effort at resistance and self-protection.

“If it wasn’t for the gaiety,” he remarked once in a flippant way that thinly hid significance, “a man out here would go under in a year. Social life gets rather reckless—exaggerated—people do things they would never dream of doing at home. Perhaps you’ve noticed it,” he added, looking suddenly at me; “Cairo and the rest—they plunge at it as though driven—a sort of excess about it somewhere.” I nodded agreement. The way he said it was unpleasant rather. “It’s an antidote,” he said, a subacid flavour in his tone. “I used to loathe society myself. But now I find gaiety—a certain irresponsible excitement—of importance. Egypt gets on the nerves after a bit. The moral fibre fails. The will grows weak.” And he glanced covertly at Isley as with a desire to point his meaning. “It’s the clash between the ugly present and the majestic past, perhaps.” He smiled.

Isley shrugged his shoulders, making no reply; and the other went on to tell stories of friends and acquaintances whom Egypt had adversely affected: Barton, the Oxford man, school teacher, who had insisted in living in a tent until the Government relieved him of his job. He took to his tent, roamed the desert, drawn irresistibly, practical considerations of the present of no avail. This yearning took him, though he could never define the exact attraction. In the end his mental balance was disturbed. “But now he’s all right again; I saw him in London only this year; he can’t say what he felt or why he did it. Only—he’s different.” Of John Lattin, too, he spoke, whom agarophobia caught so terribly in Upper Egypt; of Malahide, upon whom some fascination of the Nile induced suicidal mania and attempts at drowning; of Jim Moleson, a cousin (who had camped at Thebes with himself and Isley), whom megalomania of a most singular type attacked suddenly in a sandy waste—all radically cured as soon as they left Egypt, yet, one and all, changed and made otherwise in their very souls.

He talked in a loose, disjointed way, and though much he said was fantastic, as if meant to challenge opposition, there was impressiveness about it somewhere, due, I think, to a kind of cumulative emotion he produced.

“The monuments do not impress merely by their bulk, but by their majestic symmetry,” I remember him saying. “Look at the choice of form alone—the Pyramids, for instance. No other shape was possible: dome, square, spires, all would have been hideously inadequate. The wedge-shaped mass, immense foundations and pointed apex were the mot juste in outline. Do you think people without greatness in themselves chose that form? There was no unbalance in the minds that conceived the harmonious and magnificent structures of the temples. There was stately grandeur in their consciousness that could only be born of truth and knowledge. The power in their images is a direct expression of eternal and essential things they knew.”

We listened in silence. He was off upon his hobby. But behind the careless tone and laughing questions there was this lurking passionateness that made me feel uncomfortable. He was edging up, I felt, towards some climax that meant life and death to himself and Isley. I could not fathom it. My sympathy let me in a little, yet not enough to understand completely. Isley, I saw, was also uneasy, though for reasons that equally evaded me.

“One can almost believe,” he continued, “that something still hangs about in the atmosphere from those olden times.” He half closed his eyes, but I caught the gleam in them. “It affects the mind through the imagination. With some it changes the point of view. It takes the soul back with it to former, quite different, conditions, that must have been almost another kind of consciousness.”

He paused an instant and looked up at us. “The intensity of belief in those days,” he resumed, since neither of us accepted the challenge, “was amazing—something quite unknown anywhere in the world today. It was so sure, so positive; no mere speculative theories, I mean;—as though something in the climate, the exact position beneath the stars, the ‘attitude’ of this particular stretch of earth in relation to the sun—thinned the veil between humanity—and other things. Their hierarchies of gods, you know, were not mere idols; animals, birds, monsters, and whatnot, all typified spiritual forces and powers that influenced their daily life. But the strong thing is—they knew. People who were scientific as they were did not swallow foolish superstitions. They made colours that could last six thousand years, even in the open air; and without instruments they measured accurately—an enormously difficult and involved calculation—the precession of the equinoxes. You’ve been to Denderah?”—he suddenly glanced again at me. “No! Well, the minds that realised the zodiacal signs could hardly believe, you know, that Hathor was a cow!”

Isley coughed. He was about to interrupt, but before he could find words, Moleson was off again, some new quality in his tone and manner that was almost aggressive. The hints he offered seemed more than hints. There was a strange conviction in his heart. I think he was skirting a bigger thing that he and his companion knew, yet that his real object was to see in how far I was open to attack—how far my sympathy might be with them. I became aware that he and George Isley shared this bigger thing. It was based, I felt, on some certain knowledge that experiment had brought them.

“Think of the grand teaching of Aknahton, that young Pharaoh who regenerated the entire land and brought it to its immense prosperity. He taught the worship of the sun, but not of the visible sun. The deity had neither form nor shape. The great disk of glory was but the manifestation, each beneficent ray ending in a hand that blessed the world. It was a god of everlasting energy, love and power, yet men could know it at first hand in their daily lives, worshipping it at dawn and sunset with passionate devotion. No anthropomorphic idol masqueraded in that!”

An extraordinary glow was about him as he said it. The same minute he lowered his voice, shifting the key perceptibly. He kept looking up at me through half-closed eyelids.

“And another thing they wonderfully knew,” he almost whispered, “was that, with the precession of their deity across the equinoctial changes, there came new powers down into the world of men. Each cycle—each zodiacal sign—brought its special powers which they quickly typified in the monstrous effigies we label today in our dull museums. Each sign took some two thousand years to traverse. Each sign, moreover, involved a change in human consciousness. There was this relation between the heavens and the human heart. All that they knew. While the sun crawled through the sign of Taurus, it was the Bull they worshipped; with Aries, it was the ram that coifed their granite symbols. Then came, as you remember, with Pisces the great New Arrival, when already they sank from their grand zenith, and the Fish was taken as the emblem of the changing powers which the Christ embodied. For the human soul, they held, echoed the changes in the immense journey of the original deity, who is its source, across the Zodiac, and the truth of ‘As above, so Below’ remains the key to all manifested life. And today the sun, just entering Aquarius, new powers are close upon the world. The old—that which has been for two thousand years—again is crumbling, passing, dying. New powers and a new consciousness are knocking at our doors. It is a time of change. It is also”—he leaned forward so that his eyes came close before me—“the time to make the change. The soul can choose its own conditions. It can—”

A sudden crash smothered the rest of the sentence. A chair had fallen with a clatter upon the wooden floor where the carpet left it bare. Whether Isley in rising had stumbled against it, or whether he had purposely knocked it over, I could not say. I only knew that he had abruptly risen and as abruptly sat down again. A curious feeling came to me that the sign was somehow prearranged. It was so sudden. His voice, too, was forced, I thought.

“Yes, but we can do without all that, Moleson,” he interrupted with acute abruptness. “Suppose we have a tune instead.”

VIII

It was after dinner in his private room, and he had sat very silent in his corner until this sudden outburst. Moleson got up quietly without a word and moved over to the piano. I saw—or was it imagination merely?—a new expression slide upon his withered face. He meant mischief somewhere.

From that instant—from the moment he rose and walked over the thick carpet—he fascinated me. The atmosphere his talk and stories had brought remained. His lean fingers ran over the keys, and at first he played fragments from popular musical comedies that were pleasant enough, but made no demand upon the attention. I heard them without listening. I was thinking of another thing—his walk. For the way he moved across those few feet of carpet had power in it. He looked different; he seemed another man; he was changed. I saw him curiously—as I sometimes now saw Isley too—bigger. In some manner that was both enchanting and oppressive, his presence from that moment drew my imagination as by an air of authority it held.

I left my seat in the far corner and dropped into a chair beside the window, nearer to the piano. Isley, I then noticed, had also turned to watch him. But it was George Isley not quite as he was now. I felt rather than saw the change. Both men had subtly altered. They seemed extended, their outlines shadowy.

Isley, alert and anxious, glanced up at the player, his mind of earlier years—for the expression of his face was plain—following the light music, yet with difficulty that involved effort, almost struggle. “Play that again, will you?” I heard him say from time to time. He was trying to take hold of it, to climb back to a condition where that music had linked him to the present, to seize a mental structure that was gone, to grip hold tightly of it—only to find that it was too far forgotten and too fragile. It would not bear him. I am sure of it, and I can swear I divined his mood. He fought to realise himself as he had been, but in vain. In his dim corner opposite I watched him closely. The big black Blüthner blocked itself between us. Above it swayed the outline, lean and half shadowy, of Moleson as he played. A faint whisper floated through the room. “You are in Egypt.” Nowhere else could this queer feeling of presentiment, of anticipation, have gained a footing so easily. I was aware of intense emotion in all three of us. The least reminder of Today seemed ugly. I longed for some ancient forgotten splendour that was lost.

The scene fixed my attention very steadily, for I was aware of something deliberate and calculated on Moleson’s part. The thing was well considered in his mind, intention only half concealed. It was Egypt he interpreted by sound, expressing what in him was true, then observing its effect, as he led us cleverly towards—the past. Beginning with the present, he played persuasively, with penetration, with insistent meaning too. He had that touch which conjured up real atmosphere, and, at first, that atmosphere termed modern. He rendered vividly the note of London, passing from the jingles of musical comedy, nervous rag-times and sensuous Tango dances, into the higher strains of concert rooms and “cultured” circles. Yet not too abruptly. Most dexterously he shifted the level, and with it our emotion. I recognised, as in a parody, various ultramodern thrills: the tumult of Strauss, the pagan sweetness of primitive Debussy, the weirdness and ecstasy of metaphysical Scriabin. The composite note of Today in both extremes, he brought into this private sitting-room of the desert hotel, while George Isley, listening keenly, fidgeted in his chair.

“ ‘Après-midi d’un Faune,’ ” said Moleson dreamily, answering the question as to what he played. “Debussy’s, you know. And the thing before it was from ‘Till Eulenspiegel’—Strauss, of course.”

He drawled, swaying slowly with the rhythm, and leaving pauses between the words. His attention was not wholly on his listener, and in the voice was a quality that increased my uneasy apprehension. I felt distress for Isley somewhere. Something, it seemed, was coming; Moleson brought it. Unconsciously in his walk, it now appeared consciously in his music; and it came from what was underground in him. A charm, a subtle change, stole oddly over the room. It stole over my heart as well. Some power of estimating left me, as though my mind were slipping backwards and losing familiar, common standards.

“The true modern note in it, isn’t there?” he drawled; “cleverness, I think—intellectual—surface ingenuity—no depth or permanence—just the sensational brilliance of Today.” He turned and stared at me fixedly an instant. “Nothing everlasting,” he added impressively. “It tells everything it knows—because it’s small enough—”

And the room turned pettier as he said it; another, bigger shadow draped its little walls. Through the open windows came a stealthy gesture of eternity. The atmosphere stretched visibly. Moleson was playing a marvellous fragment from Scriabin’s “Prometheus.” It sounded thin and shallow. This modern music, all of it, was out of place and trivial. It was almost ridiculous. The scale of our emotion changed insensibly into a deeper thing that has no name in dictionaries, being of another age. And I glanced at the windows where stone columns framed dim sections of great Egypt listening outside. There was no moon; only deep draughts of stars blazed, hanging in the sky. I thought with awe of the mysterious knowledge that vanished people had of these stars, and of the Sun’s huge journey through the Zodiac. …

And, with astonishing suddenness as of dream, there rose a pictured image against that starlit sky. Lifted into the air, between heaven and earth, I saw float swiftly past a panorama of the stately temples, led by Denderah, Edfu, Abou Simbel. It paused, it hovered, it disappeared. Leaving incalculable solemnity behind it in the air, it vanished, and to see so vast a thing move at that easy yet unhasting speed unhinged some sense of measurement in me. It was, of course, I assured myself, mere memory objectified owing to something that the music summoned, yet the apprehension rose in me that the whole of Egypt presently would stream past in similar fashion—Egypt as she was in the zenith of her unrecoverable past. Behind the tinkling of the modern piano passed the rustling of a multitude, the tramping of countless feet on sand. … It was singularly vivid. It arrested in me something that normally went flowing. … And when I turned my head towards the room to call attention to my strange experience, the eyes of Moleson, I saw, were laid upon my own. He stared at me. The light in them transfixed me, and I understood that the illusion was due in some manner to his evocation. Isley rose at the same moment from his chair. The thing I had vaguely been expecting had shifted closer. And the same moment the musician abruptly changed his key.

“You may like this better,” he murmured, half to himself, but in tones he somehow made echoing. “It’s more suited to the place.” There was a resonance in the voice as though it emerged from hollows underground. “The other seems almost sacrilegious—here.” And his voice drawled off in the rhythm of slower modulations that he played. It had grown muffled. There was an impression, too, that he did not strike the piano, but that the music issued from himself.

“Place! What place?” asked Isley quickly. His head turned sharply as he spoke. His tone, in its remoteness, made me tremble.

The musician laughed to himself. “I meant that this hotel seems really an impertinence,” he murmured, leaning down upon the notes he played upon so softly and so well; “and that it’s but the thinnest kind of pretence—when you come to think of it. We are in the desert really. The Colossi are outside, and all the emptied temples. Or ought to be,” he added, raising his tone abruptly with a glance at me.

He straightened up and stared out into the starry sky past George Isley’s shoulders.

“That,” he exclaimed with betraying vehemence, “is where we are and what we play to!” His voice suddenly increased; there was a roar in it. “That,” he repeated, “is the thing that takes our hearts away.” The volume of intonation was astonishing.

For the way he uttered the monosyllable suddenly revealed the man beneath the outer sheath of cynicism and laughter, explained his heartlessness, his secret stream of life. He, too, was soul and body in the past. “That” revealed more than pages of descriptive phrases. His heart lived in the temple aisles, his mind unearthed forgotten knowledge; his soul had clothed itself anew in the seductive glory of antiquity: he dwelt with a quickening magic of existence in the reconstructed splendour of what most term only ruins. He and George Isley together had revivified a power that enticed them backwards; but whereas the latter struggled still, the former had already made his permanent home there. The faculty in me that saw the vision of streaming temples saw also this—remorselessly definite. Moleson himself sat naked at that piano. I saw him clearly then. He no longer masqueraded behind his sneers and laughter. He, too, had long ago surrendered, lost himself, gone out, and from the place his soul now dwelt in he watched George Isley sinking down to join him. He lived in ancient, subterranean Egypt. This great hotel stood precariously on the merest upper crust of desert. A thousand tombs, a hundred temples lay outside, within reach almost of our very voices. Moleson was merged with “that.”

This intuition flashed upon me like the picture in the sky; and both were true.

And, meanwhile, this other thing he played had a surge of power in it impossible to describe. It was sombre, huge and solemn. It conveyed the power that his walk conveyed. There was distance in it, but a distance not of space alone. A remoteness of time breathed through it with that strange sadness and melancholy yearning that enormous interval brings. It marched, but very far away; it held refrains that assumed the rhythms of a multitude the centuries muted; it sang, but the singing was underground in passages that fine sand muffled. Lost, wandering winds sighed through it, booming. The contrast, after the modern, cheaper music, was dislocating. Yet the change had been quite naturally effected.

“It would sound empty and monotonous elsewhere—in London, for instance,” I heard Moleson drawling, as he swayed to and fro, “but here it is big and splendid—true. You hear what I mean,” he added gravely. “You understand?”

“What is it?” asked Isley thickly, before I could say a word. “I forget exactly. It has tears in it—more than I can bear.” The end of his sentence died away in his throat.

Moleson did not look at him as he answered. He looked at me.

“You surely ought to know,” he replied, the voice rising and falling as though the rhythm forced it. “You have heard it all before—that chant from the ritual we—”

Isley sprang up and stopped him. I did not hear the sentence complete. An extraordinary thought blazed into me that the voices of both men were not quite their own. I fancied—wild, impossible as it sounds—that I heard the twin Colossi singing to each other in the dawn. Stupendous ideas sprang past me, leaping. It seemed as though eternal symbols of the cosmos, discovered and worshipped in this ancient land, leaped into awful life. My consciousness became enveloping. I had the distressing feeling that ages slipped out of place and took me with them; they dominated me; they rushed me off my feet like water. I was drawn backwards. I, too, was changing—being changed.

“I remember,” said Isley softly, a reverence of worship in his voice. But there was anguish in it too, and pity; he let the present go completely from him; the last strands severed with a wrench of pain. I imagined I heard his soul pass weeping far away—below.

“I’ll sing it,” murmured Moleson, “for the voice is necessary. The sound and rhythm are utterly divine!”

IX

And forthwith his voice began a series of long-drawn cadences that seemed somehow the root-sounds of every tongue that ever was. A spell came over me I could touch and feel. A web encompassed me; my arms and feet became entangled; a veil of fine threads wove across my eyes. The enthralling power of the rhythm produced some magical movement in the soul. I was aware of life everywhere about me, far and near, in the dwellings of the dead, as also in the corridors of the iron hills. Thebes stood erect, and Memphis teemed upon the river banks. For the modern world fell, swaying, at this sound that restored the past, and in this past both men before me lived and had their being. The storm of present life passed o’er their heads, while they dwelt underground, obliterated, gone. Upon the wave of sound they went down into their recovered kingdom.

I shivered, moved vigorously, half rose up, then instantly sank back again, resigned and helpless. For I entered by their side, it seemed, the conditions of their strange captivity. My thoughts, my feelings, my point of view were transplanted to another centre. Consciousness shifted in me. I saw things from another’s point of view—antiquity’s.

The present forgotten but the past supreme, I lost Reality. Our room became a pinpoint picture seen in a drop of water, while this subterranean world, replacing it, turned immense. My heart took on the gigantic, leisured stride of what had been. Proportions grew; size captured me; and magnitude, turned monstrous, swept mere measurement away. Some hand of golden sunshine picked me up and set me in the quivering web beside those other two. I heard the rustle of the settling threads; I heard the shuffling of the feet in sand; I heard the whispers in the dwellings of the dead. Behind the monotony of this sacerdotal music I heard them in their dim carved chambers. The ancient galleries were awake. The Life of unremembered ages stirred in multitudes about me.

The reality of so incredible an experience evaporates through the stream of language. I can only affirm this singular proof—that the deepest, most satisfying knowledge the Present could offer seemed insignificant beside some stalwart majesty of the Past that utterly usurped it. This modern room, holding a piano and two figures of Today, appeared as a paltry miniature pinned against a vast transparent curtain, whose foreground was thick with symbols of temple, sphinx and pyramid, but whose background of stupendous hanging grey slid off towards a splendour where the cities of the Dead shook off their sand and thronged space to its ultimate horizons. … The stars, the entire universe, vibrating and alive, became involved in it. Long periods of time slipped past me. I seemed living ages ago. … I was living backwards. …

The size and eternity of Egypt took me easily. There was an overwhelming grandeur in it that elbowed out all present standards. The whole place towered and stood up. The desert reared, the very horizons lifted; majestic figures of granite rose above the hotel, great faces hovered and drove past; huge arms reached up to pluck the stars and set them in the ceilings of the labyrinthine tombs. The colossal meaning of the ancient land emerged through all its ruined details … reconstructed—burningly alive. …

It became at length unbearable. I longed for the droning sounds to cease, for the rhythm to lessen its prodigious sweep. My heart cried out for the gold of the sunlight on the desert, for the sweet air by the river’s banks, for the violet lights upon the hills at dawn. And I resisted, I made an effort to return.

“Your chant is horrible. For God’s sake, let’s have an Arab song—or the music of Today!”

The effort was intense, the result was—nothing. I swear I used these words. I heard the actual sound of my voice, if no one else did, for I remember that it was pitiful in the way great space devoured it, making of its appreciable volume the merest whisper as of some bird or insect cry. But the figure that I took for Moleson, instead of answer or acknowledgment, merely grew and grew as things grow in a fairy tale. I hardly know; I certainly cannot say. That dwindling part of me which offered comments on the entire occurrence noted this extraordinary effect as though it happened naturally—that Moleson himself was marvellously increasing.

The entire spell became operative all at once. I experienced both the delight of complete abandonment and the terror of letting go what had seemed real. I understood Moleson’s sham laughter, and the subtle resignation of George Isley. And an amazing thought flashed birdlike across my changing consciousness—that this resurrection into the Past, this rebirth of the spirit which they sought, involved taking upon themselves the guise of these ancient symbols each in turn. As the embryo assumes each evolutionary stage below it before the human semblance is attained, so the souls of those two adventurers took upon themselves the various emblems of that intense belief. The devout worshipper takes on the qualities of his deity. They wore the entire series of the old-world gods so potently that I perceived them, and even objectified them by my senses. The present was their prenatal stage; to enter the past they were being born again.

But it was not Moleson’s semblance alone that took on this awful change. Both faces, scaled to the measure of Egypt’s outstanding quality of size, became in this little modern room distressingly immense. Distorting mirrors can suggest no simile, for the symmetry of proportion was not injured. I lost their human physiognomies. I saw their thoughts, their feelings, their augmented, altered hearts, the thing that Egypt put there while she stole their love from modern life. There grew an awful stateliness upon them that was huge, mysterious, and motionless as stone.

For Moleson’s narrow face at first turned hawk-like in the semblance of the sinister deity, Horus, only stretched to tower above the toy-scaled piano; it was keen and sly and monstrous after prey, while a swiftness of the sunrise leaped from both the brilliant eyes. George Isley, equally immense of outline, was in general presentment more magnificent, a breadth of the Sphinx about his spreading shoulders, and in his countenance an inscrutable power of calm temple images. These were the first signs of obsession; but others followed. In rapid series, like lantern-slides upon a screen, the ancient symbols flashed one after another across these two extended human faces and were gone. Disentanglement became impossible. The successive signatures seemed almost superimposed as in a composite photograph, each appearing and vanished before recognition was even possible, while I interpreted the inner alchemy by means of outer tokens familiar to my senses. Egypt, possessing them, expressed herself thus marvellously in their physical aspect, using the symbols of her intense, regenerative power. …

The changes merged with such swiftness into one another that I did not seize the half of them—till, finally, the procession culminated in a single one that remained fixed awfully upon them both. The entire series merged. I was aware of this single masterful image which summed up all the others in sublime repose. The gigantic thing rose up in this incredible statue form. The spirit of Egypt synthesised in this monstrous symbol, obliterated them both. I saw the seated figures of the grim Colossi, dipped in sand, night over them, waiting for the dawn. …

X

I made a violent effort, then, at self-assertion—an effort to focus my mind upon the present. And, searching for Moleson and George Isley, its nearest details, I was aware that I could not find them. The familiar figures of my two companions were not discoverable.

I saw it as plainly as I also saw that ludicrous, wee piano—for a moment. But the moment remained; the Eternity of Egypt stayed. For that lonely and terrific pair had stooped their shoulders and bowed their awful heads. They were in the room. They imaged forth the power of the everlasting Past through the little structures of two human worshippers. Room, walls, and ceiling fled away. Sand and the open sky replaced them.

The two of them rose side by side before my bursting eyes. I knew not where to look. Like some child who confronts its giants upon the nursery floor, I turned to stone, unable to think or move. I stared. Sight wrenched itself to find the men familiar to it, but found instead this symbolising vision. I could not see them properly. Their faces were spread with hugeness, their features lost in some uncommon magnitude, their shoulders, necks, and arms grown vast upon the air. As with the desert, there was physiognomy yet no personal expression, the human thing all drowned within the mass of battered stone. I discovered neither cheeks nor mouth nor jaw, but ruined eyes and lips of broken granite. Huge, motionless, mysterious, Egypt informed them and took them to herself. And between us, curiously presented in some false perspective, I saw the little symbol of Today—the Blüthner piano. It was appalling. I knew a second of majestic horror. I blenched. Hot and cold gushed through me. Strength left me, power of speech and movement too, as in a moment of complete paralysis.

The spell, moreover, was not within the room alone; it was outside and everywhere. The Past stood massed about the very walls of the hotel. Distance, as well as time, stepped nearer. That chanting summoned the gigantic items in all their ancient splendour. The shadowy concourse grouped itself upon the sand about us, and I was aware that the great army shifted noiselessly into place; that pyramids soared and towered; that deities of stone stood by; that temples ranged themselves in reconstructed beauty, grave as the night of time whence they emerged; and that the outline of the Sphinx, motionless but aggressive, piled its dim bulk upon the atmosphere. Immensity answered to immensity. … There were vast intervals of time and there were reaches of enormous distance, yet all happened in a moment, and all happened within a little space. It was now and here. Eternity whispered in every second as in every grain of sand. Yet, while aware of so many stupendous details all at once, I was really aware of one thing only—that the spirit of ancient Egypt faced me in these two terrific figures, and that my consciousness, stretched painfully yet gloriously, included all, as She also unquestionably included them—and me.

For it seemed I shared the likeness of my two companions. Some lesser symbol, though of similar kind, obsessed me too. I tried to move, but my feet were set in stone; my arms lay fixed; my body was embedded in the rock. Sand beat sharply upon my outer surface, urged upwards in little flurries by a chilly wind. There was nothing felt: I heard the rattle of the scattering grains against my hardened body. …

And we waited for the dawn; for the resurrection of that unchanging deity who was the source and inspiration of all our glorious life. … The air grew keen and fresh. In the distance a line of sky turned from pink to violet and gold; a delicate rose next flushed the desert; a few pale stars hung fainting overhead; and the wind that brought the sunrise was already stirring. The whole land paused upon the coming of its mighty God. …

Into the pause there rose a curious sound for which we had been waiting. For it came familiarly, as though expected. I could have sworn at first that it was George Isley who sang, answering his companion. There beat behind its great volume the same note and rhythm, only so prodigiously increased that, while Moleson’s chant had waked it, it now was independent and apart. The resonant vibrations of what he sang had reached down into the places where it slept. They uttered synchronously. Egypt spoke. There was in it the deep muttering as of a thousand drums, as though the desert uttered in prodigious syllables. I listened while my heart of stone stood still. There were two voices in the sky. They spoke tremendously with each other in the dawn:

“So easily we still remain possessors of the land. … While the centuries roar past us and are gone.”

Soft with power the syllables rolled forth, yet with a booming depth as though caverns underground produced them.

“Our silence is disturbed. Pass on with the multitude towards the East. … Still in the dawn we sing the old-world wisdom. … They shall hear our speech, yet shall not hear it with their ears of flesh. At dawn our words go forth, searching the distances of sand and time across the sunlight. … At dusk they return, as upon eagles’ wings, entering again our lips of stone. … Each century one syllable, yet no sentence yet complete. While our lips are broken with the utterance. …”

It seemed that hours and months and years went past me while I listened in my sandy bed. The fragments died far away, then sounded very close again. It was as though mountain peaks sang to one another above clouds. Wind caught the muffled roar away. Wind brought it back. … Then, in a hollow pause that lasted years, conveying marvellously the passage of long periods, I heard the utterance more clearly. The leisured roll of the great voice swept through me like a flood:

“We wait and watch and listen in our loneliness. We do not close our eyes. The moon and stars sail past us, and our river finds the sea. We bring Eternity upon your broken lives. … We see you build your little lines of steel across our territory behind the thin white smoke. We hear the whistle of your messengers of iron through the air. … The nations rise and pass. The empires flutter westwards and are gone. … The sun grows older and the stars turn pale. … Winds shift the line of the horizons, and our River moves its bed. But we, everlasting and unchangeable, remain. Of water, sand and fire is our essential being, yet built within the universal air. … There is no pause in life, there is no break in death. The changes bring no end. The sun returns. … There is eternal resurrection. … But our kingdom is underground in shadow, unrealised of your little day. … Come, come! The temples still are crowded, and our Desert blesses you. Our River takes your feet. Our sand shall purify, and the fire of our God shall burn you sweetly into wisdom. … Come, then, and worship, for the time draws near. It is the dawn. …”

The voices died down into depths that the sand of ages muffled, while the flaming dawn of the East rushed up the sky. Sunrise, the great symbol of life’s endless resurrection, was at hand. About me, in immense but shadowy array, stood the whole of ancient Egypt, hanging breathlessly upon the moment of adoration. No longer stern and terrible in the splendour of their long neglect, the effigies rose erect with passionate glory, a forest of stately stone. Their granite lips were parted and their ancient eyes were wide. All faced the east. And the sun drew nearer to the rim of the attentive Desert.

XI

Emotion there seemed none, in the sense that I knew feeling. I knew, if anything, the ultimate secrets of two primitive sensations—joy and awe. … The dawn grew swiftly brighter. There was gold, as though the sands of Nubia spilt their brilliance on each shining detail; there was glory, as though the retreating tide of stars spilt their light foam upon the world; and there was passion, as though the beliefs of all the ages floated back with abandonment into the—Sun. Ruined Egypt merged into a single temple of elemental vastness whose floor was the empty desert, but whose walls rose to the stars.

Abruptly, then, chanting and rhythm ceased; they dipped below. Sand muffled them. And the Sun looked down upon its ancient world. …

A radiant warmth poured through me. I found that I could move my limbs again. A sense of triumphant life ran through my stony frame. For one passing second I heard the shower of gritty particles upon my surface like sand blown upwards by a gust of wind, but this time I could feel the sting of it upon my skin. It passed. The drenching heat bathed me from head to foot, while stony insensibility gave place with returning consciousness to flesh and blood. The sun had risen. … I was alive, but I was—changed.

It seemed I opened my eyes. An immense relief was in me. I turned; I drew a deep, refreshing breath; I stretched one leg upon a thick, green carpet. Something had left me; another thing had returned. I sat up, conscious of welcome release, of freedom, of escape.

There was some violent, disorganising break. I found myself; I found Moleson; I found George Isley too. He had got shifted in that room without my being aware of it. Isley had risen. He came upon me like a blow. I saw him move his arms. Fire flashed from below his hands; and I realised then that he was turning on the electric lights. They emerged from different points along the walls, in the alcove, beneath the ceiling, by the writing-table; and one had just that minute blazed into my eyes from a bracket close above me. I was back again in the Present among modern things.

But, while most of the details presented themselves gradually to my recovered senses, Isley returned with this curious effect of speed and distance—like a blow upon the mind. From great height and from prodigious size—he dropped. I seemed to find him rushing at me. Moleson was simply “there”; there was no speed or sudden change in him as with the other. Motionless at the piano, his long thin hands lay down upon the keys yet did not strike them. But Isley came back like lightning into the little room, signs of the monstrous obsession still about his altering features. There was battle and worship mingled in his deep-set eyes. His mouth, though set, was smiling. With a shudder I positively saw the vastness slipping from his face as shadows from a stretch of broken cliff. There was this awful mingling of proportions. The colossal power that had resumed his being drew slowly inwards. There was collapse in him. And upon the sunburned cheek of his rugged face I saw a tear.

Poignant revulsion caught me then for a moment. The present showed itself in rags. The reduction of scale was painful. I yearned for the splendour that was gone, yet still seemed so hauntingly almost within reach. The cheapness of the hotel room, the glaring ugliness of its tinsel decoration, the baseness of ideals where utility instead of beauty, gain instead of worship, governed life—this, with the dwindled aspect of my companions to the insignificance of marionettes, brought a hungry pain that was at first intolerable. In the glare of light I noticed the small round face of the portable clock upon the mantelpiece, showing half-past eleven. Moleson had been two hours at the piano. And this measuring faculty of my mind completed the disillusionment. I was, indeed, back among present things. The mechanical spirit of Today imprisoned me again.

For a considerable interval we neither moved nor spoke; the sudden change left the emotions in confusion; we had leaped from a height, from the top of the pyramid, from a star—and the crash of landing scattered thought. I stole a glance at Isley, wondering vaguely why he was there at all; the look of resignation had replaced the power in his face; the tear was brushed away. There was no struggle in him now, no sign of resistance; there was abandonment only; he seemed insignificant. The real George Isley was elsewhere: he himself had not returned.

By jerks, as it were, and by awkward stages, then, we all three came back to common things again. I found that we were talking ordinarily, asking each other questions, answering, lighting cigarettes, and all the rest. Moleson played some commonplace chords upon the piano, while he leaned back listlessly in his chair, putting in sentences now and again and chatting idly to whichever of us would listen. And Isley came slowly across the room towards me, holding out cigarettes. His dark brown face had shadows on it. He looked exhausted, worn, like some soldier broken in the wars.

“You liked it?” I heard his thin voice asking. There was no interest, no expression; it was not the real Isley who spoke; it was the little part of him that had come back. He smiled like a marvellous automaton.

Mechanically I took the cigarette he offered me, thinking confusedly what answer I could make.

“It’s irresistible,” I murmured; “I understand that it’s easier to go.”

“Sweeter as well,” he whispered with a sigh, “and very wonderful!”

XII

The hand that lit my cigarette, I saw, was trembling. A desire to do something violent woke in me suddenly—to move energetically, to push or drive something away.

“What was it?” I asked abruptly, in a louder, half-challenging voice, intended for the man at the piano. “Such a performance—upon others—without first asking their permission—seems to me unpermissible—it’s—”

And it was Moleson who replied. He ignored the end of my sentence as though he had not heard it. He strolled over to our side, taking a cigarette and pressing it carefully into shape between his long thin fingers.

“You may well ask,” he answered quietly; “but it’s not so easy to tell. We discovered it”—he nodded towards Isley—“two years ago in the ‘Valley.’ It lay beside a Priest, a very important personage, apparently, and was part of the Ritual he used in the worship of the sun. In the Museum now—you can see it any day at the Boulak—it is simply labelled ‘Hymn to Ra.’ The period was Aknahton’s.”

“The words, yes,” put in Isley, who was listening closely.

“The words?” repeated Moleson in a curious tone. “There are no words. It’s all really a manipulation of the vowel sounds. And the rhythm, or chanting, or whatever you like to call it, I—I invented myself. The Egyptians did not write their music, you see.” He suddenly searched my face a moment with questioning eyes. “Any words you heard,” he said, “or thought you heard, were merely your own interpretation.”

I stared at him, making no rejoinder.

“They made use of what they called a ‘root-language’ in their rituals,” he went on, “and it consisted entirely of vowel sounds. There were no consonants. For vowel sounds, you see, run on forever without end or beginning, whereas consonants interrupt their flow and break it up and limit it. A consonant has no sound of its own at all. Real language is continuous.”

We stood a moment, smoking in silence. I understood then that this thing Moleson had done was based on definite knowledge. He had rendered some fragment of an ancient Ritual he and Isley had unearthed together, and while he knew its effect upon the latter, he chanced it on myself. Not otherwise, I feel, could it have influenced me in the extraordinary way it did. In the faith and poetry of a nation lies its soul-life, and the gigantic faith of Egypt blazed behind the rhythm of that long, monotonous chant. There were blood and heart and nerves in it. Millions had heard it sung; millions had wept and prayed and yearned; it was ensouled by the passion of that marvellous civilisation that loved the godhead of the Sun, and that now hid, waiting but still alive, below the ground. The majestic faith of ancient Egypt poured up with it—that tremendous, burning elaboration of the afterlife and of Eternity that was the pivot of those spacious days. For centuries vast multitudes, led by their royal priests, had uttered this very form and ritual—believed it, lived it, felt it. The rising of the sun remained its climax. Its spiritual power still clung to the great ruined symbols. The faith of a buried civilisation had burned back into the present and into our hearts as well.

And a curious respect for the man who was able to produce this effect upon two modern minds crept over me, and mingled with the repulsion that I felt. I looked furtively at his withered, dried-up features. He wore some vague and shadowy impress still of what had just been in him. There was a stony appearance in his shrunken cheeks. He looked smaller. I saw him lessened. I thought of him as he had been so short a time before, imprisoned in his great stone captors that had obsessed him. …

“There’s tremendous power in it—an awful power,” I stammered, more to break the oppressive pause than for any desire in me to speak with him. “It brings back Egypt in some extraordinary way—ancient Egypt, I mean—brings it close—into the heart.” My words ran on of their own accord almost. I spoke with a hush, unwittingly. There was awe in me. Isley had moved away towards the window, leaving me face to face with this strange incarnation of another age.

“It must,” he replied, deep light still glowing in his eyes, “for the soul of the old days is in it. No one, I think, can hear it and remain the same. It expresses, you see, the essential passion and beauty of that gorgeous worship, that splendid faith, that reasonable and intelligent worship of the sun, the only scientific belief the world has ever known. Its popular form, of course, was largely superstitious, but the sacerdotal form—the form used by the priests, that is—who understood the relationship between colour, sound and symbol, was—”

He broke off suddenly, as though he had been speaking to himself. We sat down. George Isley leaned out of the window with his back to us, watching the desert in the moonless night.

“You have tried its effect before upon—others?” I asked point-blank.

“Upon myself,” he answered shortly.

“Upon others?” I insisted.

He hesitated an instant.

“Upon one other—yes,” he admitted.

“Intentionally?” And something quivered in me as I asked it.

He shrugged his shoulders slightly. “I’m merely a speculative archaeologist,” he smiled, “and—and an imaginative Egyptologist. My bounden duty is to reconstruct the past so that it lives for others.”

An impulse rose in me to take him by the throat.

“You know perfectly well, of course, the magical effect it’s sure—likely at least—to have?”

He stared steadily at me through the cigarette smoke. To this day I cannot think exactly what it was in this man that made me shudder.

“I’m sure of nothing,” he replied smoothly, “but I consider it quite legitimate to try. Magical—the word you used—has no meaning for me. If such a thing exists, it is merely scientific—undiscovered or forgotten knowledge.” An insolent, aggressive light shone in his eyes as he spoke; his manner was almost truculent. “You refer, I take it, to—our friend—rather than to yourself?”

And with difficulty I met his singular stare. From his whole person something still emanated that was forbidding, yet overmasteringly persuasive. It brought back the notion of that invisible Web, that dim gauze curtain, that motionless Influence lying waiting at the centre for its prey, those monstrous and mysterious Items standing, alert and watchful, through the centuries. “You mean,” he added lower, “his altered attitude to life—his going?”

To hear him use the words, the very phrase, struck me with sudden chill. Before I could answer, however, and certainly before I could master the touch of horror that rushed over me, I heard him continuing in a whisper. It seemed again that he spoke to himself as much as he spoke to me.

“The soul, I suppose, has the right to choose its own conditions and surroundings. To pass elsewhere involves translation, not extinction.” He smoked a moment in silence, then said another curious thing, looking up into my face with an expression of intense earnestness. Something genuine in him again replaced the pose of cynicism. “The soul is eternal and can take its place anywhere, regardless of mere duration. What is there in the vulgar and superficial Present that should hold it so exclusively; and where can it find today the belief, the faith, the beauty that are the very essence of its life—where in the rush and scatter of this tawdry age can it make its home? Shall it flutter forever in a valley of dry bones, when a living Past lies ready and waiting with loveliness, strength, and glory?” He moved closer; he touched my arm; I felt his breath upon my face. “Come with us,” he whispered awfully; “come back with us! Withdraw your life from the rubbish of this futile ugliness! Come back and worship with us in the spirit of the Past. Take up the old, old splendour, the glory, the immense conceptions, the wondrous certainty, the ineffable knowledge of essentials. It all lies about you still; it’s calling, ever calling; it’s very close; it draws you day and night—calling, calling, calling. …”

His voice died off curiously into distance on the word; I can hear it to this day, and the soft, droning quality in the intense yet fading tone: “Calling, calling, calling.” But his eyes turned wicked. I felt the sinister power of the man. I was aware of madness in his thought and mind. The Past he sought to glorify I saw black, as with the forbidding Egyptian darkness of a plague. It was not beauty but Death that I heard calling, calling, calling.

“It’s real,” he went on, hardly aware that I shrank, “and not a dream. These ruined symbols still remain in touch with that which was. They are potent today as they were six thousand years ago. The amazing life of those days brims behind them. They are not mere masses of oppressive stone; they express in visible form great powers that still are—knowable.” He lowered his head, peered up into my face, and whispered. Something secret passed into his eyes.

“I saw you change,” came the words below his breath, “as you saw the change in us. But only worship can produce that change. The soul assumes the qualities of the deity it worships. The powers of its deity possess it and transform it into its own likeness. You also felt it. You also were possessed. I saw the stone-faced deity upon your own.”

I seemed to shake myself as a dog shakes water from its body. I stood up. I remember that I stretched my hands out as though to push him from me and expel some creeping influence from my mind. I remember another thing as well. But for the reality of the sequel, and but for the matter-of-fact result still facing me today in the disappearance of George Isley—the loss to the present time of all George Isley was—I might have found subject for laughter in what I saw. Comedy was in it certainly. Yet it was both ghastly and terrific. Deep horror crept below the aspect of the ludicrous, for the apparent mimicry cloaked truth. It was appalling because it was real.

In the large mirror that reflected the room behind me I saw myself and Moleson; I saw Isley too in the background by the open window. And the attitude of all three was the attitude of hieroglyphics come to life. My arms indeed were stretched, but not stretched, as I had thought, in mere self-defence. They were stretched—unnaturally. The forearms made those strange obtuse angles that the old carved granite wears, the palms of the hands held upwards, the heads thrown back, the legs advanced, the bodies stiffened into postures that expressed forgotten, ancient minds. The physical conformation of all three was monstrous; and yet reverence and truth dictated even the uncouthness of the gestures. Something in all three of us inspired the forms our bodies had assumed. Our attitudes expressed buried yearnings, emotions, tendencies—whatever they may be termed—that the spirit of the Past evoked.

I saw the reflected picture but for a moment. I dropped my arms, aware of foolishness in my way of standing. Moleson moved forward with his long, significant stride, and at the same instant Isley came up quickly and joined us from his place by the open window. We looked into each other’s faces without a word. There was this little pause that lasted perhaps ten seconds. But in that pause I felt the entire world slide past me. I heard the centuries rush by at headlong speed. The present dipped away. Existence was no longer in a line that stretched two ways; it was a circle in which ourselves, together with Past and Future, stood motionless at the centre, all details equally accessible at once. The three of us were falling, falling backwards. …

“Come!” said the voice of Moleson solemnly, but with the sweetness as of a child anticipating joy. “Come! Let us go together, for the boat of Ra has crossed the Underworld. The darkness has been conquered. Let us go out together and find the dawn. Listen! It is calling, calling, calling. …”

XIII

I was aware of rushing, but it was the soul in me that rushed. It experienced dizzy, unutterable alterations. Thousands of emotions, intense and varied, poured through me at lightning speed, each satisfyingly known, yet gone before its name appeared. The life of many centuries tore headlong back with me, and, as in drowning, this epitome of existence shot in a few seconds the steep slopes the Past had so laboriously built up. The changes flashed and passed. I wept and prayed and worshipped; I loved and suffered; I battled, lost and won. Down the gigantic scale of ages that telescoped thus into a few brief moments, the soul in me went sliding backwards towards a motionless, reposeful Past.

I remember foolish details that interrupted the immense descent—I put on coat and hat; I remember someone’s words, strangely sounding as when some bird wakes up and sings at midnight—“We’ll take the little door; the front one’s locked by now”; and I have a vague recollection of the outline of the great hotel, with its colonnades and terraces, fading behind me through the air. But these details merely flickered and disappeared, as though I fell earthwards from a star and passed feathers or blown leaves upon the way. There was no friction as my soul dropped backwards into time; the flight was easy and silent as a dream. I felt myself sucked down into gulfs whose emptiness offered no resistance … until at last the appalling speed decreased of its own accord, and the dizzy flight became a kind of gentle floating. It changed imperceptibly into a gliding motion, as though the angle altered. My feet, quite naturally, were on the ground, moving through something soft that clung to them and rustled while it clung.

I looked up and saw the bright armies of the stars. In front of me I recognised the flat-topped, shadowy ridges; on both sides lay the open expanses of familiar wilderness; and beside me, one on either hand, moved two figures who were my companions. We were in the desert, but it was the desert of thousands of years ago. My companions, moreover, though familiar to some part of me, seemed strangers or half known. Their names I strove in vain to capture; Mosely, Ilson, sounded in my head, mingled together falsely. And when I stole a glance at them, I saw dark lines of mannikins unfilled with substance, and was aware of the grotesque gestures of living hieroglyphics. It seemed for an instant that their arms were bound behind their backs impossibly, and that their heads turned sharply across their lineal shoulders.

But for a moment only; for at a second glance I saw them solid and compact; their names came back to me; our arms were linked together as we walked. We had already covered a great distance, for my limbs were aching and my breath was short. The air was cold, the silence absolute. It seemed, in this faint light, that the desert flowed beneath our feet, rather than that we advanced by taking steps. Cliffs with hooded tops moved past us, boulders glided, mounds of sand slid by. And then I heard a voice upon my left that was surely Moleson speaking:

“Towards Enet our feet are set,” he half sang, half murmured, “towards Enet-te-ntōrē. There, in the House of Birth, we shall dedicate our hearts and lives anew.”

And the language, no less than the musical intonation of his voice, enraptured me. For I understood he spoke of Denderah, in whose majestic temple recent hands had painted with deathless colours the symbols of our cosmic relationships with the zodiacal signs. And Denderah was our great seat of worship of the goddess Hathor, the Egyptian Aphrodite, bringer of love and joy. The falcon-headed Horus was her husband, from whom, in his home at Edfu, we imbibed swift kinds of power. And—it was the time of the New Year, the great feast when the forces of the living earth turn upwards into happy growth.

We were on foot across the desert towards Denderah, and this sand we trod was the sand of thousands of years ago.

The paralysis of time and distance involved some amazing lightness of the spirit that, I suppose, touched ecstasy. There was intoxication in the soul. I was not divided from the stars, nor separate from this desert that rushed with us. The unhampered wind blew freshly from my nerves and skin, and the Nile, glimmering faintly on our right, lay with its lapping waves in both my hands. I knew the life of Egypt, for it was in me, over me, round me. I was a part of it. We went happily, like birds to meet the sunrise. There were no pits of measured time and interval that could detain us. We flowed, yet were at rest; we were endlessly alive; present and future alike were inconceivable; we were in the Kingdom of the Past.

The Pyramids were just a-building, and the army of Obelisks looked about them, proud of their first balance; Thebes swung her hundred gates upon the world. New, shining Memphis glittered with myriad reflections into waters that the tears of Isis sweetened, and the cliffs of Abou Simbel were still innocent of their gigantic progeny. Alone, the Sphinx, linking timelessness with time, brooded unguessed and underived upon an alien world. We marched within antiquity towards Denderah. …

How long we marched, how fast, how far we went, I can remember as little as the marvellous speech that passed across me while my two companions spoke together. I only remember that suddenly a wave of pain disturbed my wondrous happiness and caused my calm, which had seemed beyond all reach of break, to fall away. I heard their voices abruptly with a kind of terror. A sensation of fear, of loss, of nightmare bewilderment came over me like cold wind. What they lived naturally, true to their inmost hearts, I lived merely by means of a temperamental sympathy. And the stage had come at which my powers failed. Exhaustion overtook me. I wilted. The strain—the abnormal backwards stretch of consciousness that was put upon me by another—gave way and broke. I heard their voices faint and horrible. My joy was extinguished. A glare of horror fell upon the desert and the stars seemed evil. An anguishing desire for the safe and wholesome Present usurped all this mad yearning to obtain the Past. My feet fell out of step. The rushing of the desert paused. I unlinked my arms. We stopped all three.

The actual spot is to this day well known to me. I found it afterwards, I even photographed it. It lies actually not far from Helouan—a few miles at most beyond the Solitary Palm, where slopes of undulating sand mark the opening of a strange, enticing valley called the Wadi Gerraui. And it is enticing because it beckons and leads on. Here, amid torn gorges of a limestone wilderness, there is suddenly soft yellow sand that flows and draws the feet onward. It slips away with one too easily; always the next ridge and basin must be seen, each time a little farther. It has the quality of decoying. The cliffs say, No; but this streaming sand invites. In its flowing curves of gold there is enchantment.

And it was here upon its very lips we stopped, the rhythm of our steps broken, our hearts no longer one. My temporary rapture vanished. I was aware of fear. For the Present rushed upon me with attack in it, and I felt that my mind was arrested close upon the edge of madness. Something cleared and lifted in my brain.

The soul, indeed, could “choose its dwelling-place”; but to live elsewhere completely was the choice of madness, and to live divorced from all the sweet wholesome business of Today involved an exile that was worse than madness. It was death. My heart burned for George Isley. I remembered the tear upon his cheek. The agony of his struggle I shared suddenly with him. Yet with him was the reality, with me a sympathetic reflection merely. He was already too far gone to fight. …

I shall never forget the desolation of that strange scene beneath the morning stars. The desert lay down and watched us. We stood upon the brink of a little broken ridge, looking into the valley of golden sand. This sand gleamed soft and wonderful in the starlight some twenty feet below. The descent was easy—but I would not move. I refused to advance another step. I saw my companions in the mysterious half-light beside me peering over the edge, Moleson in front a little.

And I turned to him, sure of the part I meant to play, yet conscious painfully of my helplessness. My personality seemed a straw in midstream that spun in a futile effort to arrest the flood that bore it. There was vivid human conflict in the moment’s silence. It was an eddy that paused in the great body of the tide. And then I spoke. Oh, I was ashamed of the insignificance of my voice and the weakness of my little personality.

“Moleson, we go no farther with you. We have already come too far. We now turn back.”

Behind my words were a paltry thirty years. His answer drove sixty centuries against me. For his voice was like the wind that passed whispering down the stream of yellow sand below us. He smiled.

“Our feet are set towards Enet-te-ntōrē. There is no turning back. Listen! It is calling, calling, calling!”

“We will go home,” I cried, in a tone I vainly strove to make imperative.

“Our home is there,” he sang, pointing with one long thin arm towards the brightening east, “for the Temple calls us and the River takes our feet. We shall be in the House of Birth to meet the sunrise—”

“You lie,” I cried again, “you speak the lies of madness, and this Past you seek is the House of Death. It is the kingdom of the underworld.”

The words tore wildly, impotently out of me. I seized George Isley’s arm.

“Come back with me,” I pleaded vehemently, my heart aching with a nameless pain for him. “We’ll retrace our steps. Come home with me! Come back! Listen! The Present calls you sweetly!”

His arm slipped horribly out of my grasp that had seemed to hold it so tightly. Moleson, already below us in the yellow sand, looked small with distance. He was gliding rapidly farther with uncanny swiftness. The diminution of his form was ghastly. It was like a doll’s. And his voice rose up, faint as with the distance of great gulfs of space.

“Calling … calling. … You hear it forever calling …”

It died away with the wind along that sandy valley, and the Past swept in a flood across the brightening sky. I swayed as though a storm was at my back. I reeled. Almost I went too—over the crumbling edge into the sand.

“Come back with me! Come home!” I cried more faintly. “The Present alone is real. There is work, ambition, duty. There is beauty too—the beauty of good living! And there is love! There is—a woman … calling, calling … !”

That other voice took up the word below me. I heard the faint refrain sing down the sandy walls. The wild, sweet pang in it was marvellous.

“Our feet are set for Enet-te-ntōrē. It is calling, calling … !”

My voice fell into nothingness. George Isley was below me now, his outline tiny against the sheet of yellow sand. And the sand was moving. The desert rushed again. The human figures receded swiftly into the Past they had reconstructed with the creative yearning of their souls.

I stood alone upon the edge of crumbling limestone, helplessly watching them. It was amazing what I witnessed, while the shafts of crimson dawn rose up the sky. The enormous desert turned alive to the horizon with gold and blue and silver. The purple shadows melted into grey. The flat-topped ridges shone. Huge messengers of light flashed everywhere at once. The radiance of sunrise dazzled my outer sight.

But if my eyes were blinded, my inner sight was focused the more clearly upon what followed. I witnessed the disappearance of George Isley. There was a dreadful magic in the picture. The pair of them, small and distant below me in that little sandy hollow, stood out sharply defined as in a miniature. I saw their outlines neat and terrible like some ghastly inset against the enormous scenery. Though so close to me in actual space, they were centuries away in time. And a dim, vast shadow was about them that was not mere shadow of the ridges. It encompassed them; it moved, crawling over the sand, obliterating them. Within it, like insects lost in amber, they became visibly imprisoned, dwindled in size, borne deep away, absorbed.

And then I recognised the outline. Once more, but this time recumbent and spread flat upon the desert’s face, I knew the monstrous shapes of the twin obsessing symbols. The spirit of ancient Egypt lay over all the land, tremendous in the dawn. The sunrise summoned her. She lay prostrate before the deity. The shadows of the towering Colossi lay prostrate too. The little humans, with their worshipping and conquered hearts, lay deep within them.

George Isley I saw clearest. The distinctness, the reality were appalling. He was naked, robbed, undressed. I saw him a skeleton, picked clean to the very bones as by an acid. His life lay hid in the being of that mighty Past. Egypt had absorbed him. He was gone. …

I closed my eyes, but I could not keep them closed. They opened of their own accord. The three of us were nearing the great hotel that rose yellow, with shuttered windows, in the early sunshine. A wind blew briskly from the north across the Mokattam Hills. There were soft cannonball clouds dotted about the sky, and across the Nile, where the mist lay in a line of white, I saw the tops of the Pyramids gleaming like mountain peaks of gold. A string of camels, laden with white stone, went past us. I heard the crying of the natives in the streets of Helouan, and as we went up the steps the donkeys arrived and camped in the sandy road beside their bersim till the tourists claimed them.

“Good morning,” cried Abdullah, the man who owned them. “You all go Sakkhâra today, or Memphis? Beat’ful day today, and vair good donkeys!”

Moleson went up to his room without a word, and Isley did the same. I thought he staggered a moment as he turned the passage corner from my sight. His face wore a look of vacancy that some call peace. There was radiance in it. It made me shudder. Aching in mind and body, and no word spoken, I followed their example. I went upstairs to bed, and slept a dreamless sleep till after sunset. …

XIV

And I woke with a lost, unhappy feeling that a withdrawing tide had left me on the shore, alone and desolate. My first instinct was for my friend, George Isley. And I noticed a square, white envelope with my name upon it in his writing.

Before I opened it I knew quite well what words would be inside:

“We are going up to Thebes,” the note informed me simply. “We leave by the night train. If you care to—” But the last four words were scratched out again, though not so thickly that I could not read them. Then came the address of the Egyptologist’s house and the signature, very firmly traced, “Yours ever, George Isley.” I glanced at my watch and saw that it was after seven o’clock. The night train left at half-past six. They had already started. …

The pain of feeling forsaken, left behind, was deep and bitter, for myself; but what I felt for him, old friend and comrade, was even more intense, since it was hopeless. Fear and conventional emotion had stopped me at the very gates of an amazing possibility—some state of consciousness that, realising the Past, might doff the Present, and by slipping out of Time, experience Eternity. That was the seduction I had escaped by the uninspired resistance of my pettier soul. Yet, he, my friend, yielding in order to conquer, had obtained an awful prize—ah, I understood the picture’s other side as well, with an unutterable poignancy of pity—the prize of immobility which is sheer stagnation, the imagined bliss which is a false escape, the dream of finding beauty away from present things. From that dream the awakening must be rude indeed. Clutching at vanished stars, he had clutched the oldest illusion in the world. To me it seemed the negation of life that had betrayed him. The pity of it burned me like a flame.

But I did not “care to follow” him and his companion. I waited at Helouan for his return, filling the empty days with yet emptier explanations. I felt as a man who sees what he loves sinking down into clear, deep water, still within visible reach, yet gone beyond recovery. Moleson had taken him back to Thebes; and Egypt, monstrous effigy of the Past, had caught her prey.

The rest, moreover, is easily told. Moleson I never saw again. To this day I have never seen him, though his subsequent books are known to me, with the banal fact that he is numbered with those energetic and deluded enthusiasts who start a new religion, obtain notoriety, a few hysterical followers and—oblivion.

George Isley, however, returned to Helouan after a fortnight’s absence. I saw him, knew him, talked and had my meals with him. We even did slight expeditions together. He was gentle and delightful as a woman who has loved a wonderful ideal and attained to it—in memory. All roughness was gone out of him; he was smooth and polished as a crystal surface that reflects whatever is near enough to ask a picture. Yet his appearance shocked me inexpressibly: there was nothing in him—nothing. It was the representation of George Isley that came back from Thebes; the outer simulacra; the shell that walks the London streets today. I met no vestige of the man I used to know. George Isley had disappeared.

With this marvellous automaton I lived another month. The horror of him kept me company in the hotel where he moved among the cosmopolitan humanity as a ghost that visits the sunlight yet has its home elsewhere.

This empty image of George Isley lived with me in our Helouan hotel until the winds of early March informed his physical frame that discomfort was in the air, and that he might as well move elsewhere—elsewhere happening to be northwards.

And he left just as he stayed—automatically. His brain obeyed the conventional stimuli to which his nerves, and consequently his muscles, were accustomed. It sounds so foolish. But he took his ticket automatically; he gave the natural and adequate reasons automatically; he chose his ship and landing-place in the same way that ordinary people chose these things; he said goodbye like any other man who leaves casual acquaintances and “hopes” to meet them again; he lived, that is to say, entirely in his brain. His heart, his emotions, his temperament and personality, that nameless sum-total for which the great sympathetic nervous system is accountable—all this, his soul, had gone elsewhere. This once vigorous, gifted being had become a normal, comfortable man that everybody could understand—a commonplace nonentity. He was precisely what the majority expected him to be—ordinary; a good fellow; a man of the world; he was “delightful.” He merely reflected daily life without partaking of it. To the majority it was hardly noticeable; “very pleasant” was a general verdict. His ambition, his restlessness, his zeal had gone; that tireless zest whose driving power is yearning had taken flight, leaving behind it physical energy without spiritual desire. His soul had found its nest and flown to it. He lived in the chimera of the Past, serene, indifferent, detached. I saw him immense, a shadowy, majestic figure, standing—ah, not moving!—in a repose that was satisfying because it could not change. The size, the mystery, the immobility that caged him in seemed to me—terrible. For I dared not intrude upon his awful privacy, and intimacy between us there was none. Of his experiences at Thebes I asked no single question—it was somehow not possible or legitimate; he, equally, vouchsafed no word of explanation—it was uncommunicable to a dweller in the Present. Between us was this barrier we both respected. He peered at modern life, incurious, listless, apathetic, through a dim, gauze curtain. He was behind it.

People round us were going to Sakkhâra and the Pyramids, to see the Sphinx by moonlight, to dream at Edfu and at Denderah. Others described their journeys to Assouan, Khartoum and Abou Simbel, and gave details of their encampments in the desert. Wind, wind, wind! The winds of Egypt blew and sang and sighed. From the White Nile came the travellers, and from the Blue Nile, from the Fayum, and from nameless excavations without end. They talked and wrote their books. They had the magpie knowledge of the present. The Egyptologists, big and little, read the writing on the wall and put the hieroglyphs and papyri into modern language. Alone George Isley knew the secret. He lived it.

And the high passionate calm, the lofty beauty, the glamour and enchantment that are the spell of this thrice-haunted land, were in my soul as well—sufficiently for me to interpret his condition. I could not leave, yet having left I could not stay away. I yearned for the Egypt that he knew. No word I uttered; speech could not approach it. We wandered by the Nile together, and through the groves of palms that once were Memphis. The sandy wastes beyond the Pyramids knew our footsteps; the Mokattam Ridges, purple at evening and golden in the dawn, held our passing shadows as we silently went by. At no single dawn or sunset was he to be found indoors, and it became my habit to accompany him—the joy of worship in his soul was marvellous. The great, still skies of Egypt watched us, the hanging stars, the gigantic dome of blue; we felt together that burning southern wind; the golden sweetness of the sun lay in our blood as we saw the great boats take the northern breeze upstream. Immensity was everywhere and this golden magic of the sun. …

But it was in the Desert especially, where only sun and wind observe the faint signalling of Time, where space is nothing because it is not divided, and where no detail reminds the heart that the world is called Today—it was in the desert this curtain hung most visibly between us, he on that side, I on this. It was transparent. He was with a multitude no man can number. Towering to the moon, yet spreading backwards towards his burning source of life, drawn out by the sun and by the crystal air into some vast interior magnitude, the spirit of George Isley hung beside me, close yet far away, in the haze of olden days.

And, sometimes, he moved. I was aware of gestures. His head was raised to listen. One arm swung shadowy across the sea of broken ridges. From leagues away a line of sand rose slowly. There was a rustling. Another—an enormous—arm emerged to meet his own, and two stupendous figures drew together. Poised above Time, yet throned upon the centuries, They knew eternity. So easily they remained possessors of the land. Facing the east, they waited for the dawn. And their marvellously forgotten singing poured across the world. …

A Holiday Down the Danube with Punt and Tent

Different kinds of men like different kinds of holidays, but as a boy I always had a natural longing to get off somewhere in a boat and go as fast as possible and run as many risks as possible; and I find that as a man my love for this sort of sport has strengthened rather than weakened. So, when my holidays came round last year I chose three friends of similar tastes and started off for a tour of exploration down the Danube in a punt.

We bought our tents in London—ordinary little A tents, with pegs and poles to cut wherever we happened to be in camp—and cork mattresses, and mackintosh groundsheets to put under them, and good warm blankets to put over ourselves, and then took the train for Ulm. Our boat we hoped to buy in Ulm. These purchases were not very expensive. Cork mattresses, that ought to last a careful man a lifetime, cost about 8s., and ground sheets, with holes round the edges to pass string through when using them to wrap up kit in, can be bought for a few shillings.

The subject of tents, of course, is a big one, and the result of my own experience in many kinds is that the gipsy tent, which can be made by any boy himself, is the best, cheapest, and most comfortable one in the world. It is the net result of generations of camping out by the gipsies, and gipsies know their business. It gives more room than any other kind, for the sides bulge outwards, and it is less likely to blow down. On this particular occasion, however, having to start at a day’s notice, and having the little A tents ready to hand, we elected to lose no time making new tents, but to start with what we had.

At Ulm, the sight of the Danube tearing and foaming along in its great sweep through the town filled us with delight. We soon found a secondhand fisherman’s boat, which we bought for a few pounds (this is the chief expense, but remember it saves hotels, tips, rent, and endless extras of travelling, and is well worth a price), and began to pack her. She was flat-bottomed and 20 feet long, about 3 feet wide, and the ends, bow and stern, were covered in and sloped upwards, square-nosed like a Thames punt. With all our luggage and our four big bodies on board she only drew a matter of four to five inches of water, and the whole way down this river, which is full of very unexpected shallows and shingle-beds, we ran aground only once.

The boat was very heavy, and steering was a matter to be learnt, and Ulm is not a good place to begin practising, for the river sweeps under two bridges before you can learn how to hold the huge paddles (7 feet long and weighing 12 lb.), much less how to manipulate them. But Fortune favoured us, and we swept under the arches on the crests of foaming waves, and Ulm was out of sight in less than five minutes.

The current here, and for many miles below Ulm, is so swift that, with easy paddling, the boat travels at a rate of ten or twelve miles an hour, and it is quite impossible to land without first turning completely round and paddling against the stream. This lets the boat down stream at a pace that makes it possible to grab the shore or the willows and jump out.

Our provisions will interest campers. We had a side of bacon and 10 lb. of good English tea; sacks of dried milk (Just-Hatmaker Process), which only needs dissolving in hot water to be ready for use; several pounds of oatmeal; several huge loaves of black bread (keeps moist longer than white bread); a sack of potatoes, and the usual extras of sugar, jam, cheese, and so forth. Eggs, butter, chickens, and the like we could always buy at the villages as we passed them. Here, then, was fare for a king, and, with frying-pan, stew-pot, tea-pail, and filter for the dirty river water, we had everything complete. Fortune did the rest for us, and supplied perfect weather and a racing river swollen with recent rains. And, as one of us was married and had brought his wife with him, we were sure of having good cooking and the dishes always properly washed up and spick and span. Make no mistake about it, a woman is not a bore in camp. The right woman is an immense addition to a camping party; only be sure first she is the right woman.

Ulm lies on the borderland of Würtemberg and Bavaria, but the river soon carried us flying into the latter country. Two hundred yards wide and very deep, the water rushes along with a hissing, fizzing sound that is said to be heard only on the Danube. On no other river have I heard it. Some say this peculiar noise, like the escaping of steam, is caused by the great speed of the water tearing the shingle along the riverbed. I cannot say. I only know it adds to the interest, and makes you feel you are dealing with something that is very much alive and kicking.

The middle of the river we found to be the safest channel. Even here there are whirlpools and strange eddies; but close in shore the steering is very difficult indeed, and the danger from sunken snags and sudden shallows made it wiser to stick to the middle. The steering strokes are the same as those used in a canoe. I had once before been down the Danube from its source to Budapest (1,000 miles) in a Canadian canoe, and compared with the lightness of that craft, and the instantaneous way in which she answered to the least turn of the paddle, steering in this huge flat bottomed punt seemed a very severe kind of exercise. So many turns of the paddle are necessary before the bows answer. Perhaps the current meanwhile is sweeping you sideways, or a whirlpool jumps up under the boat, or you strike a back-eddy, or something strange happens to complicate the impetus and direction of the boat, and, lo! she does not answer to your stroke. You have to lift the huge paddle and strain every muscle again to repeat your stroke and bring her round. In the end she always comes round, but if a rock, or a bridge, or a rapid is close upon you, this loss of time is a serious matter! A canoe answers at once, of course, like a living thing. But this old punt was a dignified old lady, and wanted coaxing and pushing and much persuading. Banging her violently was no use. She taught the steersman patience as well as skill before he had done with her.

To name the endless succession of towns and villages we passed through in our swift journey across Bavaria would not interest you much. We did not linger among the houses long, except to buy provisions. The people stared, asked endless questions, and followed us down to the boat. In the villages no one knew anything about the river beyond a few miles above and below their particular dwelling-place. Certainly none of them knew that it rose in the Black Forest and ended in the Black Sea, and when we told them we were going to Vienna they stared, open-mouthed, at us, and thought we were not telling the truth. There are scarcely any boats on this part of the Danube; no steamers and no pleasure-craft. A few fishermen’s punts may be seen close in shore, but the stream is too terribly swift for boats, and even to cross the river and make a point opposite you are obliged to start well above it or you will be swept down half a mile below your destination.

Wild life haunts the shores everywhere. We saw deer jumping into the water after sunrise; foxes walking quietly along the shingle; every sort of water-rat, stoat, easel, and otter; snakes swimming across; hares sitting among the grassy banks, and fawns peering at us from the under growth as we rushed by, and showing no signs of alarm. Wild duck were very plentiful, and we saw storks in great number, fishing, solitary on a shingle-bed, or standing with twenty others in a group; hawks, buzzards, plover, grey crows, and, lower down, cormorants were very plentiful indeed, and quite tame. They never moved till we were close upon them, and we passed hundreds of plover sound asleep on little shingle-beds that did not even wake as we raced past them.

We usually camped about six o’clock, either on an island or in a grove of trees. Wood was plentiful, and we were always ravenous. Bathing was a cold operation, and swimming needed care, for the icy water and the tearing current were not things to be trifled with. In the early mornings the camp was often swathed in mist, but soon after breakfast it cleared away and the sun beat down fiercely and dried everything in a very short time.

Sometimes, when we camped too near villages, the police would pay us a visit. The sight of two tents and four foreigners without passports was often too much for their equanimity, and they would threaten to arrest us and hold our baggage till we could prove who we were and show that our intentions were not dangerous to the great German Empire. Some of these men were officious and anxious to show their authority, but in the end they all went away looking rather foolish with their helmets and bayonets. We never had any serious trouble, and once we came across a really intelligent policeman, who saw at once we were only holiday-making, and was greatly interested in our journey and tried to help in every way.

The peasants were invariably nice and kind, bringing us milk and eggs and fresh water and bread, and sometimes partaking of our humble fare. At night we lay round a good fire and discussed the events of the day and made plans for the next, but by nine o’clock we were always in bed and asleep, and the moon shone down on a peaceful little camp under the trees, with two white tents, a smouldering fire, and the old punt nosing about among the reeds and rushes where she was tied up at the bank.

Just below Passau the river Inn comes in, turbulent, roaring and dancing, from the Tyrolese Alps. Its icy waters do not mingle for half a mile with the bigger river, but run alongside, a different colour and much swifter. Then the two gradually make friends and join hands, and the Danube, proud of its new friend, gains fresh impetus and hurries along into the great gorge that marks the frontier of Austria.

Here the whole gorge is filled up by the river, and camping spaces are very scarce. We found a narrow ledge at the foot of the wooded sides, where we landed with some difficulty behind a big rock that sent the current whizzing out into midstream and left comparatively quiet water just behind it. At the very same spot, a week before we got here, a terrible accident had taken place. A boat, with five members of the Regensburg Rowing Club, all experienced oarsmen and well used to the river, had upset at this exact spot, having been caught sideways in their light boat by the eddies from this very rock, and turned over before they could extricate their feet from the straps into which men stick their toes in this sort of outrigger shaped boat.

The cox managed to free himself and, making use of a whirlpool that flung him towards the shore, was swept into the bank and crawled out; but the other four men were pinned down by the boat and drowned like rats in a trap. All of them had been down this stretch times without number. It was late in the evening, and no help was near, for the place is lonely and boats pass very rarely indeed. The boat eventually rose to the surface, and the bodies, thus released, were tossed upon the shore and recovered in the morning, with the exception of one man, whose body was carried down through whirlpools and rapids for another fifty miles before the river gave it up. We saw the boat lying in the Customs House at Engelhartszell, the frontier village, and it was a mournful sight to see. All the way down we had heard this sad story of the accident, and many were the warnings we received to be careful; but in our old punt the danger was small, and a little care and common sense was all that was required to prevent disaster.

Vienna was now getting within hail, and the country became very much more civilised, and camping-grounds were not so easy to find. Steamers, too, became a daily excitement. They come tearing downstream with a string of heavily laden barges behind them, and they allow one precious little time to get out of the way. In narrow parts they are a real danger, for they are not on the look out for small craft, and, besides, have all they can do to steer themselves. The barges in tow make big waves, and once, when we were caught in a narrow sideway, the old punt jumped about in a way that amused us vastly until we took a wave in over the side and ran the risk of soaking our bread and potatoes before we were ready for them. But, even then, the old punt behaved with the greatest dignity and looked quite offended at being made to dance so violently. I believe nothing could have upset her short of an Atlantic roller.

Ruined castles, once of impregnable strength and position, now became frequent. In olden days the barons who dwelt in them used to stretch iron chains across the river and hold up the traffic and rob every boat that passed. Before their day, again, the Romans haunted these shores, and most of the towns we passed have Roman remains of one kind or another.

Just before reaching Vienna we stopped at a little village and got ready for the journey home, for our holiday time was over and we had to hurry back in the train. We gave our provisions away—bread to one boy, tea to another, a pot of stewed apricots to a third, and the axe, lanterns, filter, sugar, potatoes, and remains of the oatmeal to a family who were so pleased to get them that they afterwards brought us down a basket of fresh ripe peaches as a present in return. The old punt we gave to the landlord of the little inn where we put up for the night, and we all felt as if we were parting from an old friend who had proved her friendship in a very satisfactory way—by not leaking a drop and by carrying us for 400 miles on one of the jolliest journeys we ever had.

A Man of Earth

John Erdlieb used to tell this story—occasionally and with reluctance. It had to be dragged out of him. He seemed to feel it was telling something against himself, but that was because he didn’t believe in “the kind of thing,” and felt that he did himself a wrong and strained the credence of his listeners as well. Hence, probably, the strange impressiveness of the quaint recital; it had indubitably happened to him.

Though of German origin, he was English, stolid, steady, inarticulate English, and a rare good fellow, whose character emerged strongly in those difficult circumstances known as “tight places.” He was a mining engineer by profession; he loved the earth and anything to do with the earth, from a garden he played with half tenderly, to a mountain he attacked half savagely for tunnelling or blasting purposes. He never left the earth if he could help it; both feet and mind were always planted firmly upon terra firma; figuratively or actually, he never flew. And his physical appearance expressed his wholesome, earthly type—the rumbling, subterranean bass voice, the tangled undergrowth of beard that hid his necktie, the slow, stately walk as of a small hill advancing. Moreover, you might dig in him and find pure gold—the mass of him covered the heart of a simple, tender child, honest and loving as the day. A child of earth, in the literal sense he was, if ever such existed.

“The first time,” he said moving his words laboriously, as though they weighed, “was a June evening in Surrey, when I was going along a lane to catch a train to London. I was carrying a bag. It was a quarter-past ten, the train was 10:30, and I had a mile to go. I had come down in the afternoon to advise a friend about the laying of his tennis court—not professionally,” he explained, with a booming laugh, “but because I knew he was going the wrong way about it—and he had persuaded me to stay to dinner. He had seen me to the gate and given me directions about shortcuts. It was near the longest day, and there was light still hanging from the sky, but the lanes and paths ran along deep gullies in the sandstone, which the trees and bushes turned into tunnels of black. It was very warm and without a breath of air. Rain in the afternoon had left the atmosphere heavy, thick, and steamy. I perspired awfully, my wrist began to ache with carrying the bag, and halfway down one of the deep sandy lanes I stopped a moment to rest. I put the bag down, and struck a match to see my watch. There were seven minutes left to do a long half-mile.” He paused a moment, and we concluded from that pause that he would miss his train.

“Now, I’m not the sort of man,” he continued simply, “that a tramp would be likely to attack. I don’t look opulent, and I’m big. Until I struck that match I hadn’t passed a living soul. But my friend’s wife had told me the tramps were thick about the roads this summer, and had been pretty bold as well. I’d quite forgotten all this; it wasn’t in my mind. So when the glare of the match showed me a man standing close in front of me—so close I could have touched him—I got a start. He saw my watch, of course. But I saw his face. And he was looking straight into my eyes, just as though he had been staring at me in the dark before. The light, I mean, caught him in the act. There was no surprise in his face. Now I must tell you another thing as well: his face was smeared with earth.” He laughed again as he said it. “The fellow looked as if he had been buried and just crawled out. It was a big bearded face, and the eyes were like an animal’s—quite frank. But what struck me at the moment—I’m telling this badly, I’m afraid—was that, just as I stopped to strike that match, I noticed a strong smell of earth, of soil and mould I mean. If you’ve ever turned up real virgin soil you’d know exactly what it was like—same sort of smell you get when digging up a wet bit of field, only ten times stronger. A good smell; I love it.

“Well, the match went out, and the blackness after it was like a wall. I just thought I’d be getting on as quick as I could or I’d miss the train—no feeling at all that the fellow meant me any harm, you see—when I heard him say, ‘I’ll carry it for you. Come up this way. It’s the best.’ And before I could answer or object—do anything at all, in fact—the fellow had snatched my bag and made off with it. I suppose he had been waiting just at this darkest part of the lane on purpose. He went up hill, and I after him, striking angrily with my stick in the hope of tripping him up. But he had the start, and I was winded already, and uphill I’m not as quick as I used to be ten years ago. I heard his running tread along the sandy ground, light as a child; and, while I stumbled in the darkness among the loose stones and ruts, two other things flashed into my mind. I can’t say what made me think of them. But it seemed to me that the fellow was very short and had been standing on tiptoe when he stared into my face; and the other thing was this: that in this sandy soil—it’s mostly sand and heather and pine trees in that part—it was curious that the smell of earth should have been so strong. For it was rich, black earth I smelt.”

John Erdlieb stopped again. He had reached a difficult place, we felt, a place where he wanted help. We gave what help we could, urging him to tell the rest, whether it seemed credible to him or not.

“He kept just ahead of me,” he continued, in his growling tones that were like the deep string on a double bass, “and didn’t seem a bit anxious to escape from me. He could easily—he ran so lightly—have nipped up the banks and disappeared, and I could never in this world have caught him. But he kept ten yards in front. In the patches where the trees were thinner I saw his outline plainly; he’d run a bit, then pause, then start again just when I got too close. I shouted and cursed him, but he said no word. And at length—oh, we’d been running four or five minutes, I should think—he stopped dead, and waited. It was an open space, where the banks on both sides were clear of trees or bushes, and the light from the sky, as well as the sort of radiance that sand gives out—you know—showed him distinctly, crouching in the path, the bag beside him. I came up with a rush, my stick raised to clout him on the head, when—of course, you can’t believe it—he simply wasn’t there. I heard his voice, but—well, I can only tell you how it seemed to me—I heard it underground. It was muffled and smothered, as though it came through earth.” Erdlieb said this very low; he almost growled it; he was ashamed to tell it. “You want to know what it was he said? I’ll tell you in three words: ‘Now you’re safe.’ That was what I heard, and I heard it as distinctly as I hear my own voice now. The fellow had disappeared, as if the thing had been a dream, and I’d just wakened up.” He shut his mouth with a snap, as though there was no more to tell.

A lot of questions were discharged at him, of course, but chief among them, or first, at any rate, “And did you catch your train?” He had made such a point of catching that particular train.

“Luckily,” he said, “I missed it by three minutes. Yes, I did say ‘luckily.’ In the tunnel that begins a mile beyond the station there was a bad cave-in—it had been an exceptionally wet summer, and the first three coaches, the only first-class coaches on the train, had every occupant killed. Yes, it’s a fad of mine,” he answered a final question. “I always go first-class.”

He gave the second incident as well. He was very shy about it; but for the dusk on the verandah, where he told it, one could have seen him blush.

“It was last year, when I was in the Caucasus—the Lesser Caucasus, some 50 miles southeast of Batoum, where there are copper mines, first worked by the Phoenicians ages ago, but covered now by a forest of rhododendrons and azaleas. The ore is visible to the eye, and they get it out with pickaxes. It’s a marvellous country, wild as ever it can be, and the men wilder still, a difficult crew to manage, Georgians, Persians, Tartars, all Mohammedans, and all free with knife and pistol. We were 5,000 feet above sea-level. You could see Ararat in the distance, a pyramid of snow, and even Elbruz and Kasbek to the north, when the air was clear.

“One of my younger engineers was an American, capable as they make ’em, but with one curious drawback—he spouted Shakespeare and saw visions! A poetical sort of chap, but sober, reliable, and awfully good at his work. I think, you know, the power of the place got into him a bit—you can believe anything,” he explained apologetically, “in the Caucasus—and just across the next ridge was a settlement of Ossetines. The Ossetines are said to be older than the Egyptians, and no one knows exactly where they come from; they worship the soil, pray to heaps of earth, with the idea that it expresses deity or something, offer salt and milk to open places in the ground, and all that kind of thing. They’re a wild lot, too. But they didn’t bother us much, although some of our workmen were afraid of them. The idea was, you see, that they resented our cutting holes in the body of their deity.

“Apart from stories, that grew big unless stopped instantly”—he said this significantly—“I had no trouble with the men at all, and the Ossetines I only saw—er—this once. My American engineer was the bother, with his imaginative talk of nature-spirits, his seeing things about the mountains, and all the rest. The Caucasus just there is not exactly the place to talk that kind of stuff. It’s marvellous enough—without additions!

“Well, one afternoon this chap and I were out prospecting together—his geology was splendid, a sort of instinct in him—prospecting for new veins and outcrop and whatnot, and in the most gorgeously savage scenery you can possibly imagine. The mountain side was smothered with azalea bushes, all in bloom, every shade of colour, and the smell of them was almost more than I could stand. Azalea honey, you know, has a kind of intoxicating effect, like a drug, and the natives use it for that purpose, and, perhaps, the smell of these miles of blossom, taken in such enormous doses, affects the nerves a bit. I can’t say about that, but anyhow, Edgar began talking his nonsense about it in his peculiar way—clearheaded enough at the same time to trace his strata with amazing accuracy and judgment—and saying that his eyes were opened, and he could see down into the ground, and talking about the Ossetines and the Powers of the Place, and all mixed up with quotations from his Shakespeare and the rest. Well, it was no business of mine to stop him. He did his work all right. I let him go on fifteen to the dozen until at last it got on my nerves, and I told him to quit it. He didn’t mind a bit; just looked at me, and said, ‘I’ve had my eyes opened by the place; I can’t help it. Why, I can see your glassy essence. You’re an earth-person. You ought to feel what I feel. I think you do!’ That ‘glassy essence,’ you know, is in Measure for Measure, only I forget the whole quotation. And then he said excitedly, ‘The worship of these Ossetines up here has done it. The place is all stirred up. I shouldn’t be a bit surprised if we saw—’

“I interrupted him and told him to stow all that. The Ossetines, I told him—taking it that he referred to them and not to—er—other things—were over the next ridge, anyhow, five hours’ climbing away—when just at that very minute he came at me like a football player on the charge. He caught my shoulders and stared at me with terror in his face. ‘They’re coming!’ he cried out. ‘Can’t you hear them? They’re coming!’

“And there was a curious, deep, roaring sound up in the mountains to the north, a tremendous sound. It was like thunder. Yet it was a sunny, windless day without a cloud; there was not even falling water near us. I couldn’t believe my ears. And I turned and saw what at first I thought were sliding masses of earth and stones moving down towards us from the heights amile away. There were boulders, rolling and dancing down ahead of the general mass, only they moved so slowly and with such an extraordinary kind of motion altogether that I stood and stared in complete amazement. It all bewildered me. The sound was appalling somehow. It was like an upheaval of the earth. Then Edgar shouted, ‘Run, man, run for your life. They’re out!’ and started off downhill like a frightened deer.

“It takes a good deal to move me, however he smiled at us through the dusk so that his teeth were visible—‘and I stood still a minute longer, watching the strangest thing I’d ever seen. For those stones and rolling boulders were not rock, but people. It was a crowd of people. Not Ossetines, though. I could see that. They were small and stunted. Even at that distance I could swear they were very small. They were like dwarfs. They were dwarfs. It took my breath away; but, I swear to you, they were just like that tramp who snatched my bag in the Surrey lane five years before, and they made the same strange impression upon me of being—er—out of the ordinary.” He paused a moment, wondering most likely how much more he cared to tell. “I picked up our instruments and ran downhill after Edgar,” he told us simply, “ran as hard as I could pelt. You can judge the pace when I tell you I caught him up in something under ten minutes, too.” That didn’t impress us much, perhaps, because we had never seen the other man, but it meant a lot to Erdlieb apparently. Edgar, of course, was a younger man. “And then we ran on together side by side, not looking back, but feeling exactly as if the mountainside was at our heels. The roaring sound had stopped. Once within sight of the Works we stopped, too. Nothing unusual was anywhere to be seen. The heights stood out clear and sharp against the brilliant sky. Nothing moved. Not a living soul was visible in any direction upon the enormous slopes. Edgar, however, was white as a ghost, scared stiff, as he phrased it himself. He declared he had seen

‘A shadow, like an angel with bright hair
Dabbled in blood.’

“I was in no mood for quotations. I could have knocked him down on the spot.

“That night, an hour after sunset, when the stars were out, and all the mountains peaceful, no wind, no noise of any kind, no hint of warning either, the landslide came. You know about it because I’ve already described it to you at dinner. It’s why I’m in England now instead of superintending the copper mines out there in the Caucasus. The Works were smothered, the loss of life appalling. I told you how we escaped, Edgar and I, by the skin of our teeth and—er—luck. The spot among the azaleas where we first heard the noise in the afternoon—several hours before a single pound of earth had begun to shift—by eight o’clock lay under several hundred feet of fallen mountain, still slowly sliding. I doubt if the Works will ever he dug out. It would cost a fortune. I have advise against it.”

A Mysterious House

Explanations are usually very tedious, and so without any introduction or preambulation I will plunge right into the midst of this uncanny story I am about to tell … When, some fifteen years before the time of which I write, I was a schoolboy at Eton I made close friends with a fellow above me in the school, named Pellham. We were very great chums, and later on we went to Cambridge together, where my friend spent money and time in wasting both, while I read for holy orders, though I never actually entered the Church. Since that time I had completely lost sight of him and he of me, and, with the exception of seeing his marriage in the papers, had no news at all of his whereabouts. One morning, however, towards the close of September 1857, I received a letter from him, short, precise, and evidently written in a great hurry, asking me to go down and see him at his family seat just outside Norwich. I packed my bag and went that very same evening. He met me himself at the station and drove me home. We hardly recognised each other at first sight, so much had we changed in appearance, both being on the dark side of thirty-five, but our individual characters had remained much the same and we were still to all appearances the best of friends. My friend was not very talkatively disposed, and I kept up a fire of questions until we drew up at the park gates. Going up the drive to the house he brightened up considerably, and gave me plenty of information about himself and family. He was quite alone, I was surprised to hear, his wife and two daughters with an uncle of his having left for the Continent two days previous. After dinner he seemed quite the old “Cambridge Undergrad” again, and once settled round the old-fashioned hearth, with cheroots and coffee, we talked on over the days spent at Eton and Cambridge. We were just discussing our third edition of tobacco, when Pellham suddenly changed the subject, and said he would tell me now why he had written so shortly to me to pay him this unexpected visit. His face grew grave as he began by asking me if I was still a sceptic as regards ghostly manifestations.

“Indeed I am,” was my answer; “I have had no reason to change my views on the subject, and think exactly as I used to at Cambridge, when we so strongly differed; but I remember you then saying that, if ever in after years you should come across an opportunity of proving to me your ideas on the subject, you would write to me at once, and I also recollect giving my word that, if possible, I would come. But during the fifteen years that have since passed by I have bestowed little, if any, thought on the subject.”

“Exactly,” answered Pellham, with a grave smile that did not please me; “but now I have at last heard of a case which will satisfy us both, I think, so I wrote to you to come down and fulfil your old promise by investigating it.”

“Well! let me hear all about it first,” I said cautiously. I certainly was not overjoyed to hear this news, for, though a sceptic to all intents and purposes, still “ghosts” was a subject for which I had a certain fear, and the highest ambition of my life was not to investigate haunted houses and the like just because I had years ago promised I would should a chance occur. But I repressed my feelings and tried to look interested, which I was, and delighted, which I certainly was not. Pellham then gave me a long account—thrilling enough too it was—of the case, which I have somewhat condensed in the following form. Some three or four years before, my friend had bought up a house which stood on the moorland about eight miles off. One morning before breakfast the tenant of the house, a Mr. Sherleigh (who was there with his family), suddenly burst into my friend’s study without any ceremony, and, in great heat and excitement, shouted out the following words:

“You shall suffer for it, Lord Pellham, my wife mad, and the little boy killed with fright, because you didn’t choose to warn us of the room next the drawing-room, but you shall—.” Here the footman entered, and at a sign from his master led the excited and evidently cracked old man from the room, but not before he had crashed down some gold pieces on the table, with: “That’s the last rent you’ll get for that house, as sure as I am the last tenant.”

“Well,” continued my friend, “that very day, now two years ago, I rode over there myself and the house was empty. The Sherleighs had left it, and since that day I have never been able to let it to anyone. Mr. Sherleigh, who was quite mad, poor fellow, threw himself before a train, and was cut to pieces, and Mrs. Sherleigh spread a report that it was haunted, and now no one will take it or even go near it, though it stands high and is in a very healthy position. Two nights ago,” he went on gravely, “I was riding past the road which leads up to it, and through the trees I could see light in one of the upper rooms, and figures, or rather shadows, of a woman’s figure, with something in her arms, kept crossing to and fro before the window-blind. I determined to go in and see what on earth it was, and tying my horse just outside I went in. In a minute or two I was close underneath the window where the light was still visible, and the shadow still moving to and fro with a horrible regularity. As I stood there, undecided, a feeling within warned me not to enter the house, so vivid, it was almost a soft voice that whispered in my ear. I heard no noise inside, the night air was moaning gently through the fir trees which surrounded the house on one side and nearly obscured the upper part of the window from view. I stooped down and picked up a large stone—it was a sharp-edged flint—and without any hesitation hurled it with all my might at the window pane, some eight or ten feet from the ground. The stone went straight and struck the window on one of the wooden partitions, smashing the whole framework, glass and all, into a thousand splinters, many of which struck me where I stood. The result was awful and unexpected. The moment the stone touched the glass the lights quite disappeared, and in the blackness in which I was shrouded, the next minute, I could see hiding behind the broken corners of glass a dark face and form for a short instant, and then it went and all was pitch dark again. There I was among those gloomy pine trees hardly knowing which way to turn. The face I had caught a momentary glimpse of was the face of Mr. Sherleigh, whom I knew to be dead! My knees trembled. I tried to grope my way out of the wood, and stumbled from tree to tree, often striking my head against the low branches. In vain. With the weird light in the window as a guide, I had taken but a few minutes to come, but now all was dark and I could not find my way back again. I felt as if the dismal tree trunks were living things, which seemed to move. Suddenly I heard a noise on my left. I stopped and listened. Horror! I was still close to the window, and what I heard was a cracking and splintering of broken glass, as if someone from inside were slowly forcing their way out through the hole made by my stone! Was it he? The fir tree next me suddenly shook violently, as if agitated by a powerful gust of wind, and then in a gleam of weird light I saw a long dark body hanging halfway out of the window, with black hair streaming down the shoulders. It raised one arm and slammed down something at my feet which fell with a rattle, and then hissed out: ‘There’s the last rent you’ll ever have for this house.’ I stood literally stupefied with horror, then a cold numb sensation came over me and I fell fainting on my face, but not until I had heard my horse give a prolonged neigh and then his footsteps dying away in the distance on the hard moorland road. When I recovered consciousness it was broad daylight. I was cold and damp; all night I had lain where I fell. I rose and limped, stiff and tired, to the place where I had tied my horse the night before, but no horse was there. And the horrible sound of his hoofs echoing away in the distance came back to me, and I shuddered as I thought of what I had seen. After a terrible trudge of three hours I reached home. A tremendous search had been made for me, of course, but no one dreamt of looking for me where I really was. The horse had found his way home, and I have never found out what frightened him so.”

My friend’s account was over. He lit his cigar, which had gone out during the narrative, and settling himself comfortably in his chair, said, “Well, old boy, that’s a case I don’t feel at all inclined to investigate by myself, but I’ll do it with your aid. You know, a genuine sceptic is a great addition in such things, so we’ll get to the bottom of it somehow.”

My feelings at that moment were not difficult to describe. I disliked the whole affair, and wanted heartily to get out of it; and yet something urged me to go through with it and show my friend that the house was all right, that imagination did it all, that the horse may have taken fright at anything, and that very possibly there really was someone in the house all the time, and imagination had done the rest. Such were the somewhat mixed thoughts at the time. However, in a few moments all was in my mind settled and we had agreed to go the following night, search the house first, and then sit up all night in the room next the drawing room. Then we both went to our separate bedrooms to think the matter over and get a long sleep, as we neither expected to get any the following night.

Next morning at breakfast we both talked cheerfully about the coming night and how best to meet its requirements as regards food, etc. We agreed to take pistols for weapons, horses as a means of conveyance, and abundant food wherewith to fortify our selves against a possible attack of ghosts.

The day drew on towards its close. It was very hot and sultry weather, and not a breath of wind stirred the murky atmosphere, as at 4:30 p.m. we bestrode our horses and made off in the direction of the “White House.” A long gravel road, lonely in the extreme, led us across the wild uncultivated moorland for six or seven miles, then we saw a copse of fir trees which, my friend informed me were the trees which sheltered one side of the house. In a few minutes we had passed through the front garden gate and were among the dark fir trees, and then as we turned a sharp corner the house burst full upon us. It was square and ugly. Great staring windows in regular rows met our eyes and conveyed an unpleasant impression to the brain—at least, they did to mine. From the very moment we had passed the front gate till I left the house next morning, I felt a nasty sick sensation creep over me, a feeling of numbness and torpor which seemed to make the blood run thick and sluggish in my veins. The events of that night have remained engraven on my brain as with fire, and, though they happened years ago, I can see them now as vividly as then. Only an eyewitness can possibly describe them, should he wish to do justice to them, and so my feeble pen shall make the attempt.

It was about 6:30, and we had settled our horses in a barn outside for the night. There were only two walls to keep the barn in position, and these were simply a row of rotten posts, half decayed in places, so we securely tied the horses and, with a good supply of hay, left them for the night. We then approached the door and, after fumbling in the lock for some time, Pellham succeeded in opening it. A sickly, musty odour pervaded the hall, and the first thing we did after a thorough search, which revealed nothing, was to open all the doors and windows all over the house, so as to let in what little air there was. Then we went upstairs into the little room next the drawing-room, where, according to Sherleigh, strange things had occurred. But the window was in pieces, and hardly an entire pane of glass was left, and we were forced to select another room on the same floor (i.e. the second) and looking out on the same copse of pine trees, whose branches almost touched the glass, so close were they. It was a very ordinary room; a fireplace, no furniture but a rickety table and three chairs, one of which was broken. The only disagreeable feature we noticed about the room was its gloominess; it was so very dark. The trees outside, as I have already said, were so close that the slighest breath of wind rustled their twigs against the window. We soon had six candles fixed and burning in different parts of the little room, and the blaze of light was still further increased by a roaring fire, on which a kettle was singing for tea, and eggs boiling in a saucepan, and at half-past seven we were in the middle of our first tea in a haunted house. It was, indeed, less luxurious than the dinners I had been used to lately, but otherwise there was nothing to find fault with, and a little later the tea things were cleared away in a heap in a corner (where, by the by, they are to this day), and we were sitting round an empty table, smoking in silence. The door out into the passage was fast shut, but the window was wide open. The sun had sunk out of sight in a beautiful sky of wonderful colouring. Small fleecy clouds floating about caught the soft afterglow and looked unearthly as seen through the thick fir branches. The faint red hue of the western sky looked like the reflection of some huge and distant conflagration, growing dimmer and fainter as the dark engines of the night played upon it, extinguishing the leaping flames and suffusing the sky with a red reflected glow. Not a breath of air stirred the trees. My friend had left the window and was poking and arranging the fire, with his back turned to wards me. I was standing close to the window, looking at the fast-fading colours, when it seemed to me that the window sash was moving. I looked closer. Yes! I was not mistaken. The lower half was gradually sinking; gradually and very quietly it went down. At first I thought the weight had slipped and gone wrong, and the window was slipping down of its own accord; but when I saw the bolt pulled across and fastened as by an invisible hand, I thought differently. My first impulse was to immediately undo the bolt again and open the window, but on trying to move—good heavens! I found I had lost all power of motion and could not move a muscle of my body. I was literally rooted to the ground. Neither could I move the muscles of my tongue or mouth; I could not speak or utter a sound. Pellham was still doing something to the fire, and I could hear him muttering to himself, though I could not distinguish any words. Suddenly, then, I felt the power of motion returning to me; my muscles were relaxing, and turning, though not without a considerable effort, I walked to the fireplace. Pellham, then, for the first time noticed that the window was shut, and he made a remark about the closeness of the night, asking me why I had closed it.

“Hulloa,” he went on, before I had time to answer, “by the gods above! what is happening to that window? Look—why it’s moving!”

I turned. The window was slowly being opened again.

Yes, sure enough it was. Slowly and steadily it moved or was pushed up.

We could but believe our eyes; in half a minute the window was wide open again. I turned and looked at Pellham and he looked at me, and in dead silence we stared at one another, neither knowing what to say or wishing to break the silence. But at length my friend spoke.

“I wish I were a sceptic, old man, like you are; sceptics are always safer in a place like this.”

“Yes,” I said, as cheerfully as I could, “I feel safe enough, and what’s more, I am convinced that the window was opened by human agency from outside.”

Pellham smiled, he knew as well as I that no human fingers could have fastened the bolt from outside. “Well,” he said briskly, “perhaps you are right; come, let’s examine the window.”

We rose and approached it, and my friend put his head and shoulders out into the air. It was very dark, and a strange oppressive stillness reigned outside, only broken by the gentle moaning sound of the night wind as it rustled through the trees and swept their branches like the strings of a lyre. I followed my friend’s example, and together we peered out into the night. Soon my eyes rested on the ground below us, and at the base of one of the nearer pines I thought I could distinguish a black form, clinging, as it seemed, to the tree. I pointed it out to Pellham, who failed to see anything, or at least said so; anyhow, I was glad to believe that my excited imagination was the real cause. We were still leaning out of the window in silence, when several of the trees, especially the one where I imagined I had seen the shape, were most violently agitated, as though by a mighty wind; but we felt not the slightest breath on our faces. At the same instant we heard a subdued shuffling sound in the room behind us, which seemed to come from the direction of the chimney. But neither of us referred to it as we slowly walked back to the fire and took up our places on either side on the two chairs, which were at the best very rickety.

“It isn’t wise to leave the window open,” said my friend, suddenly, “for if there really is anyone outside, they can see all and everything we do; while we, for our part, can see absolutely nothing of what goes on outside.”

I agreed, and walked up to the window, shutting it with a bang and firmly drawing the bolt.

“I’ve brought a book,” he went on, which I thought we might read out aloud in turn to relieve the dullness and the silence.

He stopped speaking and looked at me, and at the same moment I raised my eyes to his face. To my intense horror and surprise I noticed for the first time a long smear of blood, wet and crimson, across his forehead. My horror was so great that for some seconds I could not find my tongue, and sat stupidly staring at him. At last I gasped out:

“My dear fellow, what has happened to you, have you cut yourself?”

“Where? what do you mean?” he replied, looking round him with surprise.

For answer I took out my handkerchief, and wiping his brow, showed him the red stains. But as I stood there showing him this proof and as he was expressing his utter astonishment, I distinctly saw something that for the moment made the blood rush from the extremities and crowd into my head. Something seemed to tighten round my heart. I saw a large, gleaming knife and hand disappear into the air in the direction of the window. It was too much; my nerves failed me, and I dropped fainting to the floor.

When I came to myself I was lying where I fell by the fire place. Pellham was sitting beside me.

“I thought you were dead,” he said, “you’ve been unconscious for over an hour.” He said this in such a queer manner and laughed so fiendishly that I wondered what had happened to him during the interval. Had he seen something awful and gone mad? There was a strange light in his dark eyes and a leer on his lip. Just then he took up his book quite naturally and began to read aloud, every now and then he made a comment on what he was reading, quite sensibly too, and soon I began to think, as I sipped my brandy out of our flask, that I must have had a frightful dream. But there at my feet lay the bloodstained handkerchief, and I could not get over that. I glanced at his face; the smear had disappeared, and no scratch or wound was visible.

Pellham had not been reading long, perhaps some five or ten minutes, when we heard a strange noise outside among the trees, just audible above the deathlike stillness of the autumn night. It was a confused voice like the low whispering of several persons, and as I listened, still weak from the last shock, the blood stood still in my veins. Pellham went on reading as usual. This struck me as very curious, for he must have heard the noise plainly; but I said nothing, and glancing at him I saw the same light in his eyes and the evil leer on his mouth, looking ugly in the flickering glare of the candles and firelight.

Suddenly we heard a tremendous noise outside, altogether drowning the first. The horses had broken loose and were tearing wildly past the house. Long and wild neighs rang out and died away, and we knew our horses were gone. Pellham was still reading, and as I looked at him a sudden and horrid thought flashed through my brain. It was this: Had he anything to do with this? Was it possible? Before I had time to answer my question Pellham threw down the book and made for the door, locked it, drew out the key, and opening the window threw it far away among the trees. I then recognised the awful fact that I was alone with a madman. I glanced at my watch, it was a quarter to one. Instead of one hour I must have been unconscious two at least. This was terrible in the extreme. He was a man of far more powerful physique than I. What was to be done? Pellham strode grinning up to the fire, went down on both knees and commenced blowing between the bars with all his might. I saw my chance, and quietly walking to the window, without a word I climbed out, and letting myself as far down as my arms would allow I then let go and dropped. It was a distance of four or five feet, but in the darkness I tumbled forward on my face. As I rose, uninjured, I distinctly heard the sound of running feet close to me, but in my bewilderment I could not make out clearly in which direction they were going; they only lasted a moment or two. But what a terrific sight met my gaze as I turned the corner of the house, and saw volumes of smoke pouring steadily out of the windows and roof of the back portion of the house. Now and again a long flame, too, shot up to heaven.

“Good God!” I cried, “the house is on fire.”

No wonder the horses had taken flight. But my poor friend, what could I do for him? The window was too high for me to climb in again, and the doors were locked. In a few minutes the flames would spread to this side of the house and the poor fellow would be burnt to death unless he had enough sense left to jump out of the window.

I hurried back to the spot where I had let myself down from the window, just in time to see the last scene of the most ghastly experience I have ever witnessed. Pellham was standing at the window. In his hand was a red-hot poker, and it was pointed at his throat, but the strain was too great for my nervous system and with a violent start I woke up!

After our heavy tea we had both fallen asleep, just as we were in our chairs. Pellham was still snoring opposite me, and the light was stealing in through the window. It was morning, about half-past six. All the candles had burnt themselves out, and it was a wonder they had not set fire to the dry wood near them.

Twenty minutes later we had relit the fire and were discussing the remnant of eggs and coffee. Half an hour later we were riding home in the bright, crisp, morning air, and an hour and a half later we were in the middle of a second and far superior breakfast, during which I did not tell my dream, but during which we did agree that it had been the dullest and most uncomfortable night we had ever spent away from home.

A Spiritualist Camp in New England

Although my practical acquaintance with spiritualism ceased several years ago (at the close of a period of ardent investigation), my interest was suddenly galvanised into fresh life by the news that not far from the house where I was visiting there was situated a summer encampment of spiritualists nearly five hundred strong. Five hundred spiritualists living quietly among themselves, beyond all reach of chilling doubt and scepticism, was a temptation with a special charm; and there was no great difficulty in persuading my hostess that a visit would be interesting. We accordingly organised a party of four, and started behind a pair of long-tailed horses for a drive of ten miles up into the gentle, wooded hills that at this point render the coast of the State of Connecticut peculiarly attractive.

It was somewhat of a surprise to find five hundred spiritualists occupying a fortified position in this most rigid of New England States. Numerous as they are all over the United States, especially in California and along the slopes of the Pacific Coast, we hardly expected that the puritan spirit of New England would afford them sufficient favour and nourishment to encourage a settlement of this description. In our ignorance, therefore, it was something of a shock to learn from our driver that ‘ “Them spritilists are all over this part of the country, thick as p’tater-bugs.” To us, who knew that Connecticut suffered severely from the ravages of the Colorado beetle (vulgarly known as the potato-bug) this information came with some degree of picturesque force. ‘ They’ve a powerful followin’ around here,” the man went on, “but I don’t take any stock in ’em.”

“From what class do they draw their supporters?”

“Hard to say; unejicated folk mostly, I guess.”

“Farmers?”

“No, not farmers at all,” he replied with vigour. “People from the small towns and villages; people that’s curious to know what kind of a place they’ll drop into later.”

“They have no great attraction for you?”

“None! They don’t tell you nothin’ worth knowin’, to begin with. Oh, but they’re plenty round here,

more than you can shake a stick at; and they’re a good sort mostly, pays their bills and doesn’t drink. But

they don’t pheaze me any!” The scorn of the driver, who himself came from a vigorous farming stock up country, was very instructive.

It was a sunny September afternoon. Some miles away on our right the town of New London stretched itself prettily along the banks of the Thames, a Thames that could swallow its namesake half a dozen times and show no appreciable rise. Behind us lay the blue line of the sea, dotted with shining white sails; and on our left the woods flowed away in graceful undulations that already hung aloft the crimson and golden banners of their flaming autumn dress. Presently the woods fell sharply away and a dark grove of pines came into view in a little valley below us. It was a secluded spot, protected on two sides by a loop of the river and on a third by the shoulder of the hills. Perfectly still and quiet, it lay literally in a fold of the river and the hills. Occasional threads of thin blue smoke, rising here and there over the dark pine-crests, alone betrayed the existence of busy human beings.

The first impression of the camp was a somewhat gloomy one, due partly no doubt to its sombre surrounding of dark evergreens and to the overshadowing presence of the hill which hid the setting of the sun. The gorgeous colouring of the surrounding maple woods further served to throw into contrast the subdued tints of the picture.

Nevertheless, this sudden aspect of the camp, as we afterwards remembered, gave to us its true note—peace, remoteness from the world, an unearthly stillness, and, at the same time, a curious suggestion of sleepiness, heaviness, dullness that somehow seemed also to include the idea of stagnation. The air, hovering above the still pines, seemed denser than the surrounding atmosphere and shone with a lesser brilliance in the glory of the afternoon sun. The first appearance of the place was, on the whole, depressing. This impression floated up to us on the heights and in the sunshine, but as we descended into the little valley and entered within the shadow of the grove itself and saw the numerous wooden cottages under the trees, it seemed momentarily dispelled, though it returned afterwards with gathered force and renewed conviction.

A feeling that perhaps we were intruding upon scenes not intended for us, and that our unsolicited visit might not be welcome was considerably weakened when the driver tied his horses up to a pine tree and observed, with energy: “They’ll be out in a swarm to see you, and glad too, when they know you’re here. They like visitors.”

He sat down and lit his pipe, while we strolled up one of the little lanes that intersected the grove in all

directions. The trees were dense and close together; and, though the roads had been marked out with evident purpose, the cottages had set themselves down anywhere and everywhere with the utmost irregularity. There was an air of irresponsibility about the place which was refreshing. Here and there, as if to give countenance to the road, a few cottages appeared side by side in a feeble attempt at a row, but the majority of them stood about saucily wherever the trees allowed them room. They were built, too, in all possible relations to each other and abutted at all manner of angles.

And the roads were not roads. They were the natural soft ground, covered with pine-needles: they were merely good honest trails, or vistas, cut with charming irregularity through the trees; and, if you did not like them, you could leave them and walk to your destination over the pineneedles elsewhere. Our feet passed along them in silence, and the general air of stillness about the camp was so marked that we instinctively lowered our voices almost to a whisper.

The swarm mentioned by the driver, who was evidently optimist or idealist, took a long time in making its appearance, but on the other hand no one blocked our way. Perhaps the few women we saw hovering about the cottages were its forerunners. One of these, with her arms bare to the elbows, was lazily engaged in the performance of some domestic duty, and when we asked her if any part of the camp were private, she replied that it was all open to the public and that we could go wherever we wished. However, a general tour of inspection over the forty acres, or so, revealed nothing very exciting, and we turned our attention next to the little cottages. These were all of wood, for it was a summer encampment, and the cottages were summer cottages; in two months’ time they would be deserted and under deep snow. Of the lightest possible structure, the walls were of unpapered, unvarnished pine-boards, and _ the roofs of thin cedar shingles. Only a few boasted two stories, but every one of them, no matter how small, enjoyed the luxury of a wide verandah running round the front and the two sides. On every verandah was the inevitable rocking-chair with a wicker seat, a high back, and broad arms.

So far we had come across no men and no animals. A few thin chickens, with draggled feathers, wandered disconsolately in the neighbourhood of one or two of the cottages, seeking what sustenance they could find among the dry needles. But the camp, as a whole, was so quiet it seemed almost deserted; and, as one of our party observed, it was a ghostly sort of place full of shadows and silence.

Although the houses were naturally inexpensive—no one of them could have cost more than two hundred and fifty dollars (£50)—there were everywhere evidences of neglect, poverty, and even dirt that were, to say the least of it, dispiriting. There was an unnecessary cheapness, an unnecessary vulgarity. Besides this, and in spite of the sweet fragrance of the pines, there was a closeness and stufliness about the atmosphere that affected all our party alike, and exerted on our spirits an influence far from exhilarating. Moreover, the faces we had so far seen were of a low order, coarse, heavy, uninspired, with queer, farseeing eyes that lent them their only interest, and that an unnatural one. There was nowhere, so far as we could discern, the spirit of strong cheerfulness, nowhere the note of positive happiness. Brightness was a word that fell stillborn in that atmosphere and woke no echo. All of our party, though each one expressed it differently, acknowledged to the consciousness of a certain vague despondency, almost as if the campers were forever communicating with the spirits of the dead, yet winning from them no other doctrines than those of negation and despair.

The shadows were beginning to lengthen, and the sun had already dropped behind the shoulder of the hill, when we turned a corner and came suddenly upon the first man we had as yet seen in the community.

His cottage faced the road, and he sat on the verandah rocking slowly to and fro in a very dilapidated chair. He was an old man, tall, and very thin. His legs were crossed and his bony hands rested, one over the other, upon his knees. A spare white beard straggled over half his waistcoat, and his large hooked nose somehow reminded one of a vulture or other big bird of prey. At first, as we turned the corner talking in low voices, he took no notice of us, but sat staring beyond us into vacancy. But the next minute, hearing our voices, he turned his face in our direction and we met the queer gaze of his faint blue, watery eyes. It was a picture to impress the mind vividly, this spare, spectre-like old man, white-bearded and misty-eyed, sitting solitary on his verandah and staring into the shadows of the darkening pine-grove.

From his face our glance shifted quickly to a cardboard placard hanging in the window behind him with the words in bold type—seer, $1 a sitting. Without leaving his chair he exchanged the courtesies of the evening with us in a weak, high voice and with a faint smile. One hardly knew how to continue the conversation thus begun, but he at once relieved us of all difficulties.

“Would you like to know who your guides are, or who is near you?” he asked in a matter-of-fact way, as if he were speaking of an ascent of the Alps, or a game of hide-and-seek.

“What can you tell us?”

“Most anything you want to know,” he answered obligingly, but with obvious sincerity; “who’s with you, and who’s thinkin’ of you in the spirit-world.” We hesitated and the old man saw his advantage. He turned to an elderly lady of our party. “A number of your friends have passed over,” he said.

“Passed over 1”

“Passed over,” he repeated; “we never say died.” She waited expectantly. ‘ “Isn’t that so?” he asked, stroking his beard.

“Yes,” she said, “I have lost a good many.”

“Not lost,” he said with his faint smile, “not lost, only passed over.” There was a short pause. ‘ “There’s a tall, dark man behind you now,” he went on; “he’s looking over your shoulder at this very minute.”

This was a startling bit of news and one of the ladies in the party uttered a little scream. We all turned and peered into the gathering shadows while the seer went on to describe the tall, dark man with the minutest detail.

“What’s his name?” asked the lady concerned.

“I can’t quite get that,” he replied, as if making an effort to hear, “but he was very fond of you, and is so still. Do you recognise him?” The lady shook her head. “He wants to speak to you,” continued the old man; “he says he has something important to tell you—a warning.”

“Won’t he tell it to you for me?” she asked,

The seer shook his head and smiled. “No; he says it’s for you alone; but he’ll tell it to me if I go into the trance-state, because then I don’t know what I’m telling, and don’t remember afterwards.” He continued rocking gently to and fro and staring into the darkness behind him as if he saw someone and was conversing with him.

We tried to make a bargain with the seer, but he was obdurate. Four shillings a head we considered too much, and he insisted on taking one at a time, and that one alone. He told us that during the winter he lived in H. and followed his profession with lower fees, but that in the summer he was obliged to raise them to a prohibitive figure, because he came to the camp to rest and recuperate. The sceptical and curious visitors, he explained further, exhausted and depleted him; it wasn’t worth it under a dollar a sitting.

We moved quietly up the silent lane with the uncomfortable feeling that the tall, dark man was looking over each one’s shoulder in turn and trying to whisper something portentous and unearthly into our ears, And, as we moved in and out among the cottages, we noticed that many windows showed placards similar to the one we had seen, with the various legends, Medium, Clairvoyant, Seer, Materialising Medium, Trance Medium, Crystal Gazer, and so forth.

It was now long after six o’clock and the occupants of the cottages came out in twos and threes to sit and rock on their verandahs. There were no lights in the streets nor lamps in the windows; the place was growing very dark and the air cooler.

We spoke to some of the women, especially when they were supported by interesting placards in the windows; but they one and all declined to sit for us before eight o’clock. It was too early, or they were too tired, or it was too soon after tea—or something. If we cared, however, to come back at that hour there would be no lack of mediums who would be willing to enter the trance-condition and tell us all we wanted to know. To another visit, therefore, of a week later, we were obliged to defer the dubious pleasure of communicating with spirits at the moderate rate of two shillings a head.

It was a bright moonlight night when we drove over to the camp for the second time, and as we entered the grove the pines gave forth a mournful response to the breeze that came in from the sea.

As had been foretold, there was no difficulty in finding a willing medium. The first woman we addressed agreed to give us a sitting all together. She was a stout middle-aged person clothed in a slovenly brown dress that was loose where it should have been tight, and tight where it should have been loose. Her face, though coarse and generally unattractive, was in no sense bad. She was quite illiterate. “You don’t need to pay if it isn’t satisfactory,” she said, as under her direction we entered the stuffy little parlour that opened off the verandah, and seated ourselves in more or less of a circle. Her own chair was against a curtain which separated the parlour from the bedroom—probably the only other room in the house. A turned-down oil lamp, that smelt abominably, stood on the table beside her and enabled us to see the play of her face. Otherwise, there was no light but the reflected glimmer of the moonbeams which lay outside like silver streaks among the dark tree-stems; while the only sound was the occasional muffled footstep of someone passing up or down the lane.

For about five minutes we sat in silence. The medium was opposite us, her eyes closed and her hands folded in her lap. Just over my head a canary kept fidgeting in its cage and once, when I put my hand up and passed it over my face, I struck the bars and brought down a shower of seed all over me.

Suddenly the woman shivered audibly, and drew a long breath; at the same time she raised her face as if she were looking at us, though the eyes were still closed. Then she lifted an arm weakly, about breast- high, and let it drop again upon her lap. Recalling my former knowledge of the orthodox methods of procedure on such occasions I ventured to speak according to the approved formula, and said “Good evening.”

The woman’s lips, plainly visible in the lamplight, moved a little and a voice issued forth that faintly resembled her own, yet had a different accent. “Good evening,” it said.

“We’re very glad to see that you’ve come.”

“I’se glad too,” said the voice. “You’re all strangers, aren’t you?” It spoke in the broken English peculiar to the Indians, a jargon which is difficult to reproduce. On our answering in the affirmative, it went on: “But I know you all. I’se often with you and with the two squaws too.” There was no expression on the face as it spoke; it was like the face of a corpse.

“Are you an Indian spirit?”

“Yes.”

“What’s your name?”

“Silver Star.”

“Do you often use this medium?”

“Yes,” and here it laughed, “very often. She’s my medie; I come to her all the time; I’se her control.”

“Have I got a control too?”

“Course you has. Everybody has a guide, or a control.”

“Has everyone here got a guide?”

“Yes. The squaw next you has two, and the other squaw has one, and so has the brave beyond.”

“Who is my guide?”

“T can see him; he is a great big Indian; his name’s Black Hawk. He always look after you; he stand behind your chair now.”

It would be tedious to reproduce the conversations that were carried on in this manner between Silver Star and each one of our party in turn. The future was told, the past guessed at; prophecies were made, warnings uttered, and even jokes exchanged. One of our party was informed that her husband had passed over, which was true, and was still with her day and night. Another was told that he was shortly going to cut sticks (Indian for marry), which was also true, since the young lady of his affections was at that moment seated next him. Another was told, on the other hand, that his squaw was soon to pass over, which was not true because he had not got a squaw and was in no immediate danger of getting one.

Perhaps the scene had lasted in this way about half an hour when the voice said with considerable abruptness: “Now I must go; my medie’s tired. I wish you all good night and hope I see you again.” Throughout it had expressed the tenderest solicitude for the health of the body it claimed to be making use of.

Again a shiver, ever so slight, passed over the body of the woman, and she suddenly opened her eyes and stared round the room with a dazed and puzzled expression. Then she turned up the lamp and looked hard at each of us. For a moment no one spoke.

“Was it satisfactory?” she presently asked. By way of reply we handed her the money agreed upon. “Who came?” was the next question. We informed her that Silver Star had chatted pleasantly with us but had betrayed no information of value. “Ah, she’s only a child,” the woman explained. “It’s a young Indian child; she often comes. But did she stay all the time? Was there no one else?”

“No one else.”

“Tm sorry. Of course, they’re ’most all Indian spirits, but some know more than others. Eagle Feather comes sometimes. He tells a lot, but he’s very rough and hurts me; he is violent at times and knocks me about; he don’t mean no harm, but that’s his way, you see.”

She assured us also that we each had an Indian guide who was with us most of the day and looked after our welfare, keeping away the bad spirits. “TI have a lot of them,” she said, as if they were pets, “and often see em among the trees out there,” pointing over our shoulders to the wood, “or they come to my bedside at night. I wouldn’t be without ’em for anything.”

We had little more conversation with her. She seemed happy and contented, and without the least fear of death, talking of the hereafter as if it were tomorrow or the next day.

Before we left that night we talked with other members of the camp, men and women, and saw the interior of several of the cottages. They were all the same; the people illiterate, unkempt, shabby; the rooms poorly furnished, vulgar, dirty. We saw neither books, periodicals nor pictures, with the single exception of a highly- coloured chromolithograph of a stout woman in a black dress with red cheeks, pearls round her throat, and shining dark eyes, who was “a wonder of a medium.”

The life of the camp, so far as we could gather, was quiet and uneventful. There was no pretence of occupation. The people came there from the neighbouring county as well as from far distant States, and they came to rest, and not to work. There were several shops in the little lane, a greengrocer, a stationer, and a butcher whose cart bore the inscription Spiritualists’ Camp. Many of those we spoke to were vegetarians. Alcohol was not to be purchased there in any form for love or money. We also visited a large meeting-hall capable of holding a couple of thousand people, and were told that it was used every year for the Annual Spiritualists’ Convention, and also during the summer for Sunday gatherings at which inspirational addresses were delivered.

In the immediate neighbourhood of the camp were farms and villages of the typical New England sort, and a little enquiry showed that their inhabitants paid no special attention to the campers, nor regarded them as anything out of the common. The fact was that every village had its own spiritualists; and, since the excitement of 1848, when the American movement received such amazing impetus from the Fox phenomena, the people had become so accustomed to it that they thought no more strangely of its devotees than they did of Christian Scientists, Theosophists, or Swedenborgians.

About ten o’clock, as we drove slowly along the silent lanes, no light was to be seen in any of the cottages. The grove was wrapped in stillness, and overhead the moon and the kindly stars looked down through the tangle of pine-boughs and helped us find our way out into the sweeter air of the open country.

A Voice in the Wilderness

The new book, A Tramp’s Sketches (Macmillan), by Stephen Graham, which has just been issued, is significant, to my mind at least, because it is a sign of that spirit which today is more and more making itself felt—in protest against the universal octopus of a squalid commercialism. It is a sincere plea for spiritual beauty in modern life, the cry of an honest man who has gone into the wilderness to find more space, who seeks, however, not to wreck, but to recreate. One may quarrel with the form and detail of his plea, but that it is wholesome, big and needed, no one can deny. The writer’s passionate worship of Beauty, his love of simplicity, his charity, his courage, all these make a strong appeal. He has in him poetry and vision; he strikes fearlessly; he is an honest rebel in vehement revolt; but a sane one. His deep conviction is felt in every description, in every adventure, in every comment and suggestion, and his message is one the world may well listen to as at least a little bit of stimulating leaven against the sordid commercialism that oppresses life everywhere today. Lord Dunsany, oddly enough, makes a somewhat similar plea in the English Review for October. The note sounds, indeed, from many quarters. It is in the air—a warning and a prophecy. Ostensibly these “sketches” describe the writer’s pilgrimage with Russian peasants to Jerusalem; but actually they are the notes of a spiritual pilgrim going towards the New Jerusalem. For he is no common “tramp”; there is genius in tramping as there is in painting pictures or in playing tennis. These are the notes of spiritual aspirations interpreting the incidents of the enormous journey that he made on foot, and to “review” the incidents merely would be to miss the real meaning of the book and thus give a false impression of its writer’s purpose. Details of the journey are to be published later, and will form a continuation of the work begun in his Undiscovered Russia—the full story of the places visited along the Black Sea shores, of the life of the pilgrims on the way to the Shrine of the Holy Sepulchre and at the Shrine itself. The interesting, and I would say the important, things in this book are the inner experiences of the tramp who is in rebellion, for to be a tramp, in the writer’s meaning, is to be one who has escaped—from the conventional moulds of life. “He is the walking hermit, the world-forsaker, but he is above all things a rebel and a prophet, and he stands in very distinct relation to the life of his time. … One reads every day such phrases as ‘our commercial, national and imperial welfare’—commercial first, national second, imperial third, and spiritual nowhere.” Here is the keynote of this vital but modest little book. And a hint of the earnestness of purpose which lies behind it may be gathered from the fact that the author did not merely join the pilgrims on the way, or meet them at the Shrine, but first went into Northern Russia and lived for months among them; lived as a muojik, let their thoughts and feelings soak into him until he understood them by inner sympathy—and then, as one of themselves, made the great pilgrimage of many thousand versts on foot to the Holy City.

“It is not so much a book about Russia as about the tramp … the wanderer and seeker … who has gone out into the wilderness. … It is with life itself that this volume is concerned,” and his observations upon life may be listened to for what wisdom is in them, because he is in such tremendous earnest, because he loves Beauty for its own sake and because he is constructive as well as critical. “Never in any preceding generation has the young man standing on the threshold of life felt more unsettled. … Never has he cast his eyes about more desperately for a way of redemption or a spiritual leader. For him, as for all of us, the one requirement is to find out what is the first thing to do…the essential thing, after which all other things naturally take their places.” Thus he writes after summing up the results of his many experiences and adventures. And he answers his own question thus: “It is not to wreck thc great machine”—of modern commercialism—“it is not even, as I think, to build a new machine … The one way and the first way is to use and subordinate the present machine, to limit it to its true domain, and let it be our true and vital servant”—a plea, in other words, for proportion, for higher ideals, less fever for gold, less ugly, hurried rush in the worship of that Moloch, Progress, a little more room for Beauty and inner spiritual endeavour; briefly, for simpler living. More space!

“But how?” By the combined effort of the flower of the race, those who at present are rebels, even tramps, but who, in view of their larger vision, might be spiritual leaders; and by ignoring “the smaller, meaner sort of man” which “the tremendous commercial machine is grinding out at a marvellous acceleration, the average man, ‘the damned, compact, liberal majority,’ to use the words of Ibsen. … For all the rest of ordinary humanity is waiting to live its life in relation to these (greater ones). By finding the few who can live the life of communion, the few who can show forth the true significance of the race. By saving our most precious thoughts and ideals, and adding them to the similar thoughts and ideals of others, by putting the instruments of education in their proper places, by separating and saving in the world of literature and art the expressions of Beauty which are valuable to the coming race, as distinguished from those that are merely sold for a price. By the making solitary, which is making sacred.”

And by way of allegory, typical of all, the writer suggests the “enfranchisement” of “famous and wonderful pictures now foiling and dwarfing one another in our vulgar galleries. Each great picture should be given a room to itself, like the Sistine Madonna, not only a room but a temple like that of the Iverskaya at Moscow, not only a temple, but a fair populous province. The great pictures should be objects of pilgrimages, and their temples places of prayer,” for great pictures, he urges, are very like great souls, and what is true for pictures is true for men. By these temples—of course, not temples made by hands—“we shall protect ourselves from the encroaching commercial machine, its dwarfing ethics, mean postulates, and accurst conventions, and we shall rear within the walls all the beautiful that the outside world says does not exist. We shall find a whole new world of those who despise the honours and prizes of the commercial machine … but it will not cause those of that world to falter if the great multitude of their fellow-men scoff at them or think that they miss life. … Our work, then, is to separate off and consecrate the beautiful, to bring the beautiful together and organise it, not renouncing the machine, but only taking from it the service necessary for our physical needs, in no case being ruled or guided by it or its exigencies. When we have accomplished that, a miracle is promised… The new heart means the salvation of all. … We are many: I speak for thousands who are voiceless. But we are feeble, for we know not one another: We shall know.”

To give broken quotations thus from the notebook of an idealist, I feel, is to risk injustice to their author, but I have taken the risk in order to show the deeper meaning which breathes everywhere through the pages of what is three-quarters a book of travel, and an uncommonly interesting one at that. Indeed, so deftly and unobtrusively is the idealism interwoven with the exciting adventures that the reader whom it bores may pass it by without detriment to his enjoyment of the narrative. He may even, if he will, skip the “Question of the Sceptic,” “The Unconquerable Hope,” “The Message from the Hermit” and, if he is recklessly unwise, “The Wanderer’s Story” too, though this latter is a subtle and penetrating allegory it is good to read; but he must in no case skip the fascinating descriptions of months of sleeping under the stars, in caves, on the seashore and among haunted Caucasian forests, nor omit the stories of "Hospitality," “The Rich Man and the Poor Man,” “A Lodging for the Night” and “How the Old Pilgrim Reached Bethlehem.” How the author-tramp lived on wild fruits and berries, made common meals and bed with most uncommon folk, defended himself from the ferocious Caucasian dogs and travelled with five hundred and sixty pilgrims in the hulk of a coasting vessel down the Black Sea shores—all this makes capital and diverting reading, And of particular interest is the account of his stay in the great Monastery of New Athos, and, of course, the final arrival of all the weary pilgrims at Jerusalem itself. The beauty and pathos of the scenes in the Holy City are movingly told—the baptism in the Jordan, all the pilgrims wearing their “death shroud,” the prostrations at Golgotha, and their ways and means of living in the Russian Settlement. One looks forward with keen interest to the more detailed volume that is to follow.

Accessory Before the Fact

At the moorland cross-roads Martin stood examining the sign-post for several minutes in some bewilderment. The names on the four arms were not what he expected, distances were not given, and his map, he concluded with impatience, must be hope- lessly out of date. Spreading it against the post, he stooped to study it more closely. The wind blew the corners flapping against his face. The small print was almost indecipherable in the fading light. It appeared, however—as well as he could make out—that two miles back he must have taken the wrong turning.

He remembered that turning. The path had looked inviting; he had hesitated a moment, then fol- lowed it, caught by the usual lure of walkers that it “might prove a short cut.” The short-cut snare is old as human nature. For some minutes he studied the sign-post and the map alternately. Dusk was falling, and his knapsack had grown heavy. He could not make the two guides tally, however, and a feeling of uncertainty crept over his mind. He felt oddly baffled, frustrated. His thought grew thick. Decision was most difficult. “I’m muddled,” he thought; “I must be tired,” as at length he chose the most likely arm. “Sooner or later it will bring me to an inn, though not the one I intended.” He accepted his walker’s luck, and started briskly. The arm read, “Over Litacy Hill” in small, fine letters that danced and shifted every time he looked at them; but the name was not discoverable on the map. It was, however, inviting like the short cut. A similar impulse again directed his choice. Only this time it seemed more insistent, almost urgent.

And he became aware, then, of the exceeding loneliness of the country about him. The road for a hundred yards went straight, then curved like a white river running into space; the deep blue-green of heather lined the banks, spreading upwards through the twilight; and occasional small pines stood solitary here and there, all unexplained. The curious adject- ive, having made its appearance, haunted him. So many things that afternoon were similarly—unex- plained: the short cut, the darkened map, the names on the sign-post, his own erratic impulses, and the growing strange confusion that crept upon his spirit.

The entire country-side needed explanation, though perhaps “interpretation” was the truer word. Those little lonely trees had made him see it. Why had he lost his way so easily? Why did he suffer vague impressions to influence his direction? Why was he here—exactly here? And why did he go now “over Lit- acy Hill”? Then, by a green field that shone like a thought of daylight amid the darkness of the moor, he saw a fig- ure lying in the grass. It was a blot upon the land- scape, a mere huddled patch of dirty rags, yet with a certain horrid picturesqueness too; and his mind—though his German was of the schoolroom order—at once picked out the German equivalents as against the English. Lump and Lumpen flashed across his brain most oddly. They seemed in that moment right, and so expressive, almost like onomatopoeic words, if that were possible of sight. Neither “rags” nor “rascal” would have fitted what he saw. The adequate descrip- tion was in German.

Here was a clue tossed up by the part of him that did not reason. But it seems he missed it. And the next minute the tramp rose to a sitting posture and asked the time of evening. In German he asked it.

And Martin, answering without a second’s hesitation, gave it, also in German, “halb sieben”—half-past six.

The instinctive guess was accurate. A glance at his watch when he looked a moment later proved it. He heard the man say, with the covert insolence of tramps, “T’ank you; much opliged.” For Martin had not shown his watch—another intuition subcon- sciously obeyed.

He quickened his pace along that lonely road, a curious jumble of thoughts and feelings surging through him. He had somehow known the question would come, and come in German. Yet it flustered and dismayed him. Another thing had also flustered and dismayed him. He had expected it in the same queer fashion: it was right. For when the ragged brown thing rose to ask the question, a part of it remained lying on the grass—another brown, dirty thing. There were two tramps. And he saw both faces clearly. Behind the untidy beards, and below the old slouch hats, he caught the look of unpleasant, clever faces that watched him closely while he passed. The eyes followed him. For a second he looked straight into those eyes, so that he could not fail to know them. And he understood, quite horridly, that both faces were too sleek, refined, and cunning for those of ordinary tramps. The men were not really tramps at all. They were disguised.

“How covertly they watched me!” was his thought, as he hurried along the darkening road, aware in dead earnestness now of the loneliness and desolation of the moorland all about him. Uneasy and distressed, he increased his pace. Midway in thinking what an unnecessarily clanking noise his nailed boots made upon the hard white road, there came upon him with a rush together the company of these things that haunted him as “unexplained.” They brought a single definite message: That all this busi- ness was not really meant for him at all, and hence his confusion and bewilderment; that he had intruded into someone else’s scenery, and was tres- passing upon another’s map of life. By some wrong inner turning he had interpolated his person into a group of foreign forces which operated in the little world of someone else. Unwittingly, somewhere, he had crossed the threshold, and now was fairly in—a trespasser, an eavesdropper, a Peeping Tom. He was listening, peeping; overhearing things he had no right to know, because they were intended for another.

Like a ship at sea he was intercepting wireless mes- sages he could not properly interpret, because his Receiver was not accurately tuned to their reception.

And more—these messages were warnings! Then fear dropped upon him like the night. He was caught in a net of delicate, deep forces he could not manage, knowing neither their origin nor pur- pose. He had walked into some huge psychic trap elaborately planned and baited, yet calculated for another than himself. Something had lured him in, something in the landscape, the time of day, his mood. Owing to some undiscovered weakness in himself he had been easily caught. His fear slipped easily into terror.

What happened next happened with such speed and concentration that it all seemed crammed into a moment. At once and in a heap it happened. It was quite inevitable. Down the white road to meet him a man came swaying from side to side in drunkenness quite obviously feigned—a tramp; and while Martin made room for him to pass, the lurch changed in a second to attack, and the fellow was upon him. The blow was sudden and terrific, yet even while it fell Martin was aware that behind him rushed a second man, who caught his legs from under him and bore him with a thud and crash to the ground. Blows rained then; he saw a gleam of something shining; a sudden deadly nausea plunged him into utter weak- ness where resistance was impossible. Something of fire entered his throat, and from his mouth poured a thick sweet thing that choked him. The world sank far away into darkness. … Yet through all the horror and confusion ran the trail of two clear thoughts: he realised that the first tramp had sneaked at a fast double through the heather and so come down to meet him; and that something heavy was torn from fastenings that clipped it tight and close beneath his clothes against his body. …

Abruptly then the darkness lifted, passed utterly away. He found himself peering into the map against the signpost. The wind was flapping the corners against his cheek, and he was poring over names that now he saw quite clear. Upon the arms of the sign- post above were those he had expected to find, and the map recorded them quite faithfully. All was accurate again and as it should be. He read the name of the village he had meant to make—it was plainly visible in the dusk, two miles the distance given.

Bewildered, shaken, unable to think of anything, he stuffed the map into his pocket unfolded, and hur- ried forward like a man who has just wakened from an awful dream that had compressed into a single second all the detailed misery of some prolonged, oppressive nightmare.

He broke into a steady trot that soon became a run; the perspiration poured from him; his legs felt weak, and his breath was difficult to manage. He was only conscious of the overpowering desire to get away as fast as possible from the sign-post at the cross-roads where the dreadful vision had flashed upon him. For Martin, accountant on a holiday, had never dreamed of any world of psychic possibilities.

The entire thing was torture. It was worse than a “cooked” balance of the books that some conspiracy of clerks and directors proved at his innocent door.

He raced as though the country-side ran crying at his heels. And always still ran with him the incredible conviction that none of this was really meant for himself at all. He had overheard the secrets of another. He had taken the warning for another into himself, and so altered its direction. He had thereby prevented its right delivery. It all shocked him bey- ond words. It dislocated the machinery of his just and accurate soul. The warning was intended for another, who could not—would not—now receive it.

The physical exertion, however, brought at length a more comfortable reaction and some measure of composure. With the lights in sight, he slowed down and entered the village at a reasonable pace. The inn was reached, a bedroom inspected and engaged, and supper ordered with the solid comfort of a large Bass to satisfy an unholy thirst and complete the restora- tion of balance. The unusual sensations largely passed away, and the odd feeling that anything in his simple, wholesome world required explanation was no longer present. Still with a vague uneasiness about him, though actual fear quite gone, he went into the bar to smoke an after-supper pipe and chat with the natives, as his pleasure was upon a holiday, and so saw two men leaning upon the counter at the far end with their backs towards him. He saw their faces instantly in the glass, and the pipe nearly slipped from between his teeth. Clean-shaven, sleek, clever faces—and he caught a word or two as they talked over their drinks—German words. Well dressed they were, both men, with nothing about them calling for particular attention; they might have been two tour- ists holiday-making like himself in tweeds and walk- ing-boots. And they presently paid for their drinks and went out. He never saw them face to face at all; but the sweat broke out afresh all over him, a feverish rush of heat and ice together ran about his body; bey- ond question he recognised the two tramps, this time not disguised—not yet disguised.

He remained in his corner without moving, puff- ing violently at an extinguished pipe, gripped help- lessly by the return of that first vile terror. It came again to him with an absolute clarity of certainty that it was not with himself they had to do, these men, and, further, that he had no right in the world to interfere. He had no locus standi at all; it would be immoral … even if the opportunity came. And the opportunity, he felt, would come. He had been an eavesdropper, and had come upon private informa- tion of a secret kind that he had no right to make use of, even that good might come—even to save life. He sat on in his corner, terrified and silent, waiting for the thing that should happen next.

But night came without explanation. Nothing happened. He slept soundly. There was no other guest at the inn but an elderly man, apparently a tourist like himself. He wore gold-rimmed glasses, and in the morning Martin overheard him asking the landlord what direction he should take for Litacy Hill. His teeth began then to chatter and a weakness came into his knees. “You turn to the left at the cross- roads,” Martin broke in before the landlord could reply; “you’ll see the sign-post about two miles from here, and after that it’s a matter of four miles more.” How in the world did he know, flashed horribly through him. “I’m going that way myself,” he was say- ing next; “I’ll go with you for a bit—if you don’t mind!” The words came out impulsively and ill-con- sidered; of their own accord they came. For his own direction was exactly opposite. He did not want the man to go alone. The stranger, however, easily evaded his offer of companionship. He thanked him with the remark that he was starting later in the day. … They were standing, all three, beside the horse-trough in front of the inn, when at that very moment a tramp, slouching along the road, looked up and asked the time of day. And it was the man with the gold- rimmed glasses who told him.

“T’ank you; much opliged,” the tramp replied, passing on with his slow, slouching gait, while the landlord, a talkative fellow, proceeded to remark upon the number of Germans that lived in England and were ready to swell the Teutonic invasion which he, for his part, deemed imminent.

But Martin heard it not. Before he had gone a mile upon his way he went into the woods to fight his conscience all alone. His feebleness, his cowardice, were surely criminal. Real anguish tortured him. A dozen times he decided to go back upon his steps, and a dozen times the singular authority that whispered he had no right to interfere prevented him. How could he act upon knowledge gained by eavesdropping? How interfere in the private business of another’s hidden life merely because he had over- heard, as at the telephone, its secret dangers? Some inner confusion prevented straight thinking alto- gether. The stranger would merely think him mad.

He had no “fact” to go upon. … He smothered a hundred impulses … and finally went on his way with a shaking, troubled heart.

The last two days of his holiday were ruined by doubts and questions and alarms—all justified later when he read of the murder of a tourist upon Litacy Hill. The man wore gold-rimmed glasses, and carried in a belt about his person a large sum of money. His throat was cut.

And the police were hard upon the trail of a mys- terious pair of tramps, said to be—Germans.

After the War

One often hears the question: After the war, when passion has subsided, what shall we have to say to Germans—to an individual German? What will our men, our women have to say? What will our thought and feeling, our attitude be? We cannot exclude them all from our intercourse forever; somewhere, sooner or later, individual English will come across individual Germans under conditions where some sort of intercourse will be imposed. Apart from old friendships that may survive the present shock, what treatment will an average Englishman accord an average German whom necessity, social or business, brings his way?

The answer, of course, will vary with individuals. So far as business is concerned, and for the most part, the merchant will buy and sell to the end of time where his profit lies, and, provided goods are sound and drafts are honoured, he is not concerned with the personal morality of his customer. Economic leagues of anti-German kind may hamper, even prevent such intercourse, but, speaking generally, business is impersonal. Socially, however—in the big sense “socially”—the answer is not easy. The question is a very pregnant one. There are some who will rise to the level of a great forgiveness possibly. And—there are others!

No matter how crushing the terms of peace we may be able to exact, nor how disastrous to Germany the material burden of eventual defeat, there are many who think that her severest punishment—adequately effective because the gods decree it—will lie in the treatment that for years to come the individual members of the allied nations will accord the individual Teuton whom they may be obliged to meet. Not that it will be treatment prompted necessarily by spite, by anger, least of all by desire for revenge, but that it must arise out of the conditions of the German soul which their method of making war, as well as their methods of preparing for war in time of peace, has so terribly laid bare.

The plain man cannot so easily purge his mind and memory of the loathing and horror that “frightfulness” has accumulated there; the failure of the ghastly policy (its material failure may be left to the naval and military experts) lies, to take the lowest ground merely, in the truth that it is not worth while. Its destructive effect is temporary at best, its stupendous reaction is a lasting one. It is an offence against a Higher Command for which a just retribution must be exacted to the uttermost farthing.

And not the most easily paid of these said farthings may probably be those in current social use over the greater part of Europe when the war is over. They will be paid, they will be exacted, by individuals—even by those whom a loftier ideal persuades into the Christian attitude of forgiving and trying to forget. The name of Hun has been too thoroughly deserved. The individual of the Allied nations who meets a German will instinctively—whether with his mind, his body, or his soul—turn away. Win or lose, the Teuton will be disliked, distrusted; the uncivilised savagery of his Government will cling to him like the broad arrow of the convict’s brand.

It was some weeks ago, in Montreux, that this probability first came home to me. The little neutral town was full of foreigners; there were French and Russians, Italians (it was before the declaration of war by Italy), and Poles, Belgians by the hundred, and many English; there were also contingents from the Argentine and Brazil, Chilians, Americans too—and there were Germans. I have lived much in Germany; they were what I call “nice Germans”—the learned, scholarly kind, mingled with the well-to-do middle class, all elderly, and nothing aggressively national about them anywhere. Montreux in the spring is a favourite resort with them; they came as usual. Feeling surprise that they chose a part of Switzerland that was outspokenly on the side of the Allies, whereas German-Switzerland sympathised with their cause, the proprietor of a large restaurant enlightened me cynically enough with the explanation: “Parcequ’ici on mange mieux!” But it was the reciprocal attitude of these Germans and the other foreigners in the little neutral haven that I wished to mention chiefly—the way the former kept strictly to themselves, and the way the latter obviously avoided them. For all the foreigners, not only those of the fighting races, left them severely alone; no one would speak to them; no one, it seemed, wished to have dealings or intercourse with them even of the slightest kind. The Germans, always in the most comfortable hotels, remained apart; they sat in groups, they ate, they walked in groups. They read exclusively their own newspapers, or the newspapers of Zurich, Bale, and Lucerne that were friendly to them; the Gazette de Lausanne, or the Tribune de Geneve, so hostile to their country, they never opened. The women knitted all day long, the men talked eagerly—the anxiety on their faces struck me forcibly—across their table in the corner of the crowded hall and when anyone not German passed within earshot it was noticeable that they all talked—French!

It touched one’s imagination as a foretaste of what must probably come on a bigger scale when the war is over and the nations are at peace again. To be sent to Coventry by the people of at least five important European countries, to be unable to indulge the strong love of travelling in these said five countries as before, would seem to promise a severe restriction that must guide the nation thus penalised towards a rather penetrating kind of introspection. The individual, surely, more than ever before, will ask himself the question: Why—and think upon the problem. But, will it touch him? Will he care? Will it teach him—anything?

The plain man could easily give the answer to that pregnant “Why?” But will the German listen? And, if he listens, will the meaning penetrate his unimaginative brain? At present, of course, his Government takes good care that he shall not have the opportunity to hear, much less to listen; but after the war there will be ample opportunities that no official “verboten” can prevent. There are some who think his hide may be penetrated then, that he will care, that he will even learn—in a way that material defeat could never compass, though material defeat and the consequent respect engendered is a necessary precursor of a greater open-mindedness to follow. For material defeat is physical and mental in its results, whereas “coventry,” in the large sense, is spiritual in its effects. It may touch the soul in him. The essential cad, so fortified, so jubilant in him at the moment, will begin to—wonder: “was it, after all, worth while—this frightfulness of ours?”

In a recent issue of the Berliner Tageblatt a certain Friedrich von Conring discusses the question: “Why is Germany so universally disliked?” Dismissing the usual answers (“envy born of rivalry, conduct of German travellers, our internal political structure, our want of sentiment,” and the like), he finds the answer as follows: “This infinite hatred, in my opinion, simply originates in the fact that we have not known how to capture and satisfy the aspirations and the fancies of foreign peoples, and have not known how to work on their imagination.” After suggesting naively that this desired foreign love may be obtained by “the development of our artistic activities to a characteristic style of beauty, and its adoption and extension throughout the world,” he concludes with the boastful doubt: “Whether, then, we shall win the love of foreign nations is a question which I dare not decide. Perhaps, however, when the time comes, we shall cease to trouble about it.”

If this be a representative opinion it must appear that the German, after the war, will neither listen nor learn. For the “Kultur” whose worldwide adoption is here offered is not wanted; the “foreign nations” will none of it; the plain man does not want it. It is found wanting. It has been proved linked with frightfulness. A truer answer to his answer is easily given—that the world hates a cad. Frightfulness is caddishness; it is an entire absence of the sporting spirit so strong always in a “gentleman.” The “gentleman” is a good loser, plays fair, scorns a mean advantage. The cad does none of these things, thinking them childish weakness. He uses a knuckle-duster inside his gloves, plays tricks with the ground before the challenge is even out, keeps cunning devices up his sleeve to surprise his adversary. In a word, devoid of chivalry, he knows no rules, and glories in the fact as a legitimate source of strength. The list is a staggering one. Atrocities may be left out of the account on both sides, it being granted that an individual soldier in blind rage, or drunk, or in revenge may commit a dreadful act—it is the deliberate, thought-out, cold-blooded policy that has struck civilisation so cowardly a blow and staggered the feeling of the world. The crimes calculated calmly in time of peace! From the use of gas and liquid fire to poisonous shells and burning pitch the record passes on to rape, arson, slaughter of prisoners and noncombatants, and every conceivable savage horror. There is no principle in the international law of warfare which the Germans have not violated in order to produce their desired effect of terror. The order of General Stenger, commanding the 58th Brigade of German Infantry, stated, on August 26: “From and after today no more prisoners are to be taken. All prisoners are to be massacred. The wounded, whether with or without arms, are to be killed off. No living enemy must be left behind us.” “French prisoners,” records a soldier’s captured diary, “who were severely wounded and could not get up received another bullet which put an end to them. These were the orders given to us.”

Humanity resents, abhors a bully; dislikes, despises a cad, even when it fears him. One always comes back to the Man in the Street. What will Humanity’s Man in the Street—the streets of five civilised nations—have to say to him? Has the genial, good-natured, sentimental German of sausage and sauerkraut, of beer “stein” and length pipe, gone forever? Is he now become instead the cad of Europe, the outcast of the civilised world; and is he to remain so?

On this large scale the opinion of the plain man may produce a regenerating effect. The opinion of the individuals of five countries who know chivalry, who play the game, who fight in a nobler spirit, is a force to be reckoned with, at any rate. For the plain man stands for common sense, the great, wholesome average. What Tom, Dick, and Harry think has value, though individually Tom, Dick, and Harry may be of limited intelligence. Collectively they are important, and it is the collective sense that decides wars, elects Parliaments, kills certain taxes, judges a man as hero, statesman, fool, or—cad. In sheer numbers it is as the sand; it stands for countless millions; it was the French Revolution; today it is khaki, but khaki in five editions. Above racial prejudice, which may be narrow; above political bias, which may be petty; above any of the lesser divisions of mankind caused by creed, by temperament, by climate, this collective judgment of the world today—far more than merely of the Allies—condemns Germany’s dishonour, resents her universal trickery, abhors her frightfulness. After the war the individual German, made aware of this heavy judgment, may discern the true answer to von Conring’s question, and asking himself another question: “Was it worth while?” may find the answer to that, too—and learn a better way.

Alexander Alexander

His Christian name and surname were the same, and the fact that he insisted upon their proper use, respectively, made things of ten most unpleas- ant. His sombre dignity forbade familiarity. If, greatly daring, I said “Hullo, Alexander!” using his Christian name, he would assume a stern and frightening air:

“Alexander! If you please,” he would say icily. “Use my right name.”

Herein lay, perhaps, the heart of that dark secret which deceived mean for so my years, as also the essence of that horror his double masquerade con- cealed: Whereas, between Alexander and Alexander none knew which was which, he—alone of all the world—he knew!

To me, as a little girl, there was something por- tentous about him always. More than a common man, he was a Personage, a Figure. With the passage of the years my conception of him grew, for his bulk and stature grew at the same time, until, more than man, or personage, or figure, he became almost that emanation of legendary life—a Being. Although the original sharp outline remained, he spread himself out somehow over an immense, dim background, against which that first outline yet held itself fixed in vivid silhouette. I conceive him as both remote and very close, as shadow and substance, an unreality yet dreadfully composed of solid flesh and blood.

This confusion in my own mind added enor- mously to the mystery of his strange existence; but it was the mistake in the use of his name that remained chiefly serious, a crime of untold import, since it was I myself who first—christened him. To call him by a wrong name, therefore, was an insult to his actuality, a careless and unpardonable sacrilege that trifled with the essential nature of his personality.

I lived with an uncle, who was also my guardian, and this mystifying double role contributed, no doubt, an element to the birth of Alexander Alexan- der. Some childhood’s divination dramatised itself perhaps. If so, this earliest creative drama had a prophetic, even a clairvoyant, quality that enabled him to endure until he had fully justified his dark existence. Both Alexander and Alexander persisted through my girlhood. Only at the threshold of wom- anhood, when I came of age at twenty-one, did the dreadful pair pass hand in hand to their final distress- ing dissolution.

He—Alexander—often came to see my uncle, who, I divined, was a good deal afraid of him—a fact that impressed me painfully. He was tall, dark, angu- lar, and so thin that he always looked cold, even in the sunshine; as though, having left off his flesh, as others leave off their thick underwear, he was for ever shivering in his bones. Of those mummied Pharaohs he reminded me. He had the great square jaw, deep eyes, heavy cheek-bones, and copious hair those gloomy figures of prodigious personality bear tire- lessly with them down the ages. He walked on his toes a little, adding thus to the appearance of his height. He took, too, an immense and swinging stride, with an easy gliding motion that seemed to flow. His extraordinary swiftness of movement made me think of running water.

Oh, Alexander—or do I mean Alexander?—how you impressed me when I was about six years old! Which “Alexander”? I don’t quite know, to tell the truth. Years passed before I got even an inkling.

The names still flow, like parallel rivers, down and through my consciousness, to lose themselves in the depths of some mysterious dream-ocean where, at length and at last, they become merged, I believe, in one. There were certainly two of them—once. There was Alexander, and there was Alexander. I can swear to it.

It was his—Alexander’s copious hair that impressed me vividly at the age of six. It was smoothed down with shiny grease whose faint, but not unpleasant, aroma came into a room before its wearer, and hung about in the air long after he had left. Hair, perfume, grease, all fascinated me.

“That’s pomade,” explained my nurse, answering a question and using a strange new word. Then, fearful of some wrong use I might make of the information, she added: “and no business of yours, remember, either.” The queer word seized me; it remained hang- ing about my mind … pomade, pomade. How vividly, with what lasting depth and sharpness these early impressions score the mind of a child, so ten- derly receptive. No wonder the psychologists dive after them to explain the irregularities of nerve and memory that emerge in later life. The name Alexan- der, to begin with, carried me away. It bore me along with it. There was movement in it. Jones, Green, Brown, one syllable names, are stationary and fixed; but “Alexander” had a glide. It was a watery move- ment; I always connected it with water. It flowed round and through and under me. It bore me easily away with it. I saw a rapid stream, whose undulating surface had no actual waves, owing to its speed, but swept along in rhythmic rise and fall, like a brimmed rivulet across a sloping meadow. My feet gave under me, and I was off. “Alexander, Alexander, oh, why cannot you meander? “I used to murmur to myself, using another strange new word I had discovered, a suitable word since it was the name of a river that also flowed. I saw copious hair, pomade, a lean, dark, careering figure on its toes, swinging rapidly down my mind with a pulse of hurrying water.

He was a solicitor, I imagined, and the name only half understood, somehow to me suggested prison; and my uncle, who was also my legal guardian, I fan- cied had done something wrong. It was rather con- fusing having an uncle who was guardian too. It puz- zled me. My uncle was reserved, secretive—that is, as “guardian,” he was reserved, secretive; for as “uncle” he was affectionate, playful, kind, and very dear to me. I had this mingled fear and love.

The name had a strange power. I was, perhaps, nine years old when the goose frightened me in the yard behind the stables, and some undigested fairy- tale made me think its clacking beak was going to bite me into pieces. Pulling down my little skirts frantically to protect my bare legs, I found the bad rhyme instantly, though I may have shaped it actually a little later:

Alexander, Alexander,
Oh, come down into the yard!
For I’m frightened at the gander—
Oh, come quick with your pomade!

And he came. That was what lived with me for years, increasing enormously his influence. He came at once. The glass door of the conservatory opened, and out he poured with amazing swiftness, on his toes, turning his thin, dark face and head towards me. His great stride brought him up to me in a moment. He was, I believe, really looking for my uncle, who was in the stables just then, examining the horses. But it was in answer to my cry that he was beside me in a second. I caught the whiff of the pomade.

“Oh, Alexander—!” I cried, relieved, but also alarmed.

“Alexander,” he corrected me sternly, his deep eyes staring, while the gander retreated and left me safe at once. Yet, when I turned round again from watching the retreating bird, he—Alexander—had disappeared, and my uncle—or was it my guardian?—was coming towards me from the stables with a smile. The incident, at any rate, left a deep impres- sion on me. The use—the correct use—of the great name evidently carried away with its own movement.

I saw him only occasionally as I grew older; dur- ing holidays, when home from school, and later, from a year in Paris to improve my French and acquire manners and deportment. He was aged in the eyes, and skin, and gait. The stream of his name no longer brimmed its banks as formerly. But the spell remained. And the pomaded hair kept young as ever. My uncle, I now realised somehow, welcomed his visits, yet while dreading them. I thought of the two at the time, I remember, as driver and driven in some mysterious enterprise of financial kind. They were. But Alexander was the driven, and Alexander held the whip. And once, lying half asleep in bed, a horrible suspicion came to me that my uncle—or was it my guardian?—knew. Knew what? Why “horrible?” I could not say, I felt it, that’s all.

A week after my return from Paris—I was to be of age next day—I was standing in the passage when he called. Thomas was leading the way. It was just out- side the study door.

“Mr. Alexander to see you, sir,” I heard him announced.

The visitor glowered with vexation. “Mr. Alexander,” he rebuked the servant in a low tone, as he swung through the door on his toes into the study, where my uncle, or my guardian evidently awaited him. And as I heard the name, in the way he uttered it, a sudden wave of cold anxiety, more of acute dis- tress, broke over me. As that lean, dark, pomaded head flowed round the open door with its extraordi- nary swiftness, and vanished, I felt afraid. The foot- man went past me with an expressionless face, but it seemed to me that his face was ghastly white. He dis- appeared in the empty hall beyond; I heard the green baize door into the nether regions swing to behind him with its customary gulp. But the draught of its closing came to me across all that distance; so that I felt it on my cheeks. And its touch was icy. I stood there shivering, unable at first to move or think. A vague dread and wonder held me. What were Alexan- der and Alexander saying to my uncle and my guardian?

What steps to take I knew not. For I was aware that I ought to take steps at once. My hesitation was caused by an inexplicable fear. It was the fear of my guardian, but for my uncle. Is that clear? While dreading my guardian, I felt, I knew, that I must help my uncle. Two courses seemed open to me: to enter the room, or to follow the footman and ask him an awful question.

I chose the latter. In a moment I was through the green baize door that led into the servants’ quarters; but, as I ran, a new suspicion fastened on me. It fas- tened on my spine where the shivering was. I was amazed and horror-stricken. For the suspicion was so complete that it must actually have lain in me a long, long time already.

“Thomas,” I said, breathlessly; “the gentleman you showed in just now—who was it?”

“I beg pardon, Miss,” he said, staring blankly. I asked the question a second time. “Showed in, Miss,” he repeated stupidly.

“The tall, dark gentleman,” I insisted, in a failing voice, “you just showed in to—” (I could not, for the life of me, say “my uncle’s”)—“into Mr. Burton’s study—Mr.—Mr.—?” I stammered and stuck fast.

The man paused a moment, with a puzzled air. He stared at me. “I showed no gentleman in, Miss,” he said, a trifle offended, his voice firm and decided. “Mr. Burton rang for—” (it was his turn to hesitate)—“for something to drink, Miss. And I just took it in to him.”

I knew then. I knew it all at once, complete. I tore back. But my thought raced faster than my legs. An elaborate fabric built most carefully, and standing firm for years, collapsed into ghastly ruins. The foot- man’s face, I remembered, was always white. My nurse, now dead, had always fallen in with my fan- cies. My uncle was tall and thin and dark, and had always worn pomaded hair. But it was only when I reached the study door that the final film cleared off, letting in the appalling light. For I suddenly remem- bered another thing as well; he acknowledged to a buried name. Hidden away among several others, he owned a name he never used. His full name, of course, was Frank Henry Alexander Burton.

I stood transfixed outside the door.

But precious minutes were passing. “Oh, Alexander, Alexander,” rushed down my mind. The childhood’s rhyme was about to follow, yard, gander, pomade and all, when a sound inside the room sent the ice again down my spine. It made my will tighten at the same time. I might be too late even now. With- out knocking, I rushed into the room. The desk was strewn with documents and papers. A decanter of spirits stood beside them, with a half-emptied glass. The French windows were open on the lawn. The summer air came in. There was a faint aroma of pomade. But I was too late. The room was empty. “Oh, Alexander!” I gasped, petrified by the emptiness, and was about to add “Alexander” when a horrid weakness came over me and a blackness rose before my face. My legs collapsed. I fell into a dead faint on the floor. …

It was “by water” of course, and the verdict was death by drowning while of unsound mind. I saw the body next day. It was my uncle’s, not my guardian’s body. The hair, for the first time, I saw tangled.

Oh, Alexander, Alexander! Merged at last in one! You, Alexander, left me a pauper. But for you, Alexander, I have still kind memories of a weak, affectionate, and sorely tempted uncle. …

Algonquin Songs and Legends

I

It seems strange that a tribe of Redskins, whose favourite method of torturing their captives was to make them walk barefoot over a fire of hemlock coals until relieved by death, could also have produced so tender and delicate a song of the stars as the following:

We are the stars which
We sing with our light
We are the birds of tire
We fly across the heaven
Our light is a star
We make a road tor spirits
A road tor the Great Spirit
Among us are three huntet
Who chase a beat
There never was a time
When they were not hunting
We look down on the mountains
This is the Song of the Mountains

And there is a similar strange charm in many another song of the Algonquin (New England) Red Indians, whose legends and traditions, orally chanted from generation to generation, have been saved from oblivion by the literal translations of Professor Dvyneley Prince and the late Charles Leland.[3] They con stitute an uncommonly interesting bit of aboriginal literature and of a race now so rapidly perishing that “ in fifty years there will be hardly a single representative left.’ Both Prince and Leland, familiar with their many dialects, collected the songs and stories by taking them down from the mouths of Indians whose confidence they gained, and in these translations have kept the primitive, irregular rhythm of the original. The results cannot fail to interest all who love real poetry and feel sympathy with Nature, wild Nature especially ; and many of the poems, tales of adventure or of love, have a tender delicacy of treatment that is quite exquisite, yet comes strangely from tribes so savage and so cruel in their daily life. ‘‘ Few, indeed, are those,” says Leland, ‘* who ever suspected till of late years that every hill and dale in New England had its romantic legend, its beautiful poem or its marvellous myth—the latter equal in conception and form to those of the Edda—or that a vast collection of these traditions still survives in perfect preserva- tion among the few remaining Indians of New England and the Northeast Coast.’’ The best, from a literary point of view, comments Prince, are from the Passamaquoddy branch of the Algonquins: ‘1 need only call the reader’s attention to the very remarkable song recording the attack of the squirrels on Lappilatwan, who dwelt in the birch tree, ‘ever sitting with his mouth open,’ to which I know no parallel in any othet literature. Lappilatwan was a tree-fungus who sang the ‘ signal song to all wood-birds, worms and insects to go to sleep,’ and also announced the breaking of a beautiful day The squirrels envied him his nest, and decided to evict him, and he was only saved from this humiliation by the flies, after a terrible battle in which there were many scalps taken on both sides. The sympathy of the poet is on the side of the flies, and his description of the fight ts also a description of an Indian attack : only a few squirrels could rush up the birch tree at one time, whereas the flies came upon them from all sides. Their ‘ sharp spears’ did effective work; the battle waged till sunset, and then the cry of the fungus at sunset proclaimed the first victory : ‘ Lappilatwan, Fair tree-fungus, Sits with mouth open.’ ”

Soon as they heard it,
All of the warriors
Squirrels and insects
Valiant mosquitoes,
Humble hornets,
Bold bumblebees,
Wild, whizzing wasps,
Gallant, merry midges,
Went to their wigwams
Lappilat wan
Had faith in his warriors

Next morning his sunrise-cry was the signal for renewed hostilities ; the flies were unequal to a night attack, though they spent the dark hours “ sharpening their spears, Dipping them in poison, Loud was their buzz.”

Winged warriors
By many thousands
Swarmed on the foe;
Many a horsefly
Beheld no more
His wife and children ;
Many a hornet
Sat no more
By the fire of his wigwam ;
The dying bumblebee
Chanted his death song,

and at sunset the fair tree-fungus sang his little evening-song in safety :

All was over
High on the birch-tree
Untouched by a foeman
Sat the Watchman
The flies were victorious !

“The humour,” says Professor Prince, “is as Greek as the form is Norse.”” The adjectives describing the various insects are significant, and anyone who has hunted in these woods will appreciate the terror of the flies and rejoice in their discomfiture. “Lappilatwan, the Singer in the Dusk,” is a Passamaquoddy song, as already noted. ‘‘ The wonderful song of Nipon, the Summer, and the truly tender legend of the loves of the Leaf and the Firebird serve still further to illustrate the purity of Passamaquoddy thought and diction.”

Nipon, a beautiful woman, dressed in green leaves, lived near the sun, and her grandmother, the Rain, who dwelt far away, but sometimes came to visit her, warned her against Pan, the winter. She must never go into the Northland or she would die. There is a charming description of the longing that came over Nipon to investigate for herself?:

One fair morning
She sat by her wigwam
In the bright sunshine,
And looking afar
At the Latogwesnuk (Northland
All that she saw
Seemed strangely lovely
As if enchanted.
No human being
Was in the Northland ;
A wonderful land:
Broad shining lakes,
High blue mountains,
Bright rolling rivers,
All strange and sweet.
Something came over her
She knew not what;
A dream or a voice;
There was no help,
She must rise and go
Unto the Northland.

The voice of the Rain, “a-wailing, though she could not see her,” came to warn in vain. Nipon yielded to the spell and went- months and months of travel, until one day she noted that “as she followed, the land went onward, and as she travelled, It travelled before her’’—a touch of vivid description that betrays a race accustomed to covering distances so immense that the country appears to go with one instead of being left behind. Then “something she never had known came over her: She felt the cold! An unseen power Now drove her onward; Will had departed. Her dress of green grew yellow and faded, Her hair turned white, The sun grew dim, she was very weak, The beautiful mountains were heaps of snow, The lovely rivers and lakes were ice—all in the North.”

A striking description follows of the battle between the warm winds, summoned by Granny Rain, and the cold winds sent forth by Pan; it is full of poetry and deep Nature-feeling, and the storming of the winds is vividly and boisterously given. Of course, the South comes out victor. Pun grows more and more uncomfortable: ‘‘ Even as he spoke, The sweat dropped from him, His face grew thin, His feet seemed smaller, And the mild south winds Were ever warmer, And bigger grew the drops Upon Piin’s face; His strength had left him. Down he fell, And in his falling A leg was broken!” He recalls his icy winds and sets Nipon free. Her return home is as tender a description of the coming of summer over the cruel, desolate forests of Algonquin country as one could wish to read. The girl’s dress grew greener, days and shadows longer, the hills were blue, the rivers rushed, flowers unfolded, and as Nipon’s hair turned darker, her face grew lighter, fairer, sweeter, as it had been in her early beauty, until at last “ the butterflies knew her again.” The scolding she received from Granny Rain, who was waiting in her wigwam—*“ The ancient Rain-mother, weaker and older, and worn and wearv ’’—is a model of dignified warning, advice and rebuke :

Thou hast well-nigh killed me !
By disobedience
Thou hast brought suffering
On me and all things.
But for my battle
With Pan, the winter,
All life had perished :
Never again though,
While life is in me,
Can I venture
On such a struggle !
Be this thy warning
Else will Pan,
The cruel winter,
Conquer all things,
And ice and snow
Forever and ever
Cover the world.

After a brief description of another Passamaquoddy lyric, “ The Scarlet Tanager and the Leaf,” we may pass on to look at the even more interesting songs of the Indian Witchcraft lore. Should this little notice send a few readers to the original, they will find themselves well repaid. This love-story of the Fire Bird and the Leaf, ‘‘ merry little Mipis,” has an exquisite quality that quotations can hardly reproduce. ‘ Mipis, when spring is coming and summer is shining, climbs a tree, and there, all summer, dressed in green, he rocks in the branches, listens all day to the birds and the breezes and goes to sleep to the song of the owl.” In the autumn he dresses himself in scarlet, but with the colder nights changes this to brown or yellow, ‘curls himself up like a bear for winter, lets go his hold and falls to the ground. And there he sleeps, all under the snow- drift, till he hears the bluebird calling.” Then up he climbs again and enjoys another summer. His meeting with the Fire Bird and their falling in love together is very sweetly told: Mipis was “ stretching himself” in the morning sunshine when he heard wonderful singing, and on looking up, saw before him “a beautiful merry little bird-girl, dressed in garments of brilliant scarlet.””. He promptly enquired who she was:

I am the Little Fire
When I fly in the forest
And meet in my way a bar of sunshine,
I look, as I enter and leave the shadow,
Like a red flame which leaps up in darkness,
And then falls asleep in the night again.

And she proceeds to explain that she has been sent to find him as a reward by The Mighty Mountain, who “ well loves my music.” The Leaf, however, is suspicious at first, having been warned by his grandmother that “ even the smallest insect may eat your life out. A worm so little that it can pass through the prick of a needle, even as a rabbit runs through a valley, or a fish swims free up a river, may cut your stem or blight your beauty.”” Instead of arguing, the Fire Bird sings. Leaves and butterflies stop to listen; even the ants stop running. Mipis melts :

And as the music grew tender and stronger,
And as in one long soft note it ended,
Little Leaf said to her: ‘ Be my own,”

Their subsequent adventures in the little wigwam they built in the topmost branches of the safest tree, whither she carried him in her bill, are too long to quote in full. They were safe from Indian arrows, as from Tempest, Little Whirlwind and Big Whirlwind; but they were not safe from Storm—who swept him from the arms of his love and carried him into captivity. His sorrow, and the sorrow of Little Fire in her search for him, are deliciously given in the song, until at length, after many adventures, she discovers his dungeon and sets him free in the spring:

Leaving death behind, with love before her,
She saw from afar on the great tree rising
A bright Red Leaf which shone in the sunset ;
Straight was her flight as that of an arrow,
Fast as an arrow when she beheld him.
And the Red Leaf leapt as if smit by an arrow,
When all in a moment her arms were round him
Then, without an instant’s warning,
All his darkness was turned to daylight,
And the Red Wing burst into tears of rapture

The acute observation of Nature and the childish simplicity are qualities one would naturally expect to find in Indian poetry. It is the tenderness and delicacy that are rather sur- prising. The same “ brave” that could walk upon hemlock coals until he dropped without uttering a single cry could also chant these exquisite, compassionate lyrics, so soft with human feeling, round the fire to his squaws and children.

II

The Passamaquoddies, like their other Algic kindred,” says Professor Prince, “ were firm believers in the almost unlimited power of their wizards, belief in the existence of many of whom still remains, sub- ordinate, of course, to the Catholic doctrine, which nearly all the Indians profess—there being, I am informed, only three or four Protestant Passamaquoddy families.”

The most interesting and curious of these sorcery tales relate the strange companionship between the squaws and serpents (generally a wizard disguised), the power of the magicians to sink into the hard ground—a phenomenon characteristically American, according to Prince—and the use of telepathy, or communicating with one another at great distances by thought. The other tales are of the usual animistic kind—giants, spirits in lake and tree and mountain, and demons in snow and wind and tempest.

A characteristic song of a squaw and a snake may be given; it is typical of many others: “ In the North, dwelt by a great fair lake, an Indian and his wife, a very beautiful woman given to strange, wild dreams ; passion was in her blood.” Thus it begins, and goes on to relate how she “saw one day through the ice a pair of wonderful eyes gazing at her with such power that they charmed her. Glittering all over with shining silvery plates, the owner of the eyes slid out upon the shore, announcing himself as Atosis, King of all the Serpents.”

Little she cared for his nature,
She talked with him of love,
She returned his fond embraces ;
Every day she came to meet him,
And often in the night—

until her husband noticed her frequent absences, and asked her where she went. “ To get fresh air,” was the ingenuous, but hardly satisfactory reply. Saying that he was going away for three days’ hunting, he returned unexpectedly on the second, and found the wigwam empty. As he sat, rekindling the fire, she entered. He enquired point-blank where she got the “bright, shining silver scales,” and she replied, “ My silver brooches.”” On the following day he went hunting again, but this time concealed himself and watched the wigwam from the forest. He saw his wife fall into Atosis’ arms :

The husband in awe and anger
Went forth to other people, And left his wife forever.

Her parents, however, came “ to enquire,” and found that she had given birth to offspring—serpents. ‘ “ Do not return,” she said, “ till the ice is here in winter. When you come again you will see me, but never know me.”

Years after, three Indian hunters,
Who had heard this wondrous story,
Sought by the lake for the wigwam.
It was standing still, but empty,
And all the wood about it
Was full of great black serpents
Which from the grass uprising,
Would look them in the face,
Then glide away in silence.

A characteristic, though hardly a pretty song! One that is less sinister tells of the little Indian boy who was kidnapped by a bear, though it contains a modern touch, introduced later, of course, about a rifle. Some Indians, living by a lake, went hunting moose, “the wary moose,” and left the children behind in camp, “ as is the Indian way,” and a boy, who could barely walk, crawled away into the bush and got lost. ‘* When morn- ing dawned he thought he saw his mother drawing near, and, rushing to her side, he held her fast in firm embrace. This was a she bear, shaggy, great and strong as oxen twain. She seized the lad, and bore him off, and fed him in her den,” and the search party failed to find him, so that he “ all winter long the baby lay, warmed by the sleeping bear.”

He ran away, but soon was caught and to his kind restored,
But during many years that lad was wild as any bear!

There is humour in the tale of a wizard and a Christian priest who were taken captive in an attack by Mohawks and forced to walk on hemlock coals as the most torturing death that could be devised. The priest was sent on first, whereupon the wizard, resorting to his magic arts, sprang in ahead of him, laughing, “and danced and danced, until his feet did fry, and sizzle hot like bacon in a pan,” yet without a sign of discomfort or pain. The Mohawks fled in awe. Then the priest said to the wizard :

~ O my son,
Thou shouldst repent and turn thee from thine art
Unto God’s ways, and ever keep the faith.”
Then quoth the Wizard laughing: * Father mine,
Had | repented and eschewed mine art,
Then were we both of us dead men this day |”

Prince also gives one or two short tales that various Indians chanted to him on a moose-hunting expedition. I well remember hunting moose with Prince, and how his interest in the Redskins was so keen that he would turn aside, forgetting the game alto- gether, and hold conversations with Indians encountered on the way:

= When I was fifteen years I saw a man
Who had become a demon of the wood,
A Mikumwess with power to change his size,
And art to sink into the roc! ill
Up to his ankle-joints or knees, as though “twere sand,
I saw myself the tracks where he had sunk
Into a soil all full of recks and roots.”

Another Indian claimed telepathic powers for a member of his family as follows :

“ My father was a wizard and had power
» call unto his part
I’ve often heard hit inging in the night,
All low and weird, and when the morning dawned,
He’d tell me what his partner’s luck had been,
I never knew his magic skill to fail.”

A third refers to the very rare practice of wizards eating one another in order to absorb into themselves double magic power :

“ My brother told me, may
wizards had a quarrel,
One of their number, took his corpse away,
And ate it on the isle of Grand Manan,
Sitting upon a ledge above the sea.”

The main body of legends, from which these songs of love and sorcery have been taken, deal with the doings of Kuloskap, the Master, Lord of Beasts and Men, who was the culture-hero of the entire Migonguid family, a sort of Hiawatha. Kuloskap was a god-man of truly Indian type, at once the creator and the friend of man. The name means “ liar,” yet was meant as a compliment. “He is called the deceiver,” explains Prince, “not because he deceives or injures man, but because he is clever enough to lead his enemies astray—the highest possible virtue to the early American mind.”” These legends were all written out, or spoken by friendly Indians to Leland and Prince, and they tell in quaint, vividly descriptive language the achieve- ments of Kuloskap for the good of these red children whom he dearly loved. He was, of course, a wizard-in-chief, and it is interesting to note the numerous points the system has in common with other cosmologies—the world covered with a flood, Kuloskap’s retiring into the wilderness when he wanted to increase his power by prayer and fasting, and how he finally rose to his giant wigwam in the sky, where his children may always reach him in prayer, and whence he watches over the world. Having created men out of an ash tree, he next created the animals and named them, asking each in turn what it would do if it met an Indian, and, according to their answers, making them smaller, gentler, less dangerous. The rattlesnakes were originally Redskins who mocked at his prophecy of a flood and shook their rattles at him in defiance—turtle-shells with pebbles in them ; he made the loons his messengers, hence their strange human cry before they dive; he tied one wing of Wuchosen, the great Eagle, because its two wings together made the winds dangerous ; and he met all the sorcerers on their own ground and beat them easily at their own diabolical games ; Winpe, a kind of miniature Satan, he killed at a single stroke of his giant bow. The -tracings on birch bark illustrating the first article show some of these heroic deeds. His leaving the world was caused by his disgust at human wickedness :

All were in turn ungrateful,
And, while they feared the Master,
Grew every day more wicked,
Forgetting him in their hearts ;
And roared in the land.

He invited everybody, men and beasts, to a great feast, whereat he himself kept “ grim and solemn silence.” Then they knew :

All knew that the Chief was going,
And knew, too, why he would leave them.

Like Hiawatha, he entered his great stone canoe (it was first an island) and sailed away until he was lost to view. And a wonder came to pass then, for “ all the beasts, who, before, had spoken but one common language, now talked in different tongues ; each with a tongue of his own understood the others no more. So they parted from one another, and fled into the forest ; and, since that day of parting, they have never met in council, and never again will meet till the day when all sins and sorrows will be in full forgiven, forgiven and forgotten, and their Lord, the great Kuloskap, shall return to restore his children to the age of sunshine and plenty, in joy and peace forever.’’ Alone, the great white Snowy Owl, who most had loved him, went far into the North, where it sings to this day, ‘1 a.m. sorry, I am sorry,” and the loons, his messengers, go ‘‘ ever wailing, wailing sadly, because they cannot find him.”

Of all his heroic doings, however, the tenderest, and the most true to life, is the description of the only defeat he ever experienced—by the Baby. Its humour is delicious. The Baby met his direst spells and his most bewitching songs with “Goo! Goo!” “ Back smiled the Baby, but it did not budge.”

Now to this very day, whene’er you sce
A baby well contented, erying * Goo!”
Or crowing in this style, know that it is
Because he then remembers in great joy
How he in strife, all in the olden time,
Did overcome the Master, conqueror
Of all the world, For that, of creatures all,
Or beings which on earth have ever been
Since the beginning, Baby is alone
The never yielding, and invincible.

An Arab Pilgrimage

All day long in the blazing heat the camels have come shuffling and slouching through the sand past Helouan for the March full moon is here and five thousand Bedouins are making their annual pilgrimage to the Tomb in the Desert, where the Sheikh Abou Seria (“Father of Speed”) fulfil the function of an Ar Lourdes From far and near with their families their wives and children, then tents and goats, then plain- tive piping reeds and then incessant tapping of drums the procession has been struggling In since sunrise. Hundreds of donkeys trip le the stately camels, and the separate lines of dust radiate like the spokes of in invisible wheel towards the great encampment just below Helouan, to merge later in the single stream that journeys forty miles south-east to the Tomb itself. To the music of this soft, gay piping the camels come swaying§ in beneath the enormous loads. Tents spring up over acres of yellow sand; camps are pitched, al! separate yet all touching; the donkeys roll in the hot soil; the children laugh and play; the men, grave as the camels, sit round against the walls of bersim and water-jars and baggage that lie in heaps; and the women whisper to one another behind their veils how then little ones shall all be healed presently, and more—that the childless wives among them shall at last become mothers. At the Tomb of Abou Seria these things come to pass at the March full moon. It is a time of great rejoicing.

Shortly after dawn the first stragglers came in—fellaheen on tired donkeys many, too, on foot. They came from villages on the other side of Cairo. For the poor travel slowly, and start first Che wealthy Bedouin sheikhs, swathed in white, with circlets of gold about their turbaned heads, come lat: on their grand white camels, wives and retainers close behin them. And from dawn, all through the burning heat of noo day and afternoon, the horde of fellaheen troop straggling in till the crimson sunset, dying behind the Lybian Desert, fal on an encampment grown wide and deep. The palm grove along the Delta cast long shadows. The lizards sing among the dunes. The women start their wild and curious ululating shrill as an animal cry and hardly human. And suddenly the moon shows her huge yellow disc above the Mokattam Hill and draws a marvellous sweetness out of the Desert, sheeting the spread encampment with a silvery veil.

It is a wonderful sight. The camels seem twice their natural size among the piled-up fodder. Little fires spring uy built over stones. Voices are low; noises die down one by one braving of donkeys, gurgling grunts of camels, bleating of goat and kids soon to be sacrificed. Groups gather closely round he fires, for the night air nips. Coffee is made in tiny chin cups, and the gaunt heads of the camels thrust forward ov: the very shoulders of their owners They chew and chew and chew Those dark bundles in the sand lying apart by themselves, are men already asleep, wrapped from head to feet in sheets of black and blue and white and yellow. No on treads on them. The bare feet silently to and fro, picking thei way so carefully. And everywhere dark faces gleam in the moonlight, eves flash like stars and white teeth shine.

Little visits are paid from group to group. A bearded fellow with face of night enters a circle where all are seated round the fire and coffee-pot. “Are you happy? ” | am happy because of your exist- ence.” “Coffee?” ’ handing him cup. ~ Coffee for ever,” as he sip it slowly. We outsiders watch an stare and question, yet get no near to them. Centuries lie between. The courtesy is perfect. They accept cigarette, lighting it with flint and steel, offering the latter as a present that may not be refused. The young man, playing his reeds so softly to a group of listeners, hands them over to an admirer who has praised them, with “Please accept them from me.” ’ Behind, in the sand, men are praying on their knees toward Mecca. “Sing to us, kindly,” asks an Englishman, who knows Arabic, of another man. The singer is shy, but oniy requires coaxing, and when the Englishman suggests a certain song the other hesitates. “It is not pleasing that I should sing such i. song before gentlemen and ladies.” ‘ They don’t understand . word.” “But I cannot do it. Whether they understand or no, I find it not pleasing.” And, after this lesson in sweet delicacy, between the verses of a song he finally chants, always this question: ‘‘ Does my voice please you, O gentleman? ” Yet these are merely fellaheen, the peasant toilers of the Deita, who accompany the great Bedouin Pilgrimage to the Desert Tomb of Abou Seria, Father of Speed, one of Mahomet’s generals … And after midnight one or two of them rise quietly und resume their journey. “ ‘ Our camels travel better in the night-time.’ Off they go, with their donkeys, goats and children, carrying all they possess in this world with them. The un measured desert swallows them. No sound comes back. ihe vanish in the moonlight as softly as they came. One thinks of that Bedouin who loved an Englishman, and paid him the great honour of taking him home. “I will show you my home,” he said, and they travelled three days and nights across the desert. Beneath a limestone boulder he ponte d to the ground. “Now you are in my home,” he said, proudly, and with the stately dignity of a great Prince of the Desert. And the English man saw a little pile of ashes at his feet. It was summer, tent unnecessary; the wife and flocks were away. This square foot of sand in the enormous wilderness was Home.

In the morning, with the rising sun, the Bedouin arrive. Before Helouan is awake their white head-dress was visible far down the sandy waste that meets the fringe of Delta towards Cairo. But Helouan soon comes down to see. Few of them tarry here; they go straight through; the Bedouin do not like the people, houses, tourists. They resent the cameras. flourish their whips of buffalo-hide and trot past almost fiercely. There is scorn in their eves, as they circle about their wives. High on their splendid camels, they have a regal air, making the great brutes turn and double as easily as horses, and shouting angrily if anyone goes near the water-sellers. This is their last watering- place before the Tomb is reached, and to trifle with a Bedouin’s water is like trifling with his wives. And no wonder they wear this princely mien, for the whole Imperial Desert is their home. Upon the slower camels in their lordly train, sometimes fou abreast, their women, all carefully veiled, sit with the little children. Some are hidden from sight in tent-like canvas gorgeously striped and coloured. It sways to and fro with the enormous knee-stroke of the camels like a boat at sea. Solemnly the Moslem world files past across the sands. And we out- siders get no nearer, ask, stare, and follow as we may. The gulf is not bridged that lies between our minds and theirs. In vain we try. wondering what thev think and feel, and what emotions hide behind those fine bronze faces. Their politeness veils it all, their own deep world; their courtesy screens revela- tion. They move, like the camels, at the pace of a thousand years, unchanging. We watch them across barriers, that is all. Note that oid man praying alone there, behind the munching camel. He has washed his hands and feet : his carpet is spread on the sand, and his shoes are oif. Mind. heart and soul are concentrated. He is oblivious to the worid about him as he bows towards the East and his forehead taps the ground.

As the moon rises higher and night becomes all white the fun begins in earnest—Fantasia, as they call it, borrowing foreign word. A couple Of mounted police from Helouan come down to keep order anc sec that the few Inquisitive tourists from the hotels are not molested. But their services are m once required. Only the little children trot round with their incessant demand for baksheesh Vhe Arabs take no notice of us outsiders, beyond making wav when we approach, offering here and there a word of explanation or inviting us to drink coffee with them when we draw near to their fire-circles. The Fantasia vrows fast and furious, while the crouching camels munch and the cries of goats and donkeys mingle with the women’s weird ululating In one corner a ring is formed and the band begins to play—two pipes and a tomtom. To the endless repetition of a single phrase half melody, half chant enters a Sheikh upon his Arab horse Phe gold and silver tray pings gleam in the moonlight His head-dress shines the horse’s metal necklace chinks and rattles Holding the reins in one hand, the other grips a stall with its point in the sand round this he circles in and out, making a figure of eight, the animal taking its small steps proudly, neck arched, tail flying head held gracefully erect. Suddenly the rider swings a gun round from his back, and fires it olf into the sand with one hand the people watch in silence; the horse prances out; another sheikh enters the ring and goes through a similar performances

In another direction a circle several hundred strong, packed close as herrings, sit round upon the sand, and a story-teller stands in the centre, reciting wonderful adventures with many wild gesticulations. He carries a waving stick, and his falls and rises with a wailing note. All those faces in the moon hight watch and listen with rapt attention. A burst of laughter comes, then exclamations of delight, then long-drawn “ohs!” ’ Tales of Arabian Nights go floating across the desert ait towards another group, where the dancing-girls, who accompany the Pilgrimage from Cairo, are performing to vet another circle of onlookers.

Further off, upon the outskirts of the camp, rows of tall shapely men stand waving their arms, swaying to and tro bending their thin and graceful necks as they recite their songs of a semi-religious, semi-erotic character, towards the East They suddenly kneel and bow, then rise again: the singing voes on and on for hours, and from the distance the chanting of other groups comes in upon the breeze. It is a mournful sound. A few hundred yards outside the encampment these various chanting groups combine in a single tone that holds the monotony of wind blowing among the boulders of the desert.

And the Fantasia continues tar into the night, while the moon climbs higher, the old Nile flows slowly by and the desert listens solemnly all round. Numbers sleep through it; here and there some rise up and disappear across the sand; every where are the outlines of the humped and pointed little tents, the grotesque heads and necks of camels and sheeted human figures passing softly to and fio through the moonlight Al] know that strangers stand and watch them, but, while aware of it, they are utterly indifferent. The rejoicing is amon themselves, no question of display or showing off for others. They simply do what they have done for centuries, and will do for centuries to come A sense of something eternal, ond infinite as the desert itself, rises from the camp. It stirs thi blood. Somewhere in it there is a touch of awe

At sunrise the tents are struck, and the entire mass moves on across the sand in single file, a procession stretching fot miles. At the Tomb itself, two days later, to the light of a thousand camp fires, the Fantasia is renewed in full earnest The animals are sacrificed. There is endless praying, dancing, singing, acting and the rest. Then all return the wav they went. The Bedouin scatter again to their various resting- places in the desert-home. Phe camels come slouching and shuffling through the sands past Helouan.

What remains with me, however, 1s not so much the memory of their Fantasia and wild rejoicing, as the moonlit: picture oi the little families who left the camp to continue their journey beneath the stars. For the sight stirred old deep yearnings that every Nature-lover knows too well. So quietly they stole away into the immeasurable desert! All their possessions in this world they carried easily with them, and in their hearts this ancient Faith the ages cannot change. The camels padded off, veiled women in the swaying tents upon their backs. The silhouettes were strange and mysterious against the brilliant stars Like dreams ol a forgotten world they melted into the distance swift!y. Moonlight, sand and desert took them home.

AN EGYPTIAN HORNET

The word has an angry, malignant sound that brings the idea of attack vividly into the mind. There is a vicious sting about it somewhere—even a foreigner, ignorant of the meaning, must feel it. A hornet is wicked; it darts and stabs; it pierces, aiming without provocation for the face and eyes. The name suggests a metallic droning of evil wings, fierce flight, and poisonous assault. Though black and yellow, it sounds scarlet. There is blood in it. A striped tiger of the air in concentrated form! There is no escape—if it attacks.

In Egypt an ordinary bee is the size of an English hornet, but the Egyptian hornet is enormous. It is truly monstrous—an ominous, dying terror. It shares that universal quality of the land of the Sphinx and Pyramids—great size. It is a formidable insect, worse than scorpion or tarantula. The Rev. James Milligan, meeting one for the first time, realised the meaning of another word as well, a word he used prolifically in his eloquent sermons—devil.

One morning in April, when the heat began to bring the insects out, he rose as usual betimes and went across the wide stone corridor to his bath. The desert already glared in through the open windows. The heat would be afflicting later in the day, but at this early hour the cool north wind blew pleasantly down the hotel passages. It was Sunday, and at half-past eight o’clock he would appear to conduct the morning service for the English visitors. The floor of the passage-way was cold beneath his feet in their thin native slippers of bright yellow. He was neither young nor old; his salary was comfortable; he had a competency of his own, without wife or children to absorb it; the dry climate had been recommended to him; and—the big hotel took him in for next to nothing. And he was thoroughly pleased with himself, for he was a sleek, vain, pompous, well-advertised personality, but mean as a rat. No worries of any kind were on his mind as, carrying sponge and towel, scented soap and a bottle of Scrubb’s ammonia, he travelled amiably across the deserted, shining corridor to the bathroom. And nothing went wrong with the Rev. James Milligan until he opened the door, and his eye fell upon a dark, suspicious-looking object clinging to the window-pane in front of him.

And even then, at first, he felt no anxiety or alarm, but merely a natural curiosity to know exactly what it was—this little clot of an odd-shaped, elongated thing that stuck there on the wooden framework six feet before his aquiline nose. He went straight up to it to see—then stopped dead. His heart gave a distinct, unclerical leap. His lips formed themselves into unregenerate shape. He gasped: “Good God! What is it?” For something unholy, something wicked as a secret sin, stuck there before his eyes in the patch of blazing sunshine. He caught his breath.

For a moment he was unable to move, as though the sight half fascinated him. Then, cautiously and very slowly—stealthily, in fact—he withdrew towards the door he had just entered. Fearful of making the smallest sound, he retraced his steps on tiptoe. His yellow slippers shuffled. His dry sponge fell, and bounded till it settled, rolling close beneath the horribly attractive object facing him. From the safety of the open door, with ample space for retreat behind him, he paused and stared. His entire being focused itself in his eyes. It was a hornet that he saw. It hung there, motionless and threatening, between him and the bathroom door. And at first he merely exclaimed—below his breath—“Good God! It’s an Egyptian hornet!”

Being a man with a reputation for decided action, however, he soon recovered himself. He was well schooled in self-control. When people left his church at the beginning of the sermon, no muscle of his face betrayed the wounded vanity and annoyance that burned deep in his heart. But a hornet sitting directly in his path was a very different matter. He realised in a flash that he was poorly clothed—in a word, that he was practically half naked.

From a distance he examined this intrusion of the devil. It was calm and very still. It was wonderfully made, both before and behind. Its wings were folded upon its terrible body. Long, sinuous things, pointed like temptation, barbed as well, stuck out of it. There was poison, and yet grace, in its exquisite presentment. Its shiny black was beautiful, and the yellow stripes upon its sleek, curved abdomen were like the gleaming ornaments upon some feminine body of the seductive world he preached against. Almost, he saw an abandoned dancer on the stage. And then, swiftly in his impressionable soul, the simile changed, and he saw instead more blunt and aggressive forms of destruction. The well-filled body, tapering to a horrid point, reminded him of those perfect engines of death that reduce hundreds to annihilation unawares—torpedoes, shells, projectiles, crammed with secret, desolating powers. Its wings, its awful, quiet head, its delicate, slim waist, its stripes of brilliant saffron—all these seemed the concentrated prototype of abominations made cleverly by the brain of man, and beautifully painted to disguise their invisible freight of cruel death.

“Bah!” he exclaimed, ashamed of his prolific imagination. “It’s only a hornet after all—an insect!” And he contrived a hurried, careful plan. He aimed a towel at it, rolled up into a ball—but did not throw it. He might miss. He remembered that his ankles were unprotected. Instead, he paused again, examining the black and yellow object in safe retirement near the door, as one day he hoped to watch the world in leisurely retirement in the country. It did not move. It was fixed and terrible. It made no sound. Its wings were folded. Not even the black antennae, blunt at the tips like clubs, showed the least stir or tremble. It breathed, however. He watched the rise and fall of the evil body; it breathed air in and out as he himself did. The creature, he realised, had lungs and heart and organs. It had a brain! Its mind was active all this time. It knew it was being watched. It merely waited. Any second, with a whiz of fury, and with perfect accuracy of aim, it might dart at him and strike. If he threw the towel and missed—it certainly would.

There were other occupants of the corridor, however, and a sound of steps approaching gave him the decision to act. He would lose his bath if he hesitated much longer. He felt ashamed of his timidity, though “pusillanimity” was the word thought selected owing to the pulpit vocabulary it was his habit to prefer. He went with extreme caution towards the bathroom door, passing the point of danger so close that his skin turned hot and cold. With one foot gingerly extended, he recovered his sponge. The hornet did not move a muscle. But—it had seen him pass. It merely waited. All dangerous insects had that trick. It knew quite well he was inside; it knew quite well he must come out a few minutes later; it also knew quite well that he was—naked.

Once inside the little room, he closed the door with exceeding gentleness, lest the vibration might stir the fearful insect to attack. The bath was already filled, and he plunged to his neck with a feeling of comparative security. A window into the outside passage he also closed, so that nothing could possibly come in. And steam soon charged the air and left its blurred deposit on the glass. For ten minutes he could enjoy himself and pretend that he was safe. For ten minutes he did so. He behaved carelessly, as though nothing mattered, and as though all the courage in the world were his. He splashed and soaped and sponged, making a lot of reckless noise. He got out and dried himself. Slowly the steam subsided, the air grew clearer, he put on dressing-gown and slippers. It was time to go out.

Unable to devise any further reason for delay, he opened the door softly half an inch—peeped out—and instantly closed it again with a resounding bang. He had heard a drone of wings. The insect had left its perch and now buzzed upon the floor directly in his path. The air seemed full of stings; he felt stabs all over him; his unprotected portions winced with the expectancy of pain. The beast knew he was coming out, and was waiting for him. In that brief instant he had felt its sting all over him, on his unprotected ankles, on his back, his neck, his cheeks, in his eyes, and on the bald clearing that adorned his Anglican head. Through the closed door he heard the ominous, dull murmur of his striped adversary as it beat its angry wings. Its oiled and wicked sting shot in and out with fury. Its deft legs worked. He saw its tiny waist already writhing with the lust of battle. Ugh! That tiny waist! A moment’s steady nerve and he could have severed that cunning body from the directing brain with one swift, well-directed thrust. But his nerve had utterly deserted him.

Human motives, even in the professedly holy, are an involved affair at any time. Just now, in the Rev. James Milligan, they were quite inextricably mixed. He claims this explanation, at any rate, in excuse of his abominable subsequent behaviour. For, exactly at this moment, when he had decided to admit cowardice by ringing for the Arab servant, a step was audible in the corridor outside, and courage came with it into his disreputable heart. It was the step of the man he cordially “disapproved of,” using the pulpit version of “hated and despised.” He had overstayed his time, and the bath was in demand by Mr. Mullins. Mr. Mullins invariably followed him at seven-thirty; it was now a quarter to eight. And Mr. Mullins was a wretched drinking man—“a sot.”

In a flash the plan was conceived and put into execution. The temptation, of course, was of the devil. Mr. Milligan hid the motive from himself, pretending he hardly recognised it. The plan was what men call a dirty trick; it was also irresistibly seductive. He opened the door, stepped boldly, nose in the air, right over the hideous insect on the floor, and fairly pranced into the outer passage. The brief transit brought a hundred horrible sensations—that the hornet would rise and sting his leg, that it would cling to his dressing-gown and stab his spine, that he would step upon it and die, like Achilles, of a heel exposed. But with these, and conquering them, was one other stronger emotion that robbed the lesser terrors of their potency—that Mr. Mullins would run precisely the same risks five seconds later, unprepared. He heard the gloating insect buzz and scratch the oil-cloth. But it was behind him. He was safe!

“Good morning to you, Mr. Mullins,” he observed with a gracious smile. “I trust I have not kept you waiting.”

“Mornin’!” grunted Mullins sourly in reply, as he passed him with a distinctly hostile and contemptuous air. For Mullins, though depraved, perhaps, was an honest man, abhorring parsons and making no secret of his opinions—whence the bitter feeling.

All men, except those very big ones who are supermen, have something astonishingly despicable in them. The despicable thing in Milligan came uppermost now. He fairly chuckled. He met the snub with a calm, forgiving smile, and continued his shambling gait with what dignity he could towards his bedroom opposite. Then he turned his head to see. His enemy would meet an infuriated hornet—an Egyptian hornet!—and might not notice it. He might step on it. He might not. But he was bound to disturb it, and rouse it to attack. The chances were enormously on the clerical side. And its sting meant death.

“May God forgive me!” ran subconsciously through his mind. And side by side with the repentant prayer ran also a recognition of the tempter’s eternal skill: “I hope the devil it will sting him!”

It happened very quickly. The Rev. James Milligan lingered a moment by his door to watch. He saw Mullins, the disgusting Mullins, step blithely into the bathroom passage; he saw him pause, shrink back, and raise his arm to protect his face. He heard him swear out aloud: “What’s the d——d thing doing here? Have I really got ’em again——?” And then he heard him laugh—a hearty, guffawing laugh of genuine relief—— “It’s real!”

The moment of revulsion was overwhelming. It filled the churchly heart with anguish and bitter disappointment. For a space he hated the whole race of men.

For the instant Mr. Mullins realised that the insect was not a fiery illusion of his disordered nerves, he went forward without the smallest hesitation. With his towel he knocked down the flying terror. Then he stooped. He gathered up the venomous thing his well-aimed blow had stricken so easily to the floor. He advanced with it, held at arm’s length, to the window. He tossed it out carelessly. The Egyptian hornet flew away uninjured, and Mr. Mullins—the Mr. Mullins who drank, gave nothing to the church, attended no services, hated parsons, and proclaimed the fact with enthusiasm—this same detestable Mr. Mullins went to his unearned bath without a scratch. But first he saw his enemy standing in the doorway across the passage, watching him—and understood. That was the awful part of it. Mullins would make a story of it, and the story would go the round of the hotel.

The Rev. James Milligan, however, proved that his reputation for self-control was not undeserved. He conducted morning service half an hour later with an expression of peace upon his handsome face. He conquered all outward sign of inward spiritual vexation; the wicked, he consoled himself, ever flourish like green bay trees. It was notorious that the righteous never have any luck at all! That was bad enough. But what was worse—and the Rev. James Milligan remembered for very long—was the superior ease with which Mullins had relegated both himself and hornet to the same level of comparative insignificance. Mullins ignored them both—which proved that he felt himself superior. Infinitely worse than the sting of any hornet in the world: he really was superior.

Animal-Life 1n the Egyptian Desert

It is, of course, a matter for wonder that anv life can exist in the desert at all [he absence of water and vegetation, and the scarcity ot even in- sects, seem to make sit mm possible for any living thing that subsists by eating and drinking to survive The arid, barren wastes of sand and stone and mud could not support a mouse, much less a larger animal. There is not even a shred ot moss or lichen anywhere and at first, when one sees the small isolated plants and thorn, shrubs the wee coloured flowers, and the occasional little sprouts ol spear grass known to the Bedouin as Ithmum’ ” ’ and “ ‘Dahram,’ one seeks in vain for an explanation of their growth Phat explanation is not easily found. There is heavy dew at night, and no doubt they make the most of the very rare bursts of rain, which, when they come make waterfalls of every ridge and roll the boulders noisily down the narrow gully beds. But the water sinks into the dry soil as into a thirsty sponge; none of it remains on the surface. The denudation in these torrential downfalls of the winter months is very great, but the benefit. to the scanty plant-life must be small enough. Yet along the bottom of every valley may be seen, not infrequently, the little thorny shrubs the camels eat; and perhaps, like their devourers, they have a special means of storing moisture for future use.

But, when it comes to animal-life, the wonder is far greater. Presumably the gazelles, the foxes, the jackals, hares, hyenas and the little jerbils, whose footsteps in the sand (sometimes, too, whose skeletons) one finds, know, even better than the Bedouins, the exact spots where the pools of water hide at such great distances apart. At any rate, the travellers’ notes of the animal and bird life they have encountered in these parched and desolate solitudes are full of interest and—surprise. At a stone’s throw from Helouan one thinks, of course, life stops short. Instead, it is just beginning. The silent desert is full of life. The ants, to start with, are fairly plentiful. Not in communities, be it understood, for an ant-heap is never seen; but solitary and very busy individuals, with re- curved abdomens, hurrying along as though living were the simplest matter in the world. The very minute Egyptian ant, too, is common everywhere. Scorpions beneath turned stones are frequent enough, and lizards dart about in the fierce sunshine as happily as if the plenty of Italy and France lay easily within their reach. Perhaps they never drink! They are plentiful enough, and increase as you go towards Suez and the Red Sea. Geckos and agamas, the latter a peculiar flat-bodied, large-headed, uncouth little creature, are among the ones most _tre- quently seen; but the most striking are the spiny-tailed varieties, which love the soft leaves of the “seyal” ” plant whenever they can find ie There is another kind that the weaker - minded among the Arabs dread, because they say it throws stones at them with its tail. Its ener- getic, quick movements ap- parently flick the smaller stones to a considerable distance.

There are snakes, too, though rarely seen, and to be found mostly in the hills further east towards the Ked Sea. The horned viper (kakar) is greatly dreaded by the Arabs; but no one merely walk- ing in the desert hereabouts ap- pears to have scen one. A doctor, however, interested in the desert life tells me he caught a specimen with a bird in its mouth it had just killed, and another having the re- mains of a wagtail in its stomach. The jackals come, of course, as their habit is, very close to human habitations, and may often be heard crying after nightfall or in the early morning on the outskirts of Helouan. The hyrax is another desert animal, too shy “to be often seen. It has a variable distribution, being dependent to a large extent upon the amount of rainfall, so that a colony may completely disappear from a district after a dry season. It has a sharply-pointed muzzle and small rounded ears, and the body is covered with a thick coat of nearly uniformly-coloured hair, deep brown as a rule. It lives in rocky or stony places, in communities, like rabbits, haunting holes beneath the rocks and is found, too, frequently in certain districts in the rocky watercourses. Its ieet are of remarkable structure, being very flat and pad-like, so that it can run with ease on the smooth rocky slopes. The toes are leathery in appearance, there being four on the front and three on the hind feet. The presence of two pairs of well-marked front teeth, one in the upper and the other in the lower jaw, also gives a characteristic appearance which enables the skull of a hyrax to be readily recognised. Mr. Hume of the Cairo Survey Department mentions these particulars. As a rule, these animals seem to keep with- in approachable distance of the eastern banks of the Nile. The same writer—referring for a moment to the insect-life mentions the rarity of butter- flies, yet, oddly enough, the abundance of moths; andspeaks of the beautiful blue dragon- flies (one meets them flitting down the streets of Helouan), the locusts, which fall an easy prey to the ubiquitous lizards, the wasps and hornets and crickets, too, that one meets in the Wadis at almost any distance from the houses. There was a yviant locust here last night in the hotel dining- room, which flew like a_ bat about the walls and dashed itself repeatedly against the ceiling, to the terror of the ladies, until, finally, a waiter ‘nabbed’ it with a napkin and a glass, to everybody’s great relief. The ‘ praying insects’’ “{Mantidz) are also common enough, and fully bear out their reputation of being the most predacious and bloodthirsty of creatures, ‘to which character,’ says Hume, “must be added also a considerable amount of curi- osity, as they used to come on to the table and watch the writer’s every movement, turning their peculiarly-shaped heads on one side while doing so. On another occasion one caught a moth, and, perched on the tent-rope, held it in the fore legs and calmly tote it to bits, at the same time eating the fragments with much satis- faction.’” They are from two to three centimétres long, and of a bright green colour ‘Spiders are comparatively rare,’ ” he adds, ‘ but a large grey form and quite harmless variety accompanied the writer for a good part of the journey, travelling with the tent, and appear- ing every evening. Very abundant, too, are the false spiders (Solifugz), which come into the tent at night, and one of which, over ten centimétres in length, has the reputation among the Arabs of being a deadly enemy to the scorpion.’ It is this variety, probably, that is locally spoken of round Helouan as a tarantula.

The bird-life is, perhaps, more interesting than any other form of desert life. One notices the flocks of kites, large grey birds, the moment one gets to Cairo. They circle, sometimes at an enormous height, sometimes close above the roofs and streets, and their peculiar sharp, petulant cry is distinctly one of the Cairo sounds—when the traffic allows it to become audible. Round Helouan they are very plentiful indeed, and in an hour’s walk through the desert hundreds may be observed in spots where they have scented food, most likely in the form of a dead baby camel. Vultures, too, are common, especially the carrion vulture, the well-known ‘rakham’ ” of the Arabs. They will follow human beings for very long distances, with intentions that may easily be imagined. One is almost startled to hear larks and see the darting swallows, too; the latter, preparing for migration to Europe, being very numerous towards the end of March. The desert-lark (Alamon desertorum) is a joy to see and hear; it has grey plumage, a long slender beak and a very rapid run ; and another species, the finch lark, with short, thick beak, is also readily recognised by the peculiar and sudden manner in which it drops to the ground. Wagtails, too, flit everywhere, even in the most desolate and arid gorges ; and there is a kind of chat, very small, and equally ubiquitous, noticeable by the vivid contrast of black and white in its plumage These birds add greatly to the charm of the desert. One watches them with a sort of admiration—plucky bits of life in the heart of such appalling loneliness. Their shrill twittering is the only sound one hears for hundreds and hundreds of miles. Hume, in his survey of desert birds, also makes mention of owls the eagle owl and the church owl—and says that nightjars have been met with, too, though never seen. He heard them crving at night. Barron, another writer who accompanied the survey expeditions, further de- scribes great flocks of heron- like birds he saw going north- east, hundreds at a time. But these birds, called by the Arabs “ ‘ kark,’’ were apparently not true desert birds. They resem- ble the stork, and were exceed- ingly shy, too shy to permit approach. They seemed to come from the fields along the river, and merely settled in the desert; being probably he says, the white-plumaged herons or egrets which are found so abundantly in the meadows bordering the Nile. Thev were migrating.

Among the rodents found in this portion of the desert, but apparently well distributed through the other deserts, too, is the small, sandy grey, three toed jerboa. It is a little desert kangaroo rat with a long tail and its holes are everywhere abundant. Closely allied te the jerbil, it is, nevertheless far less frequently seen. At nightfall, apparently, the jerboa finds its courage, and takes it boldly in its three-toed hands. Curiosity impels it to investi gate man. “One evening,” says Hume, ‘when the writer was sitting on a hillock, a jerboa came up, and leapt round in a series of wide circles, but on the = slightest movement at once made off. On several occasions they entered the tents at night = and jumped about over the sleepe1 7 but were far too quick in their movements to be caught. One made persistent endeavours to dig into the tent under the flaps, desisting when the latter were sharply tapped, only to begin again a few seconds later. One very cold and windy day two of the Arabs brought in a small specimen. On _ being taken out and put under one of the bsilla bushes, it had evidently formed the impression from the warmth of the tent and its good reception that it had fallen among friends, for it jumped back to the tent, and, arriving there, curled itself under the blankets.’

A doctor here, who has been interesting himself in various bacteriological experiments, and in a generai study of the desert animal-life, tells me that the jerbil, the desert mouse, never drinks at all. It simply despises water. One that he kept in captivity for over a year lived the whole time without a single drop of water. He kept it in a large glass jar, feeding it with grain dry grain that contained a very small percentage of moisture He placed water for it, but the jerbil never looked at it. The jerboa, he tells me, has the same predilection for its nourishment ‘dry.’’ A friend of his had recently been out to shoot the addax, a rare type of antelope that haunts extremely desolate parts of Northern Africa and Arabia, and, of course, is not to be found in the desert immediately round Helouan. His friend, in fact, went forty days on a camel to come up with it. The addax equally despises water; its meat is very succulent eating, and there is nothing abnormal in the condition of its blood. But it never drinks. It stands over three feet high, is yellowish white in colour, with a brown mane and a fringe of the same hair on the throat. Beth sexes carry horns, which are ringed and form an open spiral. The habits of this desert antelope resemble those of the gemsbok, and it is hunted by the Arabs for its flesh, and also to test the speed of their horses.

Arolla and Its Climbs

When writing a description of a mountaineering centre, one is invariably embarrassed by the unlikelihood of its suiting every reader. Some may be experienced climbers, preferring only the hardest expeditions, while others may be new to the sport, and unfit for anything but easy scrambling. It is for mountain lovers, therefore, of average climbing capacity that this article is intended, in the hope that they may realise that, in spite of many changes, Switzerland still possesses a few charming, though remote, centres, where the Alps can be contemplated amid simple surroundings, and may also be climbed without the aid of electric railways. Even in climbing circles there are a great many individuals whose horizon is bounded by Zermatt, Chamonix and Grindelwald, and who, when the name of Arolla is suggested, have a vague idea that it is situated in the St. Gothard Valley or the Upper Engadine. Once, however, one has removed from their minds all ideas of Airolo and Arosa, one may go on to point out its correct position, namely, at the head of the Val d’Herens, which branches off from the Rhone Valley at Sion. Here is a bit of Switzerland as the early pioneers knew it; just a simple upland village, with nothing to recommend it but its own natural attractions, unsupplemented by tennis tournaments or fashionable “five o’clocks.” In fact, Arolla has nothing to offer the idler, no funicular ascents, not even a grotte aux fées. And yet, though primarily a hunting-ground for the mountaineer, it provides ample scope for less ambitious projects, no one presumably venturing so far afield without some form of pedestrian exercise in view, And here lies one of the chief attractions of the place, in that it can offer ascents of every description and difficulty; it is an admirable school to choose for one’s early climbing education, while many of its peaks will call for all the resources of the most finished mountaineer. It would be, of course, impossible in so small a space to give anything like a detailed account of the expeditions to be made; but even the scantiest description of them may be of some assistance to any who feel inclined to climb a little off the beaten track. So, always bearing in mind that this article is intended for the average climber, I will try to give some idea of the most interesting ascents to be made.

For an introductory acquaintance with the district there is nothing to beat the Petite Dent de Veisivi, whose jagged ridge is so plainly seen to the northeast of the village; it is a perfectly straightforward piece of rock climbing of some three hours, and, though there are passages where the hands play as large a part as the feet, there is nothing which should worry an active and enthusiastic amateur. Among other second-class peaks there are the Aiguille de la Za, of which the pièce de résistance is a rather smooth slab; the Pigne d’Arolla, for those who do not mind a day’s trudge in the snow; and, lastly, the Mont Collon, an admirable combination of snow and rock work, and perhaps the most imposing-looking mountain in the neighbourhood. Of the more difficult climbs, the ascent of the Aiguille de la Za by the west face and the traverse of the Aiguilles Rouges form undoubtedly the finest expeditions of the district; they are, naturally, only for mountaineers of some experience, and are well worth a visit. The former is simply a succession of rock walls, broken up at intervals by narrow ledges from which the leading climber can attend to the safety of those below. One or two passages call for a considerable amount of gymnastics, particularly the last parapet, which is not at all unlike a lift shaft, with a glimpse of the Arolla hotels directly below. More serious still is the traverse of the Aiguilles Rouges, for not only is it a longer and more exhausting climb, some three hours being required to reach the base, but the rock work in many places is of a more sensational and tiring nature, On the northern and central peaks the climbing is fairly straightforward; but it is on the southern point that the exciting part of the day begins. Seen from below it resembles a huge hand of countless fingers; and, as a matter of fact, about nine of these fingers, or gendarmes, are crossed en route. Most of them involve exercise of the gymnastic order, and, if covered with a little ice, can cause unlimited trouble. But, on the whole, the rock is sound, and there are few climbs round Arolla which call for such a sustained effort of mind and muscle, and which afford the well trained cragsman so magnificent a reward.

Such in brief are the principal attractions of the district; but perhaps no account of Arolla would be complete without some mention of the Dent Blanche, that formidable summit which, though not in the immediate neighbourhood, is so easily approached from the convenient Bertol hut. As with all the great giants of the Alps, the ease or difficulty of its conquest is entirely dependent on weather conditions; in a hot summer its southern ridge may offer very little difficulty, while after a fresh fall of snow the ascent might be scarcely justifiable. In August of this year the writer, with a friend and two guides, was fortunate enough to make the descent by the West Ridge, perhaps the most impressive side of the mountain. Seen from above, the view of those shattered precipices is one to be remembered; tower upon tower succeed one another in an endless succession of jagged teeth, until the eye can scan the wonderful ridge no longer, but is caught by the glint of the Ferpécle icefall away below, like the flash of clear water at the bottom of a well. But the Dent Blanche is not a peak to be trifled with, and should not be attempted in doubtful weather, and therefore if time at Arolla is limited, it is wiser to confine one’s attention to the summits near at hand and where weather conditions are of less importance. Every day spent in those stoney highlands will be one to look back to, and when the climbing season comes round and the mountaineer longs once more for the ring of the axe or the tinkle of the cowbells on the upland pasture. Let him remember Arolla and spend such a summer as only his fondest dreams could picture.

At School in the Black Forest

I

How vivid still in the memory are the sensations stirred in me years ago by the news that I was to go to a school—in the Black Forest; for to the youthful imagina tion this was a mysterious region inhabited by charcoal-burners, fairies, robbers, and wild boars; a land of enchantment and story, truly, and not in the least a proper sort of place for a school where one would merely “learn German.”

For a long time it was very difficult to reconcile the two ideas, and quite impossible to solve the puzzle whether the robbers would molest the schoolboys out after dark for their pocket-money, or whether the charcoal-burners and pixies would send their offspring side by side with the ordinary pupils to learn the portentous difference between sein and haben. The chief difficulty seemed to be that no real forest could contain a school and be enchanted at the same time; and it was only after two years’ actual sojourn in just such a place that I learned in how true a sense this could really be the case.

And now, as if to prove this, it all comes back to one across the years as part and parcel of some childhood dream—the Journey over the Channel and through France to Strassbourg; the spring day in the quaint old town, picturesque and gabled; the odd-looking soldiers (how could any soldiers fight in such trousers! ); the tales I heard of the war; the astonishing facility with which everybody, even the children, spoke the language; and above all the awe inspiring Cathedral and the Twelve Apostles who came out above the old clock, just before the train started, to sound the hour of my ap proaching doom. And, as if to lend still further the colour of a dream, it seemed that nobody had ever heard of the place whither I was bound. Even the innkeeper knew it not—and in those days I thought innkeepers knew every single thing in the world—so that by the time I left Strasbourg it seemed more and more doubtful whether the place xisted on the map or only in the imaginatic of the writers who had made the tales.

Even now I can see the train laboriously climbing up the steep winding railwa, that crosses the Schwarzwald Range, doubling upon itself in a most puzzling fashion. The mountains were covered everywhere with sombre pine-woods, but opened up when least expected into sunny valleys that fairly took my breath away as I leaned out of the carriage window and wished the engine would not go so fast and make so much black smoke. Most plainly they said, “We are the haunted valleys and enchanted woods you have read about. There lies the pool where the pixie steals forth in the sil very moonlight, and yonder cleft in the mountains is the hole by which the gnomes pass up and down from the centre of the earth.”

And when the train, panting from its long climb, stopped at Peterzell station, three thousand feet above the sea, crowning the descent where the Danube rises a few miles beyond, I can still smell the odour of timber and sawn wood in the sweet air of the spring dusk as I got out with my corded tin box and drove in a springless hay-cart four miles into the interior of the forest. The trees pressed up closely, making a paling with a level top on both sides of the road, and only a narrow strip of starry sky was visible over our heads. We rattled on noisily, past occasional farmhouses with immense brown roofs, across humming little streams, and by glades that ran down mossy ways into depths no eye could pierce. The robbers and wild boars, to say nothing of the kobbolds, were no doubt watching us from the darkness under the branches; and, indeed, it was far more like reading one of the old tales again, and visualising it, than the very prosaic business of “going to school.”

From time to time the driver spoke to me in his uncouth dialect, and the small amount of nursery-governess German then at my disposal was so dismayed at this display of the real article, very much “made in Germany,” that my mind made itself up there and then that it could never in this world master any proper or useful quantity of such an appalling tongue. These impres sions are as vivid as though they were of yesterday. I can still hear his words, though to this day I cannot understand them, as he pointed with his whip across the first large clearing we had come to, and showed me a little cluster of lights twinkling in the distance against a wall of purple forest—the lights of the village of Königsfeld, and of the school where I was to dwell for two years with eighty boys of various European nationalities and master the language as best might be.

The driver cracked his whip and rattled needlessly fast down the hard white road; and when he drew up with a flourish in front of a gloomy building that towered up into the night, I felt exactly as if I were just about to serve a sentence in prison. The ominous sound of the bell he pulled so vigorously added to the impression, and the glimpse I caught through the glass door of severe walls, and a long stone corridor beyond poorly lit by a single oil lamp, com pleted it and sent my heart at once into my boots. The driver was my only friend in the world just then, and even he was in a hurry to be off. Then steps came slowly down the dim flagged hall-way. I saw a figure in black, with spectacled eyes and a truly German visage, and heard some words in my native tongue.

But, when I turned to face this Ogre of the Enchanted Castle, and understood the sympathy of the words he addressed to me in the kindest possible tones, and using my Christian name, my fears were instantly dis pelled; and I caught at once from this welcoming Herr Direktor the keynote of an establishment where a somewhat grim dis cipline went hand in hand with a genuine personal solicitude for the highest welfare of each and every pupil within its walls.

“Safe and sound after your long journey,” he said in excellent English, “and I hope you left your parents quite well at home. I have just received a letter from your honoured Herr Father. Come with me, and I will read to you what he says before seeing to your supper and bed, for I know you must be hungry as well as tired.”

To an English boy, with only the ideal of an English private school in his mind, the life of course seemed very strange in this Knaben-Anstalt of the Moravian Brother hood. To begin with, he found himself expected to live in harmony with eighty boys of many nationalities, between whom and himself there was apparently but one common object-the mutilation of the Ger man language.

The loneliness of the school, too, touched him nearly, for its setting was unique: he was cut off from the world. Planted down, with its little village, in the centre of this ancient forest, the square “clearing” was not unlike the opening that the Canadian settler first makes for himself in the tangled wilderness of the North American back woods. The forest closed in upon it from all sides, pierced only by roads that lead to picturesque villages, equally out of the world; or by glades that meandered among the trees till they stopped at a secluded farmhouse or saw-mill droning away its life on some little turbulent mountain stream.

Everywhere one came across evidences that the fairy life of the deep woods mingled more or less freely with the peasant life of the village—pools were haunted; certain pathways unsafe after dark; open knolls were used by the witches for their revels; and in some localities enchanted streams rose up, flitting, like the old man in Fouqué’s wondrous tale, through the lonely reaches, and splashing the faces of any who dared to follow and explore too boldly. All these things, however, were not ascertainable at first hand, because no boy was allowed to go out unattended. When he went abroad it was always in company with fifteen or twenty other boys, and in charge of at least one “Brother.” “Out of bounds” did not exist. The railing round the school building was “bounds,” and in the school uniform no boy could possibly have made his way far beyond it without having been detected and “returned empty.”

Yet side by side with all this old-world, dream-world charm, there existed the vigor ous modern, practical life of the finest missionary spirit the world perhaps has known. There was no display, no blowing of trumpets. There were no visible rewards to compensate the self-denial of these masters, well styled Brothers, who, with small pay and less comfort, devoted the best years of their lives to the bringing up of young lads under conditions that to many of them must have amounted to exile; and who often, later, went forth in the spirit of their great founder, Count Zinzendorf, to carry the tidings of their simple faith to those who dwell in the remote and outcast regions of the world.

I can remember one of them, even while I was there, coming to say goodbye to us all in the quietest possible manner, as though he were going away at most for a week’s holiday, when in reality he was going off to spend the remainder of his life among the Esquimaux of Labrador, and might well never return to the comforts of civilised living again.

Little enough of this, no doubt, appealed to the boys in the school at the time though it must touch the imagination of many, I think, when they come to look back upon it in later years-yet there reached us even then some inkling of the fact that we were in a school of a very unusual character, where-though it was in no sense a school of religion—the little group of devoted “brother-masters” cared almost more for the inner life and development of the pupil than for his mastery of dates in German history or the correct use of the mysterious genders. The teaching, be it said at once, lest I give a wrong impression, was thorough, painstaking, and of the best. I only wish to emphasise the fact that there was an unusually lofty standard of conduct always before the boys, and one felt that to sin against this was a greater fault than to murder the language, and that also it grieved the Brothers more.

II

Of the eighty boys in the school about a score were English, and the rest French, Swiss, Italian, Germans, and a few Russians. On arrival, a new boy was attached to a cicerone of his own persuasion, with whom he was permitted to talk his own language, and upon whose tender mercies he relied for all guidance as to the customs of the school and what was expected of him. This lasted for three days, after which nothing but German was allowed to pass his lips under severe penalty; and it is surprising how much of a foreign tongue one can pick up in a day or two when every single thought has to somehow or other find intelligent expres sion therein, and especially when the lightest penalty for using another language is halbes Frühstück—half-rations at breakfast. By the end of the three days most boys were able to take their place in the classes and do at least part of the work, though of course, so far as accurate results were con cerned, they received very lenient treatment for a long time to come.

For the purposes of both study and play, the boys were divided into four rooms erste Stube, zweite Stube, etc., where they lived together during the day under the constant eye of at least one Brother; and the medley of strange German slang that was sometimes heard in these rooms reminds me forcibly of that delightful youth in “Punch” not long ago who, when he wanted to tell a Frenchman to “shut up,” attacked him vigorously with “Fermez! Fermez!” and added 66 Snay pas un morceau de bong,” when he wished him to understand that resistance was 46 not a bit of good. ” For each boy did his level best to force the language into the slang of his own country, till the result must have tickled the patient ears of more than one of those kind-hearted Brothers sitting behind the cloud of cigar smoke at the high desk in the corner. But the Sunday afternoons, when, for a brief hour, mother-tongues were permitted, must have een still funnier in results, for then on all sides were to be heard sentences in English, French, Italian, with German words thrust anyhow-usually most uncomfortably—into their midst. ” Hurry up and hole mir die cricket-bat. Schnell, or, ” I’ll lick you,” is a sentence that rings in my ears to this day, and many another equally quaint with it.

The day began at half-past five in the morning, when a wicked bell rang in the great Schlafzimmer where we all slept—a very large room on the top floor, with lofty ceiling and excellent ventilation—and, seizing his dressing-gown, each boy raced at full speed downstairs after the Bruder and into the Waschkammer, where the boys of his particular Stube washed and dressed. If he did not reach the room before the door was closed, his reward was probably half-breakfast; and he had to be quick about it too, for most of the Brothers dashed down those long flights of stairs as if their very life de pended upon it, instead of only a boy’s half. breakfast. The clothes were all found hang ing up on the pegs, where they had been left the night before, and below them on the floor were the boots, neatly cleaned, and, in winter, oiled as well.

Half an hour was the time allotted for the processes of toilet-not very elaborate—and not a word was permitted to be uttered the whole time. Ugh! those icy tin basins and cold winter mornings in the silent, lamp-lit room, with the stars visible through the windows, and all those fuzzle-headed foreigners struggling, after as little washing as possible, into the school uniforms-how tenaciously the memory of it all clings to one!

Everything went like clockwork, and there was never a minute to waste anywhere. The Brother—he always managed to be ready first—waited at the door till the exact second of the time was up, and then led the way briskly down the passage to his Stube. Those who were ready followed him; those who were not got half-breakfast.

An hour’s study followed, from six to seven o’clock, and then we all gathered in the big room on the ground-floor and listened to prayers. A hymn, Luther’s or Zinzendorf’s, was sung with great heartiness, a passage was read from the Bible, and the Herr Direktor followed with a lengthy and earnest prayer. Breakfast was next in order, and by the time it came we were usually quite ready for it. It consisted of two bowls apiece of steaming hot milk (poured out by a boy who was honoured with the title of Einschenker ) and two very large slices of bread—delicious white bread, full of “bubbles” and baked on the premises in enormous loaves. Little boys, who knew they could not manage all their share in the appointed time, would pass on to the bigger ones, and sometimes—though of course this was against the rules-to those unfortunates who were half-breakfasting with a portion of only a single slice apiece.

Breakfast over, the business of the day began in earnest; everything had its allotted time, and punctuality was master. At half past ten, after a period of uninterrupted study, “second breakfast” was in order for those who wanted it. English boys always wanted it, but the majority preferred the three-quarters of an hour in the playground to the seductions of a huge slice of bread and a wee pat of butter.

On either side of the playground were long covered galleries where the Englander might always be seen at tip-and-run, and, if fine, at rounders or a regular cricket-match in the open. Few of the foreigners could be induced to join. Most of them were far more exercised over the addition of some insect or flower to a collection that was under the special care and guidance of a particular Brother; and the interest in natural history was encouraged in every possible way. Football, which we played in the autumn in a big field outside the village, though nomi nally compulsory, was equally unpopular among the majority; for, with few exceptions, the English boys kept the ball to themselves while the others trailed after it in a languid sort of way that showed no real desire to come into contact either with the ball or with the boy behind it. Some of the Brüder, however, played exceedingly well, and there was one Russian master especially who ran like the wind and dribbled like an all-England forward.

This breathing-spell in a long morning’s work was not always given up to mere play, for on cer tain days it was given over to Turnen (gymnastics), and on others to drilling and manoeuvring of the miniature army which the authorities maintained with great thoroughness and discipline. The manoeuvres in the forest, however, we always considered delightful, and the boys one and all looked forward to them with unfeigned glee.

The chief meal of the day Mittagsessen—was at noon. It invariably began with soup—hot water and Nudels usually-then a single helping of meat with two vegetables, one ofwhich was always Sauerkraut, and by way of pudding there was a bit of fruit Kuchen, excellent and very filling. The Sauerkraut was genuinely sauer and not at all like the savoury dish provided with Frankfurter sausages in tion. The little village of Koen most German hotels; but as our appetites dealt more with quantity than with mere flavour, there was never any grumbling, and boys and Brüder alike did justice to all they got. Cases of sickness were exceedingly rare—I hardly recall a single one—and no doubt the excellent plain living did much to keep us all in such robust condition. Headaches, sleeplessness, and the like were unknown in the wonderful air of this bracing mountain village, and even colds were the exception rather than the rule.

The early part of the afternoon was spent in the open air. In winter, each Stube with its Bruder, we wandered through the lovely forest paths, skated, tobogganed, or plunged in high snow-boots through the great drifts in the woods. It was the real Black Forest then. No tourist was ever seen. No carriages, bicycles, or “visitors for health” ever crossed our path. Unmolested, we explored new glades, and found hidden away among the dense trees and Strafe (punishment), when to the pain of carpeted with moss a foot thick.

In one direction was the Gallows Hill (Galgen Hügel), where two huge upright stones overlooked an immense stretch of forest, and where robbers and witches were said to have been executed in the past. They had a wonderful view for their last glimpse of this earth—rolling hills and peaks in every direction covered with a velvet garment of deep, dark woods. Black Forest is seen to be the only possible name from a hill like the Galgen Hügel. In another direction was the bit of haunted road where the Red Mill formerly stood, and whose thrill ing story a Bruder once told us as we wended homewards in the dusk of evening; and all round, wherever we went, there were saw mills, pools, waterfalls, and the like, that held for us an inexhaustible and ever new fascina tion. The little village of Koen igsfeld itself was a Protestant stronghold surrounded by Roman Catholic sections of the country; and a few miles in any direction brought us to giant crucifixes in the woods and at the cross-roads, and to little shrines with wired enclosures at the entrance to the villages.

The magic of a great forest has never touched me more nearly than on these little daily excursions. We saw the trees in rain and sunshine; weighted down with snow, or with their fresh green points just visible in the spring; roaring in great gales of winter (and what a roar it was), or silent in those long summer days when everything seemed motionless and dreaming under a stainless sky. We came to know and love every mood of these enthralling deep woods, a sense of mystery and wonder, that was not wholly of this world, seemed to pervade them in all seasons and in all weathers. It was almost as though they were touched with a radiant spiritual beauty, borrowed, perhaps, from the lives of the good people who dwelt so serenely in their shade; and their majesty tempered by a gentleness that was reflected from the very human hearts of the simple brotherhood beneath their branches.

At four o’clock we came in to “vespers,” a light meal of weak tea and dry bread, and from then till seven was occupied with studies, music (the boys and masters made up between them a complete orchestra), reading, and writing. Supper of bread and stewed fruits was at half-past seven, and an hour later, after evening prayers and a short time of enforced quiet, the Bruder led his Stube of sleepy, tired boys into the Wasch kammer, and thence, when they had dis robed, a flock of yawning youths in grey dressing-gowns, upstairs to bed. It was a full day, but a wholesome one. The punishments were characteristic. Flogging of any sort was unknown. Halbes Frühstück was the commonest penalty and was usually incurred for being late, talking during work-hours, or for using one’s own language.

Next to this came Aufstehen, when the offender was ordered to “stand up.” This was invariably inflicted during work-hours, and generally for inattention, or even nodding over books. German text-books always seemed to induce a healthy slumber in the Ausländer, as all were styled who were not Germans. Oh, those hot summer afternoons, with bees humming through the open windows and the scents of field and forest wafted in across the table, when one looked up from dozes of a fewseconds each and saw faces of many other countries all struggling between dreams of the homeland and the dull books under their noses, and then heard a gruff voice say ing “Aufstehen!” The stand ing up, however, never lasted for more than the remainder of the hour, and was not much dreaded. It was often easier to stand up than to struggle with sleep. A more serious punishment was Strafe (punishment), when to the pain of standing up was added the ignominy of being in Strafe. Speech was forbidden then, and Strafe might last all day, even out of doors, when the victim had to pace the gallery or walk just ahead of the Bruder, if in the forest. It was an effective and boring punishment. But, worse than either, and exceedingly dreaded, was Aufbleiben. This was sitting up when the rest of the boys went to bed. It was meted out only to grave offenders, and was very trying. One had to sit in one of the little cell-like rooms that lined the corridors and were used for music-lessons or special tuition, and there copy out a page or two of German history in German charac ters. The upper half of the door was glass, and it was impossible to go to sleep, and yet almost impossible to prevent it. It was quite distressing, on the way upstairs to bed, to see some poor wretch sitting in his cell with the oil lamp, nodding over his book and paper. Aufbieiben lasted an hour usually. These, then, were the punishments in this Moravian school, and, according to English notions, they were not very severe; nor, I am free to say, was the necessity for their being inflicted very frequent.

III

There was nothing to correspond to the English system of monitors or prefects. The leaders among the boys were the natural leaders. The Engländer led in usual bread and butter. It was never pos games and outdoor exercises, if not in study. No one attempted to dispute their authority there. Sometimes they took the law into their own hands, and the masters, if they knew of it, never interfered. A favourite form of punishment for those who merited their displeasure by not playing up at football, or by “sneaking in some form or other, was waschen—to wash them in the snow. I well remember this penalty being inflicted upon a big French boy whose face, if you please, we considered had not a Then the journeys to the wooden church sufficient acquaintance with soap and water.

He shirked the icy basins in the Waschkammer, and as he lived in our Stube we were obliged to take notice of it. Hints were of no avail. The opportunity came one day when we were out for a trudge in the forest. The snow was soft and very deep. Waiting till the victim was well in front, and there were as many trees as possible between us and the Bruder with the lynx eyes, we ran up and informed him bluntly enough—I can even recall the slang German of it-” Wir halten es für nötig Dich zu waschen “; and I can see now his white face as he dropped meekly into a great drift and underwent the punishment without a struggle. It had evidently been expected. Remorse, however, has always followed us in this particular instance, because, as one of our number observed the following Sunday when English was permissible, “I don’t believe it was dirt at all. I think it’s only his beastly complexion.” Certainly, so far as we could see, was as interesting as any, when we drank he never looked any cleaner for his washing.

On the whole, however, the different nations lived easily and good-temperedly together. round to us in a large clothes-basket. But There was not a single fight during the the whole two years of my stay there, nor did history at that time bear record of any in the past. Among the Germans and English especially there were many friendships of a very genuine character.

Two very important events in the year—at least in the minds of the boys—were the Big and Little Journey. The Little Journey took place in the spring, when we went in parties of fifteen each for a ten-days walking tour through the forest. Each boy carried a knapsack, and a couple of Briider acted as guides and leaders. The weather was always tolerably certain, and each boy was permitted to use his mother-tongue. These trips into the untrodden ways of the forest, sleeping in out-of-the-way villages and charming inns, climbing the hills and exploring the valleys, were a time of unalloyed delight and happiness. Roads were good, the air invigorating, and the simple food—bread, beer, and sausages—just suited our tremendous appetites. All the boys were strong walkers, and most of us, owing to the life we led, in the pink of condition.

The Big Journey took place in the summer holidays, and lasted for about three wecks. It was made up of those boys whose homes were too far away for them to leave, and we started by taking the train into Switzerland or the Tyrol, and then walking wherever it pleased us. Brief accounts of these delightful trips used to appear in the little school paper, “Die Concordia,” and were usually written by one of the more talented Ausladnder.

The religious life of the school was strongly marked, and curious little observances and festivals were woven into the woot of the daily and weekly routine. Scarcely five days passed without a Feast of one sort or another, and we noted these well, because, for one thing. they always brought us Kuchen for vespers in addition to the usual bread and butter. It was never possible to forget that we were in the school of a religious brotherhood. The mode of addressing not only the masters, but the tradespeople of the village, bootmaker, butcher, confectioner, as Bruder, and the women—there were only two, the Direktor’s wife and the kindly old housekeeper who mended our clothes—as Schiester, was @ constant reminder that our teachers and overseers stood in closer relations to us than mere ushers.

Then the journeys to the wooden church across the village square were pretty frequent. The men and boys sat on one side of the centre aisle, and the women and girls’-school on the other. We had no dealings with them, either out of church or in it. An English boy in our Stube hada sister in the Miéidchen-Anstalt, but he rarely saw her, and then only by special arrangement. If we chanced to meet a portion of the girls’-school out for a walk, the Bruder switched us off immediately into the forest before we could catch the merest sight of their sweet faces.

The services held in the church were very simple. A little orchestra helped out the organ on special occasions, and the singing was always hearty, but slow and monotonous, and not unlike the chanting of the Psalms in a Scottish kirk. The sermons were abnormally long, but they at least taught one the language.

Among the Festivals, the Liebesmahl was as interesting as any, when we drank cups of weak tea, and invariably choked over them, and ate buns that were handed round to us in a large clothes-basket. But the New Year’s service was the most trying of any. In its way it was quite an ordeal, for, tired as we were after a day that had begun at half-past five in the morning, we had to troop off to church to see the old year out and the new year in. At half-past eleven the Prediger began his sermon, but on the stroke of twelve, no matter what he was saying, the organ and orchestra crashed out a terrific chord and all the congregation rose to their feet and sang a hymn. Of all the services, though, the Easter Festival was the most picturesque, when in the early morning starlight we marched silently out to the “God’s acre” and took part in a sort of watching service round an open grave, waiting for the light in the cast to spread across the sky. It is a scene impossible to forget-—that group of schoolboys standing reverently with bared heads in the little burial-ground, waiting so quietly, until the first ray shot across the heavens, when, led by the deep voice of the Briider, they turned eastwards in the shadow of those still woods and sang to the rising sun and the risen Saviour.

In the school life itself another simple little festival was observed among the boys. It was called Bescherfest, the Festival of Gifts, and the whole school paired off and presented each other with suitable presents—books, fret-saw articles, and so forth, Each boy might choose with whom he wished to pair, and it was the custom also to ascertain beforehand what present would be most acceptable and useful.

One thing—or, rather, the absence of it—a new English boy noticed very soon. There was no “tuck shop” where he could waste his pocket-money and damage his interior. Occasionally on Sunday (it was only once a month, if I remember rightly) the indulgence in sweetmeats was permitted; but halfof the pleasure—choosing one’s own particular poison—was of a vicarious nature. One boy was chosen from each Stube to go to the little Conditorei that lay on the farther side of the village square, close to the Home for Widows, and there to expend as judiciously as possible the various sums entrusted to his care by the other boys. Ten pfennigs each, about 2d., was allowed per head, and by careful selection one could buy a good deat for the amount. It was even possible to get a double quantity by inducing a boy who wanted none for himself to purchase for you, but this was considered a mean trick and was very little resorted to except by the exceptionally greedy. Some of the boys were too poor, however, even for this simple treat, and it is very pleasant to recall bow often the more fortunate ones shared with them the results of their purchase. One lad, there was, however, a Strassbourger, who not. only always bought two lots of cakes, but never passed on the least bit of them to any one else, not even to the boy in whose name and by whose kindness he was able to get the extra allowance. He was in the second Stube_ when his ugly fame first got noised abroad among us. When he was promoted to the erste Stube he had his punishment, for the Purchaser of Cakes of that room made it a point as often as he could to forget altogether to buy for him, to report that the things he wanted were all gone, or to buy the wrong cakes and bring back sugarless morsels instead—much to the disgust of the greedy Strassbourger.

Before the Season

Being in Switzerland early in December is like being behind the scenes during the preparation of a great winter pantomime. Five hundred hotels are empty, trains are empty, shops and streets are empty, too; but yet everything is humming and buzzing with excitement, like a hive. On the 20th the great exodus from England begins. Ask a porter for a bit of string now, and it will be forthcoming with a pleasant smile; but ask for it ten days hence, and he will look surprised, groan, mutter an excuse and promptly vanish underground.

Those are fortunate who were able to get out early this year, for the December weather has been most kind, with keen frost, plenty of snow and the mountain slopes unstreaked by the ugly network of ski tracks that mars their loveliness later. That is to say, above a certain height, and in certain places, snow is plentiful. Here, at Saanenméser, on the mountain line between Montreux and Spiez, at a height of some four thousand feet, skiing conditions have been as perfect as in an ideal February, and February is the chosen month of experts. Although every room in the excellent little hotel is booked weeks ahead, it has been empty for a fortnight, and the mountains have been unusually inviting. On arriving here on December 3rd, several feet of snow lay already on the ground, and after two days of blazing sunshine, a welcome wind rose out of the west, bringing a heavy fall that lasted without stopping for twenty-four hours. Keen frost followed. The snow shone and sparkled with those big erystals dear to every skier’s heart, running was swift and accurate, and the numerous expeditions that open in all directions, like the spokes of a wheel, made daily trips imperative, regardless of the staleness that invariably punishes too ardent zeal at the beginning. But then, Saanenméser lies in a valley that is a veritable snow-trap. A little below, Gstaad on one side, and Zweisimmen on the other, the valleys are still green and springlike. Saanenméser, like its admirable mountain hotel is unique. Railways help it on all sides—to bring one home again apart from a dozen smaller “runs” of enticing beauty that start from the very door, there are two and three day trips in other directions, all easily accessible; and the great Wildhorn beckons just beyond the ridge—the Wildhorn, whose head towers 10,000ft. into the sunshine, whose climbing means a lightning descent of some 6,000ft., and a night in a hut halfway up into the bargain. The cold, of course, is something to remember; so is the night on the straw when every available thread of clothing seems not half enough; the cooking of dinner and breakfast on a fire of wood; the wild desolation of winter that the moon shines on outside, and the sunrise in the morning that reveals a world the gods have just that very second turned out in marvellous, white detail.

It is difficult to believe that in a few days at most these little mountain villages will buzz with cosmopolitan languages, dazzling the eye of the native with the latest “winter costume” from London, Paris and Vienna; that there will be music and dancing every night; and that these rinks, now so busily preparing, will teem with hundreds and look like some parade of a fancy-dress performance. Fifteen years ago there were practically no private rinks at all; no such thing as ski went rustling and flying down these mighty slopes. In so short a time has this great winter industry sprung into existence, bringing health and pleasure to countless thousands, and leaving countless thousands, too, in the pockets of the hotel proprietors. In the first few years it was the proper thing to send to Norway for ski, ski boots, and all the rest, but now Zurich and Bern, seizing the opportunity, make as perfect articles as ever came out of Christiania, and cheaper into the bargain.

The work of preparing for this winter multitude is more than many, perhaps, imagine. The summer and autumn season has hardly gone before the army of workmen begin operations. Hotels barely close their doors at all now. There is little breathing space for anybody, and though the proprietors may grumble privately to you, they do not grumble in their heart of hearts, for their incomes have been easily doubled. Early in December the experts come to make the rinks, at salaries by no means insignificant. It is as difficult to make a really good rink as it is to lay a really good hard tennis court. All night long in the moonlight, at a bitter and freezing temperature, the man in charge stands spraying the surface with the hosepipe, aided by the glare of a large electric light swung across upon a wire. His gauntlet gloves get frozen solid, and he takes another pair. The sound of the hissing water follows one into dreamland. By sunrise he is there again, still scattering water over the uneven lumpy field that hundreds cut intricate figures on by Christmas Day. From the tourists he gets little thanks, the slightest inequality being blamed loudly, and laid at the door of his “abominable incompetence.” But it is no easy job to lay a proper rink. After the first heavy fall of snow the greater mass is carted off to build the enclosing walls, while the remainder is beaten flat by a score of workmen till it is smooth enough to take the first sprinkling of water. Once this is done, the probability is there comes another fall of snow, when the entire process has to be repeated—till the final result represents hours and hours of labour, carried on in all weathers and at all hours of the day and night.

Besides the rink, there is the ice-run for toboggans, an enterprise calling for even greater skill. Its general “lay” and direction, its curves, its walls and the adequate watering of these so that they freeze into a wild, yet safe, descent, combine in a task that is not easily—nor by any means always—quite successful. Yet people grumble at the slightest thing amiss, and many grumble, too, because the hotels make an extra weekly charge for the enjoyment of these costly and elaborate “sports.” Indeed, the Swiss winter resorts now lay themselves out to prepare for their visitors as ambitiously and variously as any popular summer resort beside the sea.

There is, however, one serious drawback in coming out too early. Being first in the field involves making the first tracks. Later, up all the main ascents, others have done this for you. And the labour of making the opening track in deep and powdery snow for several hours in a blazing sun has to be known to be appreciated.

By Water

The night before young Larsen left to take up his new appointment in Egypt he went to the clairvoyante. He neither believed nor disbelieved. He felt no interest, for he already knew his past and did not wish to know his future. “Just to please me, Jim,” the girl pleaded. “The woman is wonderful. Before I had been five minutes with her she told me your initials, so there must be something in it.” “She read your thought,” he smiled indulgently. “Even I can do that!” But the girl was in earnest. He yielded; and that night at his farewell dinner he came to give his report of the interview.

The result was meagre and unconvincing: money was coming to him, he was soon to make a voyage, and—he would never marry. “So you see how silly it all is,” he laughed, for they were to be married when his first promotion came. He gave the details, however, making a little story of it in the way he knew she loved.

“But was that all, Jim?” The girl asked it, looking rather hard into his face. “Aren’t you hiding something from me?” He hesitated a moment, then burst out laughing at her clever discernment. “There was a little more,” he confessed, “but you take it all so seriously; I——”

He had to tell it then, of course. The woman had told him a lot of gibberish about friendly and unfriendly elements. “She said water was unfriendly to me; I was to be careful of water, or else I should come to harm by it. Fresh water only,” he hastened to add, seeing that the idea of shipwreck was in her mind.

“Drowning?” the girl asked quickly.

“Yes,” he admitted with reluctance, but still laughing; “she did say drowning, though drowning in no ordinary way.”

The girl’s face showed uneasiness a moment. “What does that mean—drowning in no ordinary way?” she asked, a catch in her breath.

But that he could not tell her, because he did not know himself. He gave, therefore, the exact words: “You will drown, but will not know you drown.”

It was unwise of him. He wished afterwards he had invented a happier report, or had kept this detail back. “I’m safe in Egypt, anyhow,” he laughed. “I shall be a clever man if I can find enough water in the desert to do me harm!” And all the way from Trieste to Alexandria he remembered the promise she had extracted—that he would never once go on the Nile unless duty made it imperative for him to do so. He kept that promise like the literal, faithful soul he was. His love was equal to the somewhat quixotic sacrifice it occasionally involved. Fresh water in Egypt there was practically none other, and in any case the natrum works where his duty lay had their headquarters some distance out into the desert. The river, with its banks of welcome, refreshing verdure, was not even visible.

Months passed quickly, and the time for leave came within measurable distance. In the long interval luck had played the cards kindly for him, vacancies had occurred, early promotion seemed likely, and his letters were full of plans to bring her out to share a little house of their own. His health, however, had not improved; the dryness did not suit him; even in this short period his blood had thinned, his nervous system deteriorated, and, contrary to the doctor’s prophecy, the waterless air had told upon his sleep. A damp climate liked him best, and once the sun had touched him with its fiery finger.

His letters made no mention of this. He described the life to her, the work, the sport, the pleasant people, and his chances of increased pay and early marriage. And a week before he sailed he rode out upon a final act of duty to inspect the latest diggings his company were making. His course lay some twenty miles into the desert behind El-Chobak and towards the limestone hills of Guebel Haidi, and he went alone, carrying lunch and tea, for it was the weekly holiday of Friday, and the men were not at work.

The accident was ordinary enough. On his way back in the heat of early afternoon his pony stumbled against a boulder on the treacherous desert film, threw him heavily, broke the girth, bolted before he could seize the reins again, and left him stranded some ten or twelve miles from home. There was a pain in his knee that made walking difficult, a buzzing in his head that troubled sight and made the landscape swim, while, worse than either, his provisions, fastened to the saddle, had vanished with the frightened pony into those blazing leagues of sand. He was alone in the Desert, beneath the pitiless afternoon sun, twelve miles of utterly exhausting country between him and safety.

Under normal conditions he could have covered the distance in four hours, reaching home by dark; but his knee pained him so that a mile an hour proved the best he could possibly do. He reflected a few minutes. The wisest course was to sit down and wait till the pony told its obvious story to the stable, and help should come. And this was what he did, for the scorching heat and glare were dangerous; they were terrible; he was shaken and bewildered by his fall, hungry and weak into the bargain; and an hour’s painful scrambling over the baked and burning little gorges must have speedily caused complete prostration. He sat down and rubbed his aching knee. It was quite a little adventure. Yet, though he knew the Desert might not be lightly trifled with, he felt at the moment nothing more than this—and the amusing description of it he would give in his letter, or—intoxicating thought—by word of mouth. In the heat of the sun he began to feel drowsy. A soft torpor crept over him. He dozed. He fell asleep.

It was a long, a dreamless sleep ... for when he woke at length the sun had just gone down, the dusk lay awfully upon the enormous desert, and the air was chilly. The cold had waked him. Quickly, as though on purpose, the red glow faded from the sky; the first stars shone; it was dark; the heavens were deep violet. He looked round and realised that his sense of direction had gone entirely. Great hunger was in him. The cold already was bitter as the wind rose, but the pain in his knee having eased, he got up and walked a little—and in a moment lost sight of the spot where he had been lying. The shadowy desert swallowed it. “Ah,” he realised, “this is not an English field or moor. I’m in the Desert!” The safe thing to do was to remain exactly where he was; only thus could the rescuers find him; once he wandered he was done for. It was strange the search-party had not yet arrived. To keep warm, however, he was compelled to move, so he made a little pile of stones to mark the place, and walked round and round it in a circle of some dozen yards’ diameter. He limped badly, and the hunger gnawed dreadfully; but, after all, the adventure was not so terrible. The amusing side of it kept uppermost still. Though fragile in body, his spirit was not unduly timid or imaginative; he could last out the night, or, if the worst came to the worst, the next day as well. But when he watched the little group of stones, he saw that there were dozens of them, scores, hundreds, thousands of these little groups of stones. The desert’s face, of course, is thickly strewn with them. The original one was lost in the first five minutes. So he sat down again. But the biting cold, and the wind that licked his very skin beneath the light clothing, soon forced him up again. It was ominous; and the night huge and shelterless. The shaft of green zodiacal light that hung so strangely in the western sky for hours had faded away; the stars were out in their bright thousands; no guide was anywhere; the wind moaned and puffed among the sandy mounds; the vast sheet of desert stretched appallingly upon the world; he heard the jackals cry. ...

And with the jackals’ cry came suddenly the unwelcome realisation that no play was in this adventure any more, but that a bleak reality stared at him through the surrounding darkness. He faced it—at bay. He was genuinely lost. Thought blocked in him. “I must be calm and think,” he said aloud. His voice woke no echo; it was small and dead; something gigantic ate it instantly. He got up and walked again. Why did no one come? Hours had passed. The pony had long ago found its stable, or—had it run madly in another direction altogether? He worked out possibilities, tightening his belt. The cold was searching; he never had been, never could be warm again; the hot sunshine of a few hours ago seemed the merest dream. Unfamiliar with hardship, he knew not what to do, but he took his coat and shirt off, vigorously rubbed his skin where the dried perspiration of the afternoon still caused clammy shivers, swung his arms furiously like a London cabman, and quickly dressed again. Though the wind upon his bare back was fearful, he felt warmer a little. He lay down exhausted, sheltered by an overhanging limestone crag, and took snatches of fitful dog’s-sleep, while the wind drove overhead and the dry sand pricked his skin. One face continually was near him; one pair of tender eyes; two dear hands smoothed him; he smelt the perfume of light brown hair. It was all natural enough. His whole thought, in his misery, ran to her in England—England where there were soft fresh grass, big sheltering trees, hemlock and honeysuckle in the hedges—while the hard black Desert guarded him, and consciousness dipped away at little intervals under this dry and pitiless Egyptian sky. ...

It was perhaps five in the morning when a voice spoke and he started up with a horrid jerk—the voice of that clairvoyante woman. The sentence died away into the darkness, but one word remained: Water! At first he wondered, but at once explanation came. Cause and effect were obvious. The clue was physical. His body needed water, and so the thought came up into his mind. He was thirsty.

This was the moment when fear first really touched him. Hunger was manageable, more or less—for a day or two, certainly. But thirst! Thirst and the Desert were an evil pair that, by cumulative suggestion gathering since childhood days, brought terror in. Once in the mind it could not be dislodged. In spite of his best efforts, the ghastly thing grew passionately—because his thirst grew too. He had smoked much; had eaten spiced things at lunch; had breathed in alkali with the dry, scorched air. He searched for a cool flint pebble to put into his burning mouth, but found only angular scraps of dusty limestone. There were no pebbles here. The cold helped a little to counteract, but already he knew in himself subconsciously the dread of something that was coming. What was it? He tried to hide the thought and bury it out of sight. The utter futility of his tiny strength against the power of the universe appalled him. And then he knew. The merciless sun was on the way, already rising. Its return was like the presage of execution to him. ...

It came. With true horror he watched the marvellous swift dawn break over the sandy sea. The eastern sky glowed hurriedly as from crimson fires. Ridges, not noticeable in the starlight, turned black in endless series, like flat-topped billows of a frozen ocean. Wide streaks of blue and yellow followed, as the sky dropped sheets of faint light upon the wind-eaten cliffs and showed their under sides. They did not advance; they waited till the sun was up—and then they moved; they rose and sank; they shifted as the sunshine lifted them and the shadows crept away. But in an hour there would be no shadows any more. There would be no shade! ...

The little groups of stones began to dance. It was horrible. The unbroken, huge expanse lay round him, warming up, twelve hours of blazing hell to come. Already the monstrous Desert glared, each bit familiar, since each bit was a repetition of the bit before, behind, on either side. It laughed at guidance and direction. He rose and walked; for miles he walked, though how many, north, south, or west, he knew not. The frantic thing was in him now, the fury of the Desert; he took its pace, its endless, tireless stride, the stride of the burning, murderous Desert that is—waterless. He felt it alive—a blindly heaving desire in it to reduce him to its conditionless, awful dryness. He felt—yet knowing this was feverish and not to be believed—that his own small life lay on its mighty surface, a mere dot in space, a mere heap of little stones. His emotions, his fears, his hopes, his ambition, his love—mere bundled group of little unimportant stones that danced with apparent activity for a moment, then were merged in the undifferentiated surface underneath. He was included in a purpose greater than his own.

The will made a plucky effort then. “A night and a day,” he laughed, while his lips cracked smartingly with the stretching of the skin, “what is it? Many a chap has lasted days and days ...!” Yes, only he was not of that rare company. He was ordinary, unaccustomed to privation, weak, untrained of spirit, unacquainted with stern resistance. He knew not how to spare himself. The Desert struck him where it pleased—all over. It played with him. His tongue was swollen; the parched throat could not swallow. He sank. ... An hour he lay there, just wit enough in him to choose the top of a mound where he could be most easily seen. He lay two hours, three, four hours. ... The heat blazed down upon him like a furnace. ... The sky, when he opened his eyes once, was empty ... then a speck became visible in the blue expanse; and presently another speck. They came from nowhere. They hovered very high, almost out of sight. They appeared, they disappeared, they—reappeared. Nearer and nearer they swung down, in sweeping stealthy circles ... little dancing groups of them, miles away but ever drawing closer—the vultures. ...

He had strained his ears so long for sounds of feet and voices that it seemed he could no longer hear at all. Hearing had ceased within him. Then came the water-dreams, with their agonising torture. He heard that ... heard it running in silvery streams and rivulets across green English meadows. It rippled with silvery music. He heard it splash. He dipped hands and feet and head in it—in deep, clear pools of generous depth. He drank; with his skin he drank, not with mouth and throat alone. Ice clinked in effervescent, sparkling water against a glass. He swam and plunged. Water gushed freely over back and shoulders, gallons and gallons of it, bathfuls and to spare, a flood of gushing, crystal, cool, life-giving liquid. ... And then he stood in a beech wood and felt the streaming deluge of delicious summer rain upon his face; heard it drip luxuriantly upon a million thirsty leaves. The wet trunks shone, the damp moss spread its perfume, ferns waved heavily in the moist atmosphere. He was soaked to the skin in it. A mountain torrent, fresh from fields of snow, foamed boiling past, and the spray fell in a shower upon his cheeks and hair. He dived—head foremost. ... Ah, he was up to the neck ... and she was with him; they were under water together; he saw her eyes gleaming into his own beneath the copious flood.

The voice, however, was not hers. ... “You will drown, yet you will not know you drown ...!” His swollen tongue called out a name. But no sound was audible. He closed his eyes. There came sweet unconsciousness. ...

A sound in that instant was audible, though. It was a voice—voices—and the thud of animal hoofs upon the sand. The specks had vanished from the sky as mysteriously as they came. And, as though in answer to the sound, he made a movement—an automatic, unconscious movement. He did not know he moved. And the body, uncontrolled, lost its precarious balance. He rolled; but he did not know he rolled. Slowly, over the edge of the sloping mound of sand, he turned sideways. Like a log of wood he slid gradually, turning over and over, nothing to stop him—to the bottom. A few feet only, and not even steep; just steep enough to keep rolling slowly. There was a—splash. But he did not know there was a splash.

They found him in a pool of water—one of these rare pools the Desert Bedouin mark preciously for their own. He had lain within three yards of it for hours. He was drowned ... but he did not know he drowned. ...

CAIN’S ATONEMENT

So many thousands to-day have deliberately put Self aside, and are ready to yield their lives for an ideal, that it is not surprising a few of them should have registered experiences of a novel order. For to step aside from Self is to enter a larger world, to be open to new impressions. If Powers of Good exist in the universe at all, they can hardly be inactive at the present time. ...

The case of two men, who may be called Jones and Smith, occurs to the mind in this connection. Whether a veil actually was lifted for a moment, or whether the tension of long and terrible months resulted in an exaltation of emotion, the experience claims significance. Smith, to whom the experience came, holds the firm belief that it was real. Jones, though it involved him too, remained unaware.

It is a somewhat personal story, their peculiar relationship dating from early youth: a kind of unwilling antipathy was born between them, yet an antipathy that had no touch of hate or even of dislike. It was rather in the nature of an instinctive rivalry. Some tie operated that flung them ever into the same arena with strange persistence, and ever as opponents. An inevitable fate delighted to throw them together in a sense that made them rivals; small as well as large affairs betrayed this malicious tendency of the gods. It showed itself in earliest days, at school, at Cambridge, in travel, even in house-parties and the lighter social intercourse. Though distant cousins, their families were not intimate, and there was no obvious reason why their paths should fall so persistently together. Yet their paths did so, crossing and recrossing in the way described. Sooner or later, in all his undertakings, Smith would note the shadow of Jones darkening the ground in front of him; and later, when called to the Bar in his chosen profession, he found most frequently that the learned counsel in opposition to him was the owner of this shadow, Jones. In another matter, too, they became rivals, for the same girl, oddly enough, attracted both, and though she accepted neither offer of marriage (during Smith’s lifetime!), the attitude between them was that of unwilling rivals. For they were friends as well.

Jones, it appears, was hardly aware that any rivalry existed; he did not think of Smith as an opponent, and as an adversary, never. He did notice, however, the constantly recurring meetings, for more than once he commented on them with good-humoured amusement. Smith, on the other hand, was conscious of a depth and strength in the tie that certainly intrigued him; being of a thoughtful, introspective nature, he was keenly sensible of the strange competition in their lives, and sought in various ways for its explanation, though without success. The desire to find out was very strong in him. And this was natural enough, owing to the singular fact that in all their battles he was the one to lose. Invariably Jones got the best of every conflict. Smith always paid; sometimes he paid with interest.

Occasionally, too, he seemed forced to injure himself while contributing to his cousin’s success. It was very curious. He reflected much upon it; he wondered what the origin of their tie and rivalry might be, but especially why it was that he invariably lost, and why he was so often obliged to help his rival to the point even of his own detriment. Tempted to bitterness sometimes, he did not yield to it, however; the relationship remained frank and pleasant; if anything, it deepened.

He remembered once, for instance, giving his cousin a chance introduction which yet led, a little later, to the third party offering certain evidence which lost him an important case—Jones, of course, winning it. The third party, too, angry at being dragged into the case, turned hostile to him, thwarting various subsequent projects. In no other way could Jones have procured this particular evidence; he did not know of its existence even. That chance introduction did it all. There was nothing the least dishonourable on the part of Jones—it was just the chance of the dice. The dice were always loaded against Smith—and there were other instances of similar kind.

About this time, moreover, a singular feeling that had lain vaguely in his mind for some years past, took more definite form. It suddenly assumed the character of a conviction, that yet had no evidence to support it. A voice, long whispering in the depths of him, became much louder, grew into a statement that he accepted without further ado: “I’m paying off a debt,” he phrased it, “an old, old debt is being discharged. I owe him this—my help and so forth.” He accepted it, that is, as just; and this certainty of justice kept sweet his heart and mind, shutting the door on bitterness or envy. The thought, however, though it recurred persistently with each encounter, brought no explanation.

When the war broke out both offered their services; as members of the O.T.C., they got commissions quickly; but it was a chance remark of Smith’s that made his friend join the very regiment he himself was in. They trained together, were in the same retreats and the same advances together. Their friendship deepened. Under the stress of circumstances the tie did not dissolve, but strengthened. It was indubitably real, therefore. Then, oddly enough, they were both wounded in the same engagement.

And it was here the remarkable fate that jointly haunted them betrayed itself more clearly than in any previous incident of their long relationship—Smith was wounded in the act of protecting his cousin. How it happened is confusing to a layman, but each apparently was leading a bombing-party, and the two parties came together. They found themselves shoulder to shoulder, both brimmed with that pluck which is complete indifference to Self; they exchanged a word of excited greeting; and the same second one of those rare opportunities of advantage presented itself which only the highest courage could make use of. Neither, certainly, was thinking of personal reward; it was merely that each saw the chance by which instant heroism might gain a surprise advantage for their side. The risk was heavy, but there was a chance; and success would mean a decisive result, to say nothing of high distinction for the man who obtained it—if he survived. Smith, being a few yards ahead of his cousin, had the moment in his grasp. He was in the act of dashing forward when something made him pause. A bomb in mid-air, flung from the opposing trench, was falling; it seemed immediately above him; he saw that it would just miss himself, but land full upon his cousin—whose head was turned the other way. By stretching out his hand, Smith knew he could field it like a cricket ball. There was an interval of a second and a half, he judged. He hesitated—perhaps a quarter of a second—then he acted. He caught it. It was the obvious thing to do. He flung it back into the opposing trench.

The rapidity of thought is hard to realise. In that second and a half Smith was aware of many things: He saved his cousin’s life unquestionably; unquestionably also Jones seized the opportunity that otherwise was his cousin’s. But it was neither of these reflections that filled Smith’s mind. The dominant impression was another. It flashed into actual words inside his excited brain: “I must risk it. I owe it to him—and more besides!” He was, further, aware of another impulse than the obvious one. In the first fraction of a second it was overwhelmingly established. And it was this: that the entire episode was familiar to him. A subtle familiarity was present. All this had happened before. He had already—somewhere, somehow—seen death descending upon his cousin from the air. Yet with a difference. The “difference” escaped him; the familiarity was vivid. That he missed the deadly detonators in making the catch, or that the fuse delayed, he called good luck. He only remembers that he flung the gruesome weapon back whence it had come, and that its explosion in the opposite trench materially helped his cousin to find glory in the place of death. The slight delay, however, resulted in his receiving a bullet through the chest—a bullet he would not otherwise have received, presumably.

It was some days later, gravely wounded, that he discovered his cousin in another bed across the darkened floor. They exchanged remarks. Jones was already “decorated,” it seemed, having snatched success from his cousin’s hands, while little aware whose help had made it easier. ... And once again there stole across the inmost mind of Smith that strange, insistent whisper: “I owed it to him ... but, by God, I owe more than that ... I mean to pay it too ...!”

There was not a trace of bitterness or envy now; only this profound conviction, of obscurest origin, that it was right and absolutely just—full, honest repayment of a debt incurred. Some ancient balance of account was being settled; there was no “chance”; injustice and caprice played no role at all. ... And a deeper understanding of life’s ironies crept into him; for if everything was just, there was no room for whimpering.

And the voice persisted above the sound of busy footsteps in the ward: “I owe it ... I’ll pay it gladly ...!”

Through the pain and weakness the whisper died away. He was exhausted. There were periods of unconsciousness, but there were periods of half-consciousness as well; then flashes of another kind of consciousness altogether, when, bathed in high, soft light, he was aware of things he could not quite account for. He saw. It was absolutely real. Only, the critical faculty was gone. He did not question what he saw, as he stared across at his cousin’s bed. He knew. Perhaps the beaten, worn-out body let something through at last. The nerves, over-strained to numbness, lay very still. The physical system, battered and depleted, made no cry. The clamour of the flesh was hushed. He was aware, however, of an undeniable exaltation of the spirit in him, as he lay and gazed towards his cousin’s bed. ...

Across the night of time, it seemed to him, the picture stole before his inner eye with a certainty that left no room for doubt. It was not the cells of memory in his brain of To-day that gave up their dead, it was the eternal Self in him that remembered and understood—the soul. ...

With that satisfaction which is born of full comprehension, he watched the light glow and spread about the little bed. Thick matting deadened the footsteps of nurses, orderlies, doctors. New cases were brought in, “old” cases were carried out; he ignored them; he saw only the light above his cousin’s bed grow stronger. He lay still and stared. It came neither from the ceiling nor the floor; it unfolded like a cloud of shining smoke. And the little lamp, the sheets, the figure framed between them—all these slid cleverly away and vanished utterly. He stood in another place that had lain behind all these appearances—a landscape with wooded hills, a foaming river, the sun just sinking below the forest, and dusk creeping from a gorge along the lonely banks. In the warm air there was a perfume of great flowers and heavy-scented trees; there were fire-flies, and the taste of spray from the tumbling river was on his lips. Across the water a large bird, flapped its heavy wings, as it moved down-stream to find another fishing place. For he and his companion had disturbed it as they broke out of the thick foliage and reached the river-bank. The companion, moreover, was his brother; they ever hunted together; there was a passionate link between them born of blood and of affection—they were twins. ...

It all was as clear as though of Yesterday. In his heart was the lust of the hunt; in his blood was the lust of woman; and thick behind these lurked the jealousy and fierce desire of a primitive day. But, though clear as of Yesterday, he knew that it was of long, long ago. ... And his brother came up close beside him, resting his bloody spear with a clattering sound against the boulders on the shore. He saw the gleaming of the metal in the sunset, he saw the shining glitter of the spray upon the boulders, he saw his brother’s eyes look straight into his own. And in them shone a light that was neither the reflection of the sunset, nor the excitement of the hunt just over.

“It escaped us,” said his brother. “Yet I know my first spear struck.”

“It followed the fawn that crossed,” was the reply. “Besides, we came down wind, thus giving it warning. Our flocks, at any rate, are safer——”

The other laughed significantly.

“It is not the safety of our flocks that troubles me just now, brother,” he interrupted eagerly, while the light burned more deeply in his eyes. “It is, rather, that she waits for me by the fire across the river, and that I would get to her. With your help added to my love,” he went on in a trusting voice, “the gods have shown me the favour of true happiness!” He pointed with his spear to a camp-fire on the farther bank, turning his head as he strode to plunge into the stream and swim across.

For an instant, then, the other felt his natural love turn into bitter hate. His own fierce passion, unconfessed, concealed, burst into instant flame. That the girl should become his brother’s wife sent the blood surging through his veins in fury. He felt his life and all that he desired go down in ashes. ... He watched his brother stride towards the water, the deer-skin cast across one naked shoulder—when another object caught his practised eye. In mid-air it passed suddenly, like a shining gleam; it seemed to hang a second; then it swept swiftly forward past his head—and downward. It had leaped with a blazing fury from the overhanging bank behind; he saw the blood still streaming from its wounded flank. It must land—he saw it with a secret, awful pleasure—full upon the striding figure, whose head was turned away!

The swiftness of that leap, however, was not so swift but that he could easily have used his spear. Indeed, he gripped it strongly. His skill, his strength, his aim—he knew them well enough. But hate and love, fastening upon his heart, held all his muscles still. He hesitated. He was no murderer, yet he paused. He heard the roar, the ugly thud, the crash, the cry for help—too late ... and when, an instant afterwards, his steel plunged into the great beast’s heart, the human heart and life he might have saved lay still for ever. ... He heard the water rushing past, an icy wind came down the gorge against his naked back, he saw the fire shine upon the farther bank ... and the figure of a girl in skins was wading across, seeking out the shallow places in the dusk, and calling wildly as she came. ... Then darkness hid the entire landscape, yet a darkness that was deeper, bluer than the velvet of the night alone. ...

And he shrieked aloud in his remorseful anguish: “May the gods forgive me, for I did not mean it! Oh, that I might undo ... that I might repay ...!”

That his cries disturbed the weary occupants in more than one bed is certain, but he remembers chiefly that a nurse was quickly by his side, and that something she gave him soothed his violent pain and helped him into deeper sleep again. There was, he noticed, anyhow, no longer the soft, clear, blazing light about his cousin’s bed. He saw only the faint glitter of the oil-lamps down the length of the great room. ...

And some weeks later he went back to fight. The picture, however, never left his memory. It stayed with him as an actual reality that was neither delusion nor hallucination. He believed that he understood at last the meaning of the tie that had fettered him and puzzled him so long. The memory of those far-off days of shepherding beneath the stars of long ago remained vividly beside him. He kept his secret, however. In many a talk with his cousin beneath the nearer stars of Flanders no word of it ever passed his lips.

The friendship between them, meanwhile, experienced a curious deepening, though unacknowledged in any spoken words. Smith, at any rate, on his side, put into it an affection that was a brave man’s love. He watched over his cousin. In the fighting especially, when possible, he sought to protect and shield him, regardless of his own personal safety. He delighted secretly in the honours his cousin had already won. He himself was not yet even mentioned in dispatches, and no public distinction of any kind had come his way.

His V.C. eventually—well, he was no longer occupying his body when it was bestowed. He had already “left.”... He was now conscious, possibly, of other experiences besides that one of ancient, primitive days when he and his brother were shepherding beneath other stars. But the reckless heroism which saved his cousin under fire may later enshrine another memory which, at some far future time, shall reawaken as a “hallucination” from a Past that to-day is called the Present. ... The notion, at any rate, flashed across his mind before he “left.”

Carlton’s Drive

It is difficult, of course, to estimate the effect of such a thing upon another’s temperament. The change seemed bewilderingly sudden; yet spiritual chemistry is a process incalculable, past finding out, and the results in this case were undeniable. Carlton had changed in the course of a brief year or two. And he dates it from that drive. He knows.

He told it to a few intimates only. Those who know his face as it is today, serene and strong, yet recall how it was scored and beaten with the ravages of dissipation a few years before (so that the human seemed almost to have dropped back into the beast), can scarcely credit his identity. Now—its calm austerity, softened by the greatest yearning known to men, the yearning to save, proclaim at a glance the splendid revolution; whereas then—! The memory is unpleasant; exceedingly wonderful the contrast. His life was inoffensive enough, negatively, at least, till the money came; then, with the inheritance, his innate sensuality broke out. Yet it seemed a prodigious step for a man to make in so brief a time: from that life of depravity that stained his face and smothered his soul, to the Brotherhood of Devotion he founded, and himself led full charge against the vice of the world! But not incomprehensible, perhaps. He did nothing by halves. It was the swing of the pendulum.

He was somewhere about thirty, his nerves shattered by the savagery of concentrated fast living, his system too exhausted to respond even to unusual stimulant, when he found himself one early spring morning on the pavement beside St. George’s Hospital. He had been up all night, and was making his way homewards on foot, his pockets stuffed with the proceeds of lucky gambling; and how he happened to be standing at that particular spot, watching the traffic, at eight in the morning, is not clear. Probably, seduced by the sweetness of the air, he had wandered, driven by gusts of mood as by gusts of wind. Though he had drunk steadily since midnight he was not so much intoxicated as fuddled—stupid. He was on the south corner, where the ’buses stop in their journey westwards. The sun poured a flood of light down Piccadilly; the street was brisk with pedestrians going to work; the hospital side-entrance behind him already astir. Across the road the trees in the park shimmered in a wave of fluttering green. The pride of life was in the June air. In his own heart, however, was a loathsome satiety—sign of the first death.

In a line with the trees opposite stood a solitary hansom. A faint surprise that it should be there at such an hour jostled in his sodden brain with the idea that he might as well drive home—when, suddenly, he became aware that the man perched on the box was looking at him across the street with a fixity of manner that was both singular and offensive. Carlton felt his own gaze, blear-eyed and troubled, somehow caught and held—uncomfortably. The other’s eyes were fastened upon his own—had been fastened for sometime—sinisterly, and with a purpose. Just at this moment, however, a sharp spasm of pain and faintness, due to exhaustion and debauch, shot through him, so that he reeled, half staggering, and, before he quite knew what he was doing, he had nodded to the driver, and saw that the horse was already turning with clattering hoofs to cross the slippery street. A minute later he had climbed heavily in, noticing vaguely that the driver wore all black, the horse was black, and on the whip was a strip of crêpe that fluttered in the breeze. As he got in, too, the effort strained him. But, more than that, something that was cold and terrible—“like a hand of ragged steel,” he described it afterwards—clutched at his heart. It puzzled him; but he was too “done” to think; and he lurched back wearily on the cushions as the horse started forward with the jerkiness of long habit.

“Same address, sir?” the man called down through the trap. His voice was harsh “like iron”; and Carlton, supposing that he recognized a fare, replied testily, “Of course, you fool! And let her rip—to the devil!” The spasm of strange pain had passed. He only felt tired to brokenness, sick with his corrupt and unsatisfying life, a dull, incomprehensible anger burning in him against the world, the driver—and himself.

The hansom swung forwards over the smooth, uncrowded streets like a ship with a breeze behind her, for the horse was fresh, and the man drove well. He took off his opera hat and let the cool wind fan his face. That drive of a mile to his rooms was the most soothing and restful he had ever known. But, after a while, braced, perhaps, by the morning wind, he began to notice that they were following a strange route through streets he did not recognize. He had been lolling in the corner with half-closed eyes; now he sat up and looked about him. Time had passed. He ought to have reached home long ago. They were going at a tremendous and unholy pace, too. He poked open the trap sharply.

“Hi, hi!” he called out angrily; “are you drunk? Where, in the name of—are you driving to?”

“It’s all right, sir; it’s the shortest way. The usual roads are closed.”

The man’s voice—deep, with a curious rumbling note—had such conviction and authority in it that Carlton accepted the explanation with a growl and flung himself back into his soft corner. Again, however, for a single second, that cold thing of steel moved horribly in his heart. He felt as if the “ragged hand” had given it another twist. Then it passed, and he gave himself up to the swinging motion of the drive. The hansom tore along now; it was delightful. Curious, though, that all the known streets should be “up”! Positively the houses were getting less, as though he was driving out into the country. Perhaps, too, the feeling of laisser aller that came over him was caused by some inhibition of the will due to prolonged excesses. Carlton admits it was unlike his normal self not to force the man to drive where he wanted; but he felt lulled, lazy, indifferent. “Let the fool take his own way!” his thought ran; “I shan’t pay him any more for it!”

Somebody was waving to him from the pavement with a coloured parasol—a girl he knew, one of his sort; gay and smiling, tripping along quickly. With a momentary surprise that she should be thus early astir, he smiled through the window and waved his hand. It gave him pleasure to see she was going in the same direction as himself. The instant he passed her the horse leaped forward with increased speed, so that the hansom rattled, shaking him a little as it lurched from side to side.

“Steady on, idiot!” he shouted, “or you’ll smash me up before I get to the end!” And he was just going to bang open the trap and swear, when his attention was caught by another salutation from the pavement. It was a man this time—running hard; a man who played, drank, and the rest of it even harder than himself, a man who shared his trips to Paris. He was radiant and gesticulating. “Good journey, old man!” he heard him cry as the hansom shot past; “Hurry up! We’re coming, too! We shall be there together!” Carlton did not quite like this greeting. It reminded him for a second that he was a bit uncertain where the mad driver was heading for. It gave him a passing uneasiness—almost immediately forgotten, however. The pace was too delicious to bring to an end just yet. Presently he would call the fellow to order with a vengeance, but meanwhile—“let her rip!” His friends were all going the same way; it must be all right. His thoughts, he admits, were somewhat mixed; for great speed destroys calm judgment; it exhilarated, but it also bewildered. The pace, assuredly, had something to do with his mental confusion, for it was terrific. Yet he saw on the pavement, from time to time, more friends and acquaintances, and somehow at the moment it did not strike him as too peculiar that they should be there, all moving hurriedly in the same direction. He had an odd feeling that they all knew of some destination agreed upon; that he, too, knew it; but that it was not “playing the game” to admit that he knew. Yet about some of them—their hurried steps, their gay faces, their waving hands—there was a queer fugitive suggestion of sadness, even of fear. One or two touched the source of horror in him even. It hardly surprised him that the horse, steaming and sweating, should start forward with a frightened leap as each figure in turn was sighted and left behind. Probably he was himself too much a part of the wild, exhilarating rush to realize how singular it was. Certainly, it seemed as though some faculty of his mind was suspended during that drive.

But at last, after passing another friend, the horse gave a leap that really frightened him, flinging him against the boards. It was a man, twice his own age, who more than any other had helped him in his evil living, not by doing likewise, but by smothering his first remorse with a smile and a sentence: “Of course, my boy, sow your wild oats! You’ll settle down later. No man is worth his salt who hasn’t sown his wild oats!” He was sliding along—a kind of crawl, with something loathsome in his motion that suggested the reptile. Carlton nodded to him. The same second the horse gave its terrible bound. The whip for the first time slashed down across its flanks. He saw the strip of crêpe, black against the green and sunny landscape. For by now all houses were left behind, and they were rushing at a mad pace along a broad country road, growing momentarily steeper, and—downhill.

At the same moment he caught his own face in the glass. To his utter horror he saw that a black veil, crêpe-like, hung over the upper part, already hiding the eyes, and that it was moving downwards, slowly creeping. The hand of steel turned again within him. He knew that it was Death.

Yet, most singular of all, he instantly found in himself the power to believe it was not there. His hand brushed it off. His face was young, clean, and smiling once more. … And now the hansom flew. The horse was running away; he heard the driver shouting to it, and the shouting sounded like a song. The man was drunk after all. Mingled with his song, too, came a confused murmur of voices behind—far away. What in the world did it all mean? Dashing aside the little curtain he looked back out of the window, and the first thing he saw was a face pressed close against the glass, staring straight into his eyes with a beseeching, pitiful expression. Good God! It was the face of his mother. He swore; the face melted away—and he then saw that the whole country behind him was black, and through it, down the darkened road, ran the figures he had passed. But how changed! The girl was no longer gay and smiling; her face was old, streaked with evil, and with one hand she clutched her heart as she ran—trying in vain to stop. Behind her were the others—worn and broken, with bloodshot eyes and toothless gums, all grinning dreadfully, all racing down the ever-steepening descent, yet all trying frantically to stop. One or two, however, still ran with a brave show as if they wished to; debonair, holding themselves with a certain appearance of dignity and pleasure. And some—the old man of the “wild oats” sentence at their head—were close upon the hansom, pushing it … The face of his mother slid once again upon the glass, between their evil, outstretched hands and himself, but less close, less visible than before. …

Carlton knew a spasm of pain that was terrible. He sat up. He flung open the doors, and his eyes measured the leap. But the faculty of mind that had all the time been in suspension returned a little, and he saw that to jump was—impossible. He smashed the trap open with his fist and cried out, “Stop! I tell you, stop!”

“Can’t stop here, sir,” the driver answered, peering down at him out of the square opening that let in—darkness. “It’s not allowed. It’s not usual, either.”

“Stop, I say,” thundered Carlton, trying to rise and strike him.

But the driver laughed through that square of blackness.

“Can’t be done, sir. You told me ‘same address.’ There’s no stopping now!”

Carlton’s clenched fist was close to the man’s eyes when the fingers grew limp and opened. He sank back upon the seat again. The face peering down upon him was—his own.

And in this supreme moment it was that some secret reserve of soul, hitherto untainted—stirred into life, he declares, by the sight of his mother’s face at the window—rose and offered itself to him. He accepted it. His will moved in its sleep and woke.

“But I say you shall stop!” he cried, catching the reins in both hands, and, when they snapped, seizing the rims, and even the spokes, of the wheels. His great strength acted like a brake. The hansom reeled, shook, then slackened. It was a most curious thing, but the force that twisted his heart with its hand of “ragged steel” seemed to lend him its power. His will moved and gripped; the machinery groaned, but worked. Carlton did nothing by halves; he put his life into his efforts; the skin was torn like paper from his hands. The hansom stopped with a trembling jerk and flung him out upon his face in the mud. And the same second he saw the horse and driver, both torn from their fastenings, whirled past him overhead to disappear into a gulf that yawned dreadfully under his very eyes, blacker than night, deeper than all things. …

And when, at length, he rose to his feet, he found that he was tied with bands of iron to the shafts. Slowly, with vast efforts, groaning and sweating, he turned and began painfully to reclimb the huge and toilsome ascent, dragging the awful weight behind him … towards the Light.

For the glare that suddenly broke through the sky was the sun shine coming through the windows of the hospital room—St. George’s Hospital—where they had carried him when he fainted on the pavement half-an-hour before.

II

CHINESE MAGIC

1

Dr. Owen Francis felt a sudden wave of pleasure and admiration sweep over him as he saw her enter the room. He was in the act of going out; in fact, he had already said good-bye to his hostess, glad to make his escape from the chattering throng, when the tall and graceful young woman glided past him. Her carriage was superb; she had black eyes with a twinkling happiness in them; her mouth was exquisite. Round her neck, in spite of the warm afternoon, she wore a soft thing of fur or feathers; and as she brushed by to shake the hand he had just shaken himself, the tail of this touched his very cheek. Their eyes met fair and square. He felt as though her eyes also touched him.

Changing his mind, he lingered another ten minutes, chatting with various ladies he did not in the least remember, but who remembered him. He did not, of course, desire to exchange banalities with these other ladies, yet did so gallantly enough. If they found him absent-minded they excused him since he was the famous mental specialist whom everybody was proud to know. And all the time his eyes never left the tall graceful figure that allured him almost to the point of casting a spell upon him.

His first impression deepened as he watched. He was aware of excitement, curiosity, longing; there was a touch even of exaltation in him; yet he took no steps to seek the introduction which was easily enough procurable. He checked himself, if with an effort. Several times their eyes met across the crowded room; he dared to believe—he felt instinctively—that his interest was returned. Indeed, it was more than instinct, for she was certainly aware of his presence, and he even caught her indicating him to a woman she spoke with, and evidently asking who he was. Once he half bowed, and once, in spite of himself, he went so far as to smile, and there came, he was sure, a faint, delicious brightening of the eyes in answer. There was, he fancied, a look of yearning in the face. The young woman charmed him inexpressibly; the very way she moved delighted him. Yet at last he slipped out of the room without a word, without an introduction, without even knowing her name. He chose his moment when her back was turned. It was characteristic of him.

For Owen Francis had ever regarded marriage, for himself at least, as a disaster that could be avoided. He was in love with his work, and his work was necessary to humanity. Others might perpetuate the race, but he must heal it. He had come to regard love as the bait wherewith Nature lays her trap to fulfill her own ends. A man in love was a man enjoying a delusion, a deluded man. In his case, and he was nearing forty-five, the theory had worked admirably, and the dangerous exception that proved it had as yet not troubled him.

“It’s come at last—I do believe,” he thought to himself, as he walked home, a new tumultuous emotion in his blood; “the exception, quite possibly, has come at last. I wonder....”

And it seemed he said it to the tall graceful figure by his side, who turned up dark eyes smilingly to meet his own, and whose lips repeated softly his last two words “I wonder....”

The experience, being new to him, was baffling. A part of his nature, long dormant, received the authentic thrill that pertains actually to youth. He was a man of chaste, abstemious custom. The reaction was vehement. That dormant part of him became obstreperous. He thought of his age, his appearance, his prospects; he looked thirty-eight, he was not unhandsome, his position was secure, even remarkable. That gorgeous young woman—he called her gorgeous—haunted him. Never could he forget that face, those eyes. It was extraordinary—he had left her there unspoken to, unknown, when an introduction would have been the simplest thing in the world.

“But it still is,” he replied. And the reflection filled his being with a flood of joy.

He checked himself again. Not so easily is established habit routed. He felt instinctively that, at last, he had met his mate; if he followed it up he was a man in love, a lost man enjoying a delusion, a deluded man. But the way she had looked at him! That air of intuitive invitation which not even the sweetest modesty could conceal! He felt an immense confidence in himself; also he felt oddly sure of her.

The presence of that following figure, already precious, came with him into his house, even into his study at the back where he sat over a number of letters by the open window. The pathetic little London garden showed its pitiful patch. The lilac had faded, but a smell of roses entered. The sun was just behind the buildings opposite, and the garden lay soft and warm in summer shadows.

He read and tossed aside the letters; one only interested him, from Edward Farque, whose journey to China had interrupted a friendship of long standing. Edward Farque’s work on eastern art and philosophy, on Chinese painting and Chinese thought in particular, had made its mark. He was an authority. He was to be back about this time, and his friend smiled with pleasure. “Dear old unpractical dreamer, as I used to call him,” he mused. “He’s a success, anyhow!” And as he mused, the presence that sat beside him came a little closer, yet at the same time faded. Not that he forgot her—that was impossible—but that just before opening the letter from his friend, he had come to a decision. He had definitely made up his mind to seek acquaintance. The reality replaced the remembered substitute.

“As the newspapers may have warned you,” ran the familiar and kinky writing, “I am back in England after what the scribes term my ten years of exile in Cathay. I have taken a little house in Hampstead for six months, and am just settling in. Come to us to-morrow night and let me prove it to you. Come to dinner. We shall have much to say; we both are ten years wiser. You know how glad I shall be to see my old-time critic and disparager, but let me add frankly that I want to ask you a few professional, or, rather, technical, questions. So prepare yourself to come as doctor and as friend. I am writing, as the papers said truthfully, a treatise on Chinese thought. But—don’t shy!—it is about Chinese Magic that I want your technical advice [the last two words were substituted for “professional wisdom,” which had been crossed out] and the benefit of your vast experience. So come, old friend, come quickly, and come hungry! I’ll feed your body as you shall feed my mind.—Yours,
“Edward Farque.”

“P.S.—‘The coming of a friend from a far-off land—is not this true joy?’”

Dr. Francis laid down the letter with a pleased anticipatory chuckle, and it was the touch in the final sentence that amused him. In spite of being an authority, Farque was clearly the same fanciful, poetic dreamer as of old. He quoted Confucius as in other days. The firm but kinky writing had not altered either. The only sign of novelty he noticed was the use of scented paper, for a faint and pungent aroma clung to the big quarto sheet.

“A Chinese habit, doubtless,” he decided, sniffing it with a puzzled air of disapproval. Yet it had nothing in common with the scented sachets some ladies use too lavishly, so that even the air of the street is polluted by their passing for a dozen yards. He was familiar with every kind of perfumed note-paper used in London, Paris, and Constantinople. This one was difficult. It was delicate and penetrating for all its faintness, pleasurable too. He rather liked it, and while annoyed that he could not name it, he sniffed at the letter several times, as though it were a flower.

“I’ll go,” he decided at once, and wrote an acceptance then and there. He went out and posted it. He meant to prolong his walk into the Park, taking his chief preoccupation, the face, the eyes, the figure, with him. Already he was composing the note of inquiry to Mrs. Malleson, his hostess of the tea-party, the note whose willing answer should give him the name, the address, the means of introduction he had now determined to secure. He visualized that note of inquiry, seeing it in his mind’s eye; only, for some odd reason, he saw the kinky writing of Farque instead of his own more elegant script. Association of ideas and emotions readily explained this. Two new and unexpected interests had entered his life on the same day, and within half an hour of each other. What he could not so readily explain, however, was that two words in his friend’s ridiculous letter, and in that kinky writing, stood out sharply from the rest. As he slipped his envelope into the mouth of the red pillar-box they shone vividly in his mind. These two words were “Chinese Magic.”

2

It was the warmth of his friend’s invitation as much as his own state of inward excitement that decided him suddenly to anticipate his visit by twenty-four hours. It would clear his judgment and help his mind, if he spent the evening at Hampstead rather than alone with his own thoughts. “A dose of China,” he thought, with a smile, “will do me good. Edward won’t mind. I’ll telephone.”

He left the Park soon after six o’clock and acted upon his impulse. The connexion was bad, the wire buzzed and popped and crackled; talk was difficult; he did not hear properly. The Professor had not yet come in, apparently. Francis said he would come up anyhow on the chance.

“Velly pleased,” said the voice in his ear, as he rang off.

Going into his study, he drafted the note that should result in the introduction that was now, it appeared, the chief object of his life. The way this woman with the black, twinkling eyes obsessed him was—he admitted it with joy—extraordinary. The draft he put in his pocket, intending to re-write it next morning, and all the way up to Hampstead Heath the gracious figure glided silently beside him, the eyes were ever present, his cheek still glowed where the feather boa had touched his skin. Edward Farque remained in the background. In fact, it was on the very door-step, having rung the bell, that Francis realized he must pull himself together. “I’ve come to see old Farque,” he reminded himself, with a smile. “I’ve got to be interested in him and his, and, probably, for an hour or two, to talk Chinese——” when the door opened noiselessly, and he saw facing him, with a grin of celestial welcome on his yellow face, a China-man.

“Oh!” he said, with a start. He had not expected a Chinese servant.

“Velly pleased,” the man bowed him in.

Dr. Francis stared round him with astonishment he could not conceal. A great golden idol faced him in the hall, its gleaming visage blazing out of a sort of miniature golden palanquin, with a grin, half dignified, half cruel. Fully double human size, it blocked the way, looking so life-like that it might have moved to meet him without too great a shock to what seemed possible. It rested on a throne with four massive legs, carved, the doctor saw, with serpents, dragons, and mythical monsters generally. Round it on every side were other things in keeping. Name them he could not, describe them he did not try. He summed them up in one word—China: pictures, weapons, cloths and tapestries, bells, gongs, and figures of every sort and kind imaginable.

Being ignorant of Chinese matters, Dr. Francis stood and looked about him in a mental state of some confusion. He had the feeling that he had entered a Chinese temple, for there was a faint smell of incense hanging about the house that was, to say the least, un-English. Nothing English, in fact, was visible at all. The matting on the floor, the swinging curtains of bamboo beads that replaced the customary doors, the silk draperies and pictured cushions, the bronze and ivory, the screens hung with fantastic embroideries, everything was Chinese. Hampstead vanished from his thoughts. The very lamps were in keeping, the ancient lacquered furniture as well. The value of what he saw, an expert could have told him, was considerable.

“You likee?” queried the voice at his side.

He had forgotten the servant. He turned sharply.

“Very much; it’s wonderfully done,” he said. “Makes you feel at home, John, eh?” he added tactfully, with a smile, and was going to ask how long all this preparation had taken, when a voice sounded on the stairs beyond. It was a voice he knew, a note of hearty welcome in its deep notes.

“The coming of a friend from a far-off land, even from Harley Street—is not this true joy?” he heard, and the next minute was shaking the hand of his old and valued friend. The intimacy between them had always been of the truest.

“I almost expected a pigtail,” observed Francis, looking him affectionately up and down, “but, really—why, you’ve hardly changed at all!”

“Outwardly, not as much, perhaps, as Time expects,” was the happy reply, “but inwardly——!” He scanned appreciatively the burly figure of the doctor in his turn. “And I can say the same of you,” he declared, still holding his hand tight. “This is a real pleasure, Owen,” he went on in his deep voice, “to see you again is a joy to me. Old friends meeting again—there’s nothing like it in life, I believe, nothing.” He gave the hand another squeeze before he let it go. “And we,” he added, leading the way into a room across the hall, “neither of us is a fugitive from life. We take what we can, I mean.”

The doctor smiled as he noted the un-English turn of language, and together they entered a sitting-room that was, again, more like some inner chamber of a Chinese temple than a back room in a rented Hampstead house.

“I only knew ten minutes ago that you were coming, my dear fellow,” the scholar was saying, as his friend gazed round him with increased astonishment, “or I would have prepared more suitably for your reception. I was out till late. All this”—he waved his hand—“surprises you, of course, but the fact is I have been home some days already, and most of what you see was arranged for me in advance of my arrival. Hence its apparent completion. I say ‘apparent,’ because, actually, it is far from faithfully carried out. Yet to exceed,” he added, “is as bad as to fall short.”

The doctor watched him while he listened to a somewhat lengthy explanation of the various articles surrounding them. The speaker—he confirmed his first impression—had changed little during the long interval; the same enthusiasm was in him as before, the same fire and dreaminess alternately in the fine grey eyes, the same humour and passion about the mouth, the same free gestures, and the same big voice. Only the lines had deepened on the forehead, and on the fine face the air of thoughtfulness was also deeper. It was Edward Farque as of old, scholar, poet, dreamer and enthusiast, despiser of western civilization, contemptuous of money, generous and upright, a type of value, an individual.

“You’ve done well, done splendidly, Edward, old man,” said his friend presently, after hearing of Chinese wonders that took him somewhat beyond his depth perhaps. “No one is more pleased than I. I’ve watched your books. You haven’t regretted England, I’ll be bound?” he asked.

“The philosopher has no country, in any case,” was the reply, steadily given. “But out there, I confess, I’ve found my home.” He leaned forward, a deeper earnestness in his tone and expression. And into his face, as he spoke, came a glow of happiness. “My heart,” he said, “is in China.”

“I see it is, I see it is,” put in the other, conscious that he could not honestly share his friend’s enthusiasm. “And you’re fortunate to be free to live where your treasure is,” he added after a moment’s pause. “You must be a happy man. Your passion amounts to nostalgia, I suspect. Already yearning to get back there, probably?”

Farque gazed at him for some seconds with shining eyes. “You remember the Persian saying, I’m sure,” he said. “‘You see a man drink, but you do not see his thirst.’ Well,” he added, laughing happily, “you may see me off in six months’ time, but you will not see my happiness.”

While he went on talking, the doctor glanced round the room, marvelling still at the exquisite taste of everything, the neat arrangement, the perfect matching of form and colour. A woman might have done this thing, occurred to him, as the haunting figure shifted deliciously into the foreground of his mind again. The thought of her had been momentarily replaced by all he heard and saw. She now returned, filling him with joy, anticipation and enthusiasm. Presently, when it was his turn to talk, he would tell his friend about this new, unimagined happiness that had burst upon him like a sunrise. Presently, but not just yet. He remembered, too, with a passing twinge of possible boredom to come, that there must be some delay before his own heart could unburden itself in its turn. Farque wanted to ask some professional questions, of course. He had for the moment forgotten that part of the letter in his general interest and astonishment.

“Happiness, yes....” he murmured, aware that his thoughts had wandered, and catching at the last word he remembered hearing. “As you said just now in your own queer way—you haven’t changed a bit, let me tell you, in your picturesqueness of quotation, Edward—one must not be fugitive from life; one must seize happiness when and where it offers.”

He said it lightly enough, hugging internally his own sweet secret; but he was a little surprised at the earnestness of his friend’s rejoinder: “Both of us, I see,” came the deep voice, backed by the flash of the far-seeing grey eyes, “have made some progress in the doctrine of life and death.” He paused, gazing at the other with sight that was obviously turned inwards upon his own thoughts. “Beauty,” he went on presently, his tone even more serious, “has been my lure; yours, Reality....”

“You don’t flatter either of us, Edward. That’s too exclusive a statement,” put in the doctor. He was becoming every minute more and more interested in the workings of his friend’s mind. Something about the signs offered eluded his understanding. “Explain yourself, old scholar-poet. I’m a dull, practical mind, remember, and can’t keep pace with Chinese subtleties.”

“You’ve left out Beauty,” was the quiet rejoinder, “while I left out Reality. That’s neither Chinese nor subtle. It is simply true.”

“A bit wholesale, isn’t it?” laughed Francis. “A big generalization, rather.”

A bright light seemed to illuminate the scholar’s face. It was as though an inner lamp was suddenly lit. At the same moment the sound of a soft gong floated in from the hall outside, so soft that the actual strokes were not distinguishable in the wave of musical vibration that reached the ear.

Farque rose to lead the way in to dinner.

“What if I——” he whispered, “have combined the two?” And upon his face was a look of joy that reached down into the other’s own full heart with its unexpectedness and wonder. It was the last remark in the world he had looked for. He wondered for a moment whether he interpreted it correctly.

“By Jove...!” he exclaimed. “Edward, what d’you mean?”

“You shall hear—after dinner,” said Farque, his voice mysterious, his eyes still shining with his inner joy. “I told you I have some questions to ask you—professionally.” And they took their seats round an ancient, marvellous table, lit by two swinging lamps of soft green jade, while the Chinese servant waited on them with the silent movements and deft neatness of his imperturbable celestial race.

3

To say that he was bored during the meal were an over-statement of Dr. Francis’s mental condition, but to say that he was half-bored seemed the literal truth; for one-half of him, while he ate his steak and savoury and watched Farque manipulating chou chop suey and chou om dong most cleverly with chop-sticks, was too pre-occupied with his own romance to allow the other half to give its full attention to the conversation.

He had entered the room, however, with a distinct quickening of what may be termed his instinctive and infallible sense of diagnosis. That last remark of his friend’s had stimulated him. He was aware of surprise, curiosity, and impatience. Willy-nilly, he began automatically to study him with a profounder interest. Something, he gathered, was not quite as it should be in Edward Farque’s mental composition. There was what might be called an elusive emotional disturbance. He began to wonder and to watch.

They talked, naturally, of China and of things Chinese, for the scholar responded to little else, and Francis listened with what sympathy and patience he could muster. Of art and beauty he had hitherto known little, his mind was practical and utilitarian. He now learned that all art was derived from China, where a high, fine, subtle culture had reigned since time immemorial. Older than Egypt was their wisdom. When the western races were eating one another, before Greece was even heard of, the Chinese had reached a level of knowledge and achievement that few realized. Never had they, even in earliest times, been deluded by anthropomorphic conceptions of the Deity, but perceived in everything the expressions of a single whole whose giant activities they reverently worshipped. Their contempt for the western scurry after knowledge, wealth, machinery, was justified, if Farque was worthy of belief. He seemed saturated with Chinese thought, art, philosophy, and his natural bias towards the celestial race had hardened into an attitude to life that had now become ineradicable.

“They deal, as it were, in essences,” he declared; “they discern the essence of everything, leaving out the superfluous, the unessential, the trivial. Their pictures alone prove it. Come with me,” he concluded, “and see the ‘Earthly Paradise,’ now in the British Museum. It is like Botticelli, but better than anything Botticelli ever did. It was painted”—he paused for emphasis—“600 years B.C.”

The wonder of this quiet, ancient civilization, a sense of its depth, its wisdom, grew upon his listener as the enthusiastic poet described its charm and influence upon himself. He willingly allowed the enchantment of the other’s Paradise to steal upon his own awakened heart. There was a good deal Francis might have offered by way of criticism and objection, but he preferred on the whole to keep his own views to himself, and to let his friend wander unhindered through the mazes of his passionate evocation. All men, he well knew, needed a dream to carry them through life’s disappointments, a dream that they could enter at will and find peace, contentment, happiness. Farque’s dream was China. Why not? It was as good as another, and a man like Farque was entitled to what dream he pleased.

“And their women?” he inquired at last, letting both halves of his mind speak together for the first time.

But he was not prepared for the expression that leaped upon his friend’s face at the simple question. Nor for his method of reply. It was no reply, in point of fact. It was simply an attack upon all other types of woman, and upon the white, the English, in particular—their emptiness, their triviality, their want of intuitive imagination, of spiritual grace, of everything, in a word, that should constitute woman a meet companion for man, and a little higher than the angels into the bargain. The doctor listened spellbound. Too humorous to be shocked, he was, at any rate, disturbed by what he heard, displeased a little, too. It threatened too directly his own new tender dream.

Only with the utmost self-restraint did he keep his temper under, and prevent hot words he would have regretted later from tearing his friend’s absurd claim into ragged shreds. He was wounded personally as well. Never now could he bring himself to tell his own secret to him. The outburst chilled and disappointed him. But it had another effect—it cooled his judgment. His sense of diagnosis quickened. He divined an id�e fixe, a mania possibly. His interest deepened abruptly. He watched. He began to look about him with more wary eyes, and a sense of uneasiness, once the anger passed, stirred in his friendly and affectionate heart.

They had been sitting alone over their port for some considerable time, the servant having long since left the room. The doctor had sought to change the subject many times without much success, when suddenly Farque changed it for him.

“Now,” he announced, “I’ll tell you something,” and Francis guessed that the professional questions were on the way at last. “We must pity the living, remember, and part with the dead. Have you forgotten old Shan-Yu?”

The forgotten name came back to him, the picturesque East End dealer of many years ago. “The old merchant who taught you your first Chinese? I do recall him dimly; now you mention it. You made quite a friend of him, didn’t you? He thought very highly of you—ah, it comes back to me now—he offered something or other very wonderful in his gratitude, unless my memory fails me?”

“His most valuable possession,” Farque went on, a strange look deepening on his face, an expression of mysterious rapture, as it were, and one that Francis recognized and swiftly pigeon-holed in his now attentive mind.

“Which was?” he asked sympathetically. “You told me once, but so long ago that really it’s slipped my mind. Something magical, wasn’t it?” He watched closely for his friend’s reply.

Farque lowered his voice to a whisper almost devotional:

“The Perfume of the Garden of Happiness,” he murmured, with an expression in his eyes as though the mere recollection gave him joy. “‘Burn it,’ he told me, ‘in a brazier; then inhale. You will enter the Valley of a Thousand Temples wherein lies the Garden of Happiness, and there you will meet your Love. You will have seven years of happiness with your Love before the Waters of Separation flow between you. I give this to you who alone of men here have appreciated the wisdom of my land. Follow my body towards the Sunrise. You, an eastern soul in a barbarian body, will meet your Destiny.’”

The doctor’s attention, such is the power of self-interest, quickened amazingly as he heard. His own romance flamed up with power. His friend—it dawned upon him suddenly—loved a woman.

“Come,” said Farque, rising quietly, “we will go into the other room, and I will show you what I have shown to but one other in the world before. You are a doctor,” he continued, as he led the way to the silk-covered divan where golden dragons swallowed crimson suns, and wonderful jade horses hovered near. “You understand the mind and nerves. States of consciousness you also can explain, and the effect of drugs is, doubtless, known to you.” He swung to the heavy curtains that took the place of door, handed a lacquered box of cigarettes to his friend, and lit one himself. “Perfumes, too,” he added, “you probably have studied, with their extraordinary evocative power.” He stood in the middle of the room, the green light falling on his interesting and thoughtful face, and for a passing second Francis, watching keenly, observed a change flit over it and vanish. The eyes grew narrow and slid tilted upwards, the skin wore a shade of yellow underneath the green from the lamp of jade, the nose slipped back a little, the cheek-bones forward.

“Perfumes,” said the doctor, “no. Of perfumes I know nothing, beyond their interesting effect upon the memory. I cannot help you there. But, you, I suspect,” and he looked up with an inviting sympathy that concealed the close observation underneath, “you yourself, I feel sure, can tell me something of value about them?”

“Perhaps,” was the calm reply, “perhaps, for I have smelt the perfume of the Garden of Happiness, and I have been in the Valley of a Thousand Temples.” He spoke with a glow of joy and reverence almost devotional.

The doctor waited in some suspense, while his friend moved towards an inlaid cabinet across the room. More than broad-minded, he was that much rarer thing, an open-minded man, ready at a moment’s notice to discard all preconceived ideas, provided new knowledge that necessitated the holocaust were shown to him. At present, none the less, he held very definite views of his own. “Please ask me any questions you like,” he added. “All I know is entirely yours, as always.” He was aware of suppressed excitement in his friend that betrayed itself in every word and look and gesture, an excitement intense, and not as yet explained by anything he had seen or heard.

The scholar, meanwhile, had opened a drawer in the cabinet and taken from it a neat little packet tied up with purple silk. He held it with tender, almost loving care, as he came and sat down on the divan beside his friend.

“This,” he said, in a tone, again, of something between reverence and worship, “contains what I have to show you first.” He slowly unrolled it, disclosing a yet smaller silken bag within, coloured a deep rich orange. There were two vertical columns of writing on it, painted in Chinese characters. The doctor leaned forward to examine them. His friend translated:

“The Perfume of the Garden of Happiness,” he read aloud, tracing the letters of the first column with his finger. “The Destroyer of Honourable Homes,” he finished, passing to the second, and then proceeded to unwrap the little silken bag. Before it was actually open, however, and the pale shredded material resembling coloured chaff visible to the eyes, the doctor’s nostrils had recognized the strange aroma he had first noticed about his friend’s letter received earlier in the day. The same soft, penetrating odour, sharply piercing, sweet and delicate, rose to his brain. It stirred at once a deep emotional pleasure in him. Having come to him first when he was aglow with his own unexpected romance, his mind and heart full of the woman he had just left, that delicious, torturing state revived in him quite naturally. The evocative power of perfume with regard to memory is compelling. A livelier sympathy towards his friend, and towards what he was about to hear, awoke in him spontaneously.

He did not mention the letter, however. He merely leaned over to smell the fragrant perfume more easily.

Farque drew back the open packet instantly, at the same time holding out a warning hand. “Careful,” he said gravely, “be careful, my old friend—unless you desire to share the rapture and the risk that have been mine. To enjoy its full effect, true, this dust must be burned in a brazier and its smoke inhaled; but even sniffed, as you now would sniff it, and you are in danger——”

“Of what?” asked Francis, impressed by the other’s extraordinary intensity of voice and manner.

“Of Heaven; but, possibly, of Heaven before your time.”

4

The tale that Farque unfolded then had certainly a strange celestial flavour, a glory not of this dull world; and as his friend listened, his interest deepened with every minute, while his bewilderment increased. He watched closely, expert that he was, for clues that might guide his deductions aright, but for all his keen observation and experience he could detect no inconsistency, no weakness, nothing that betrayed the smallest mental aberration. The origin and nature of what he already decided was an id�e fixe, a mania, evaded him entirely. This evasion piqued and vexed him; he had heard a thousand tales of similar type before; that this one in particular should baffle his unusual skill touched his pride. Yet he faced the position honestly, he confessed himself baffled until the end of the evening. When he went away, however, he went away satisfied, even forgetful—because a new problem of yet more poignant interest had replaced the first.

“It was after three years out there,” said Farque, “that a sense of my loneliness first came upon me. It came upon me bitterly. My work had not then been recognized; obstacles and difficulties had increased; I felt a failure; I had accomplished nothing. And it seemed to me I had misjudged my capacities, taken a wrong direction, and wasted my life accordingly. For my move to China, remember, was a radical move, and my boats were burnt behind me. This sense of loneliness was really devastating.”

Francis, already fidgeting, put up his hand.

“One question, if I may,” he said, “and I’ll not interrupt again.”

“By all means,” said the other patiently, “what is it?”

“Were you—we are such old friends”—he apologized—“were you still celibate as ever?”

Farque looked surprised, then smiled. “My habits had not changed,” he replied, “I was, as always, celibate.”

“Ah!” murmured the doctor, and settled down to listen.

“And I think now,” his friend went on, “that it was the lack of companionship that first turned my thoughts towards conscious disappointment. However that may be, it was one evening, as I walked homewards to my little house, that I caught my imagination lingering upon English memories, though chiefly, I admit, upon my old Chinese tutor, the dead Shan-Yu.

“It was dusk, the stars were coming out in the pale evening air, and the orchards, as I passed them, stood like wavering ghosts of unbelievable beauty. The effect of thousands upon thousands of these trees, flooding the twilight of a spring evening with their sea of blossom, is almost unearthly. They seem transparencies, their colour hangs sheets upon the very sky. I crossed a small wooden bridge that joined two of these orchards above a stream, and in the dark water I watched a moment the mingled reflection of stars and flowering branches on the quiet surface. It seemed too exquisite to belong to earth, this fairy garden of stars and blossoms, shining faintly in the crystal depths, and my thought, as I gazed, dived suddenly down the little avenue that memory opened into former days. I remembered Shan-Yu’s present, given to me when he died. His very words came back to me: The Garden of Happiness in the Valley of the Thousand Temples, with its promise of love, of seven years of happiness, and the prophecy that I should follow his body towards the Sunrise and meet my destiny.

“This memory I took home with me into my lonely little one-storey house upon the hill. My servants did not sleep there. There was no one near. I sat by the open window with my thoughts, and you may easily guess that before very long I had unearthed the long-forgotten packet from among my things, spread a portion of its contents on a metal tray above a lighted brazier, and was comfortably seated before it, inhaling the light blue smoke with its exquisite and fragrant perfume.

“A light air entered through the window, the distant orchards below me trembled, rose and floated through the dusk, and I found myself, almost at once, in a pavilion of flowers; a blue river lay shining in the sun before me, as it wandered through a lovely valley where I saw groves of flowering trees among a thousand scattered temples. Drenched in light and colour, the Valley lay dreaming amid a peaceful loveliness that woke what seemed impossible, unrealizable, longings in my heart. I yearned towards its groves and temples, I would bathe my soul in that flood of tender light, and my body in the blue coolness of that winding river. In a thousand temples must I worship. Yet these impossible yearnings instantly were satisfied. I found myself there at once ... and the time that passed over my head you may reckon in centuries, if not in ages. I was in the Garden of Happiness and its marvellous perfume banished time and sorrow, there was no end to chill the soul, nor any beginning, which is its foolish counterpart.

“Nor was there loneliness.” The speaker clasped his thin hands, and closed his eyes a moment in what was evidently an ecstasy of the sweetest memory man may ever know. A slight trembling ran through his frame, communicating itself to his friend upon the divan beside him—this understanding, listening, sympathetic friend, whose eyes had never once yet withdrawn their attentive gaze from the narrator’s face.

“I was not alone,” the scholar resumed, opening his eyes again, and smiling out of some deep inner joy. “Shan-Yu came down the steps of the first temple and took my hand, while the great golden figures in the dim interior turned their splendid shining heads to watch. Then, breathing the soul of his ancient wisdom in my ear, he led me through all the perfumed ways of that enchanted garden, worshipping with me at a hundred deathless shrines, led me, I tell you, to the sound of soft gongs and gentle bells, by fragrant groves and sparkling streams, mid a million gorgeous flowers, until, beneath that unsetting sun, we reached the heart of the Valley, where the source of the river gushed forth beneath the lighted mountains. He stopped and pointed across the narrow waters. I saw the woman——”

“The woman,” his listener murmured beneath his breath, though Farque seemed unaware of interruption.

“She smiled at me and held her hands out, and while she did so, even before I could express my joy and wonder in response, Shan-Yu, I saw, had crossed the narrow stream and stood beside her. I made to follow then, my heart burning with inexpressible delight. But Shan-Yu held up his hand, as they began to move down the flowered bank together, making a sign that I should keep pace with them, though on my own side.

“Thus, side by side, yet with the blue sparkling stream between us, we followed back along its winding course, through the heart of that enchanted valley, my hands stretched out towards the radiant figure of my Love, and hers stretched out towards me. They did not touch, but our eyes, our smiles, our thoughts, these met and mingled in a sweet union of unimagined bliss, so that the absence of physical contact was unnoticed and laid no injury on our marvellous joy. It was a spirit union, and our kiss a spirit kiss. Therein lay the subtlety and glory of the Chinese wonder, for it was our essences that met, and for such union there is no satiety and, equally, no possible end. The Perfume of the Garden of Happiness is an essence. We were in Eternity.

“The stream, meanwhile, widened between us, and as it widened, my Love grew farther from me in space, smaller, less visibly defined, yet ever essentially more perfect, and never once with a sense of distance that made our union less divinely close. Across the widening reaches of blue, sunlit water I still knew her smile, her eyes, the gestures of her radiant being; I saw her exquisite reflection in the stream; and, mid the music of those soft gongs and gentle bells, the voice of Shan-Yu came like a melody to my ears:

“‘You have followed me into the sunrise, and have found your destiny. Behold now your Love. In this Valley of a Thousand Temples you have known the Garden of Happiness, and its Perfume your soul now inhales.’

“‘I am bathed,’ I answered, ‘in a happiness divine. It is forever.’

“‘The Waters of Separation,’ his answer floated like a bell, ‘lie widening between you.’

“I moved nearer to the bank, impelled by the pain in his words to take my Love and hold her to my breast.

“‘But I would cross to her,’ I cried, and saw that, as I moved, Shan-Yu and my Love came likewise closer to the water’s edge across the widening river. They both obeyed, I was aware, my slightest wish.

“‘Seven years of Happiness you may know,’ sang his gentle tones across the brimming flood, ‘if you would cross to her. Yet the Destroyer of Honourable Homes lies in the shadows that you must cast outside.’

“I heard his words, I noticed for the first time that in the blaze of this radiant sunshine we cast no shadows on the sea of flowers at our feet, and—I stretched out my arms towards my Love across the river.

“‘I accept my destiny,’ I cried, ‘I will have my seven years of bliss,’ and stepped forward into the running flood. As the cool water took my feet, my Love’s hands stretched out both to hold me and to bid me stay. There was acceptance in her gesture, but there was warning too.

“I did not falter. I advanced until the water bathed my knees, and my Love, too, came to meet me, the stream already to her waist, while our arms stretched forth above the running flood towards each other.

“The change came suddenly. Shan-Yu first faded behind her advancing figure into air; there stole a chill upon the sunlight; a cool mist rose from the water, hiding the Garden and the hills beyond; our fingers touched, I gazed into her eyes, our lips lay level with the water—and the room was dark and cold about me. The brazier stood extinguished at my side. The dust had burnt out, and no smoke rose. I slowly left my chair and closed the window, for the air was chill.”

5

It was difficult at first to return to Hampstead and the details of ordinary life about him. Francis looked round him slowly, freeing himself gradually from the spell his friend’s words had laid even upon his analytical temperament. The transition was helped, however, by the details that everywhere met his eye. The Chinese atmosphere remained. More, its effect had gained, if anything. The embroideries of yellow gold, the pictures, the lacquered stools and inlaid cabinets, above all, the exquisite figures in green jade upon the shelf beside him, all this, in the shimmering pale olive light the lamps shed everywhere, helped his puzzled mind to bridge the gulf from the Garden of Happiness into the decorated villa upon Hampstead Heath.

There was silence between the two men for several minutes. Far was it from the doctor’s desire to injure his old friend’s delightful fantasy. For he called it fantasy, although something in him trembled. He remained, therefore, silent. Truth to tell, perhaps, he knew not exactly what to say.

Farque broke the silence himself. He had not moved since the story ended; he sat motionless, his hands tightly clasped, his eyes alight with the memory of his strange imagined joy, his face rapt and almost luminous, as though he still wandered through the groves of the Enchanted Garden and inhaled the perfume of its perfect happiness in the Valley of the Thousand Temples.

“It was two days later,” he went on suddenly in his quiet voice, “only two days afterwards, that I met her.”

“You met her? You met the woman of your dream?” Francis’s eyes opened very wide.

“In that little harbour town,” repeated Farque calmly, “I met her in the flesh. She had just landed in a steamer from up the coast. The details are of no particular interest. She knew me, of course, at once. And, naturally, I knew her.”

The doctor’s tongue refused to act as he heard. It dawned upon him suddenly that his friend was married. He remembered the woman’s touch about the house; he recalled, too, for the first time that the letter of invitation to dinner had said “come to us.” He was full of a bewildered astonishment.

The reaction upon himself was odd, perhaps, yet wholly natural. His heart warmed towards his imaginative friend. He could now tell him his own new strange romance. The woman who haunted him crept back into the room and sat between them. He found his tongue.

“You married her, Edward?” he exclaimed.

“She is my wife,” was the reply, in a gentle, happy voice.

“A Ch——” he could not bring himself to say the word. “A foreigner?”

“My wife is a Chinese woman,” Farque helped him easily, with a delighted smile.

So great was the other’s absorption in the actual moment, that he had not heard the step in the passage that his host had heard. The latter stood up suddenly.

“I hear her now,” he said. “I’m glad she’s come back before you left.” He stepped towards the door.

But before he reached it, the door was opened and in came the woman herself. Francis tried to rise, but something had happened to him. His heart missed a beat. Something, it seemed, broke in him. He faced a tall, graceful young English woman with black eyes of sparkling happiness, the woman of his own romance. She still wore the feather boa round her neck. She was no more Chinese than he was.

“My wife,” he heard Farque introducing them, as he struggled to his feet, searching feverishly for words of congratulation, normal, everyday words he ought to use, “I’m so pleased, oh, so pleased,” Farque was saying—he heard the sound from a distance, his sight was blurred as well—“my two best friends in the world, my English comrade and my Chinese wife.” His voice was absolutely sincere with conviction and belief.

“But we have already met,” came the woman’s delightful voice, her eyes full upon his face with smiling pleasure, “I saw you at Mrs. Malleson’s tea only this afternoon.”

And Francis remembered suddenly that the Mallesons were old acquaintances of Farque’s as well as of himself. “And I even dared to ask who you were,” the voice went on, floating from some other space, it seemed, to his ears, “I had you pointed out to me. I had heard of you from Edward, of course. But you vanished before I could be introduced.”

The doctor mumbled something or other polite and, he hoped, adequate. But the truth had flashed upon him with remorseless suddenness. She had “heard of” him—the famous mental specialist. Her interest in him was cruelly explained, cruelly both for himself and for his friend. Farque’s delusion lay clear before his eyes. An awakening to reality might involve dislocation of the mind. She, too, moreover, knew the truth. She was involved as well. And her interest in himself was—consultation.

“Seven years we’ve been married, just seven years to-day,” Farque was saying thoughtfully, as he looked at them. “Curious, rather, isn’t it?”

“Very,” said Francis, turning his regard from the black eyes to the grey.

Thus it was that Owen Francis left the house a little later with a mind in a measure satisfied, yet in a measure forgetful too—forgetful of his own deep problem, because another of even greater interest had replaced it.

“Why undeceive him?” ran his thought. “He need never know. It’s harmless anyhow—I can tell her that.”

But, side by side with this reflection, ran another that was oddly haunting, considering his type of mind: “Destroyer of Honourable Homes,” was the form of words it took. And with a sigh he added “Chinese Magic.”

Christmas in England

Of late years, when there has scarcely been enough snow on the ground at Christmas-time to give the country even a seasonable appearance, it has seemed almost a mockery to continue to celebrate the same old customs and to perform the same ceremonies that are connected from time immemorial in the minds of the English people with a winter sky and landscape, which, in the days of our forefathers, were so rarely absent at this season of the year. However this may be, the customs always associated with an old- fashioned Christmas-tide are still practised to a great extent; the piled-up wood fires still crackle and burn as brightly as ever in the ample old grates, and the stout-legged oaken tables still support as tender roast beef and as tasty and indigestible a plum-pudding as they ever did in days of yore.

In England Christmas is a universal holiday. In the cities the banks are closed; offices are deserted. The stores in the towns and villages are all shut, and while the morning of Christmas-day is in every respect treated as a Sunday, the latter part of the day is given up to whatever out-door amusements the state of the weather may render suitable; the evening sees the assembly of joyous parties and friendly gatherings, which last into the small hours of the morning, and are looked forward to by the younger portion of the community with an eagerness which the passing years tend rather to increase than to diminish.

But to see Christmas as it is really kept by the people we must leave the cities and dive deep into the heart of the country; we must mingle with the crowd that at the festive season enters the gates of the squire's hospitable mansion, or in the long low rooms of the old farm-houses. The real beginning of the festivities is on Christmas-eve, when the large parties meet their friends from far and near round the festive board. Then the time passes right merrily.

The village inn represented in the sketch below, sending its ruddy glow through its lattice windows, across the snow, and with its well-known sign—say the "Red Lion"—hanging above the door, will reap a considerable harvest; and a jovial gathering of big-boned labourers and hardy rustics, with the host himself, portly and rubicund, in their midst, will make the blackened rafters ring again with song and joke as the night wears on. There we shall hear many an odd conceit or quaint superstition which the season of the yule-log and the holly-berry again brings round to their memories. As they sit and talk over their tankards they care very little for anything else but the fact that "Ye goode old Chrismasse-tide " has come again. It matters little to them that the actual Christmas-day was not even fixed on the 25th December until the fourth century. They are prepared to celebrate the day as it is, and be merry, come what may.

As hinted before, superstition of the most absurd kind is everywhere rife at this season, and few persons who have not spent Christmas among the people in the country villages can have any idea of the extent to which it prevails. In his "English Country Life," Thos. Miller tells us how he incurred the displeasure of a relative by breaking through a rule which a certain superstition had made necessary. He says: "To give a person a light between Christmas and Twelfth Night is to bring upon yourself ill -fortune all that year. I recollect well losing the good-will of my old grandmother by allowing a benighted waggoner to light his lanthorn while her back was turned, and it was many a week before the old lady forgave me."

In the olden days our ancestors used to keep the merry season in much the same way, but during the Middle Ages a custom prevailed which has since lost its character, if it has not altogether died out. Thus, in the larger towns were performed certain mysteries-dramatic representations- in which the players wore grotesque dresses and masks. These were celebrated with great pomp and ceremony, and the country people flocked from far and near to witness them. The only custom which bears any resemblance to these, and which is only found now in certain parts of the midland counties, is called the " December Liberties," or the feast of fools and asses, which is described as "grotesque saturnalia, in which everthing serious was ridiculed." Whole villages would turn out to dance, carrying torches and evergreens, casting weird shadows on the glistening snow.

Within doors the houses at Christmas-time are very cheerful and bright. On the wide stone hearth a yule-log burns, briskly casting a ruddy glow on everything around, while the walls and pictures are decorated with holly, ivy, and several bunches of mistletoe hung up in obvious places for equally obvious reasons. These decorations are usually kept up until Twelfth Night or old Christmas-day. At this season , too, there is a plant called rosemary, which flowers about Christmas-time. It was held in high repute by our ancestors, though the purposes for which they used it have now ceased to be noticed. They held high holiday from Christmas-day until Candlemas (February 2nd ), and their first feast was the occasion of bringing in the head of the wild boar,

" Upon a silver platter with minstrelsye. "

Then, once the great tankards had been filled , it was the custom to stir the foaming potations with twigs of rosemary. It was also considered auspicious to use it on two other occasions of a very opposite nature, namely, a wedding and a burial. Boughs of the plant were carried before the bride or laid on the grave, as the occasion called for, and referring to this old custom in his " Hesperides," Herrick says that the rosemary plant

"Grows for two ends; it matters not at all
Be it for my bridal or my burial."

It is only right that churches, which were built to the honour of Him whose birth we celebrate at this season, should be as brightly decorated as they are; and in the little country church there is sure to be a full congregation, from the squire, who is not so regular in his attendance, perhaps, as he might be, during the year, to the oldest peasant, who unearths from its year-long grave an ancient beaver hat, from which the silken gloss has long since fled, and which he dons in honour of the day.

Should it ever fall to the lot of a stranger to be walking through the country lanes near midnight on Christmas-eve, he will be startled to hear, on the last stroke of twelve, the iron clang of the church bells far and near ring out the best chimes of which they are capable, and from Land's End to John o' Groats not a church tower that possesses bells will be silent. When these cease the waits begin their rounds, and going from house to house, and village to village, they sing carols and Christmas hymns `until the light begins to glimmer in the eastern sky and another Christmas-day has dawned.

The custom of singing carols at Christmas-time may be traced back through many a long century. In the classic city of Oxford, the stronghold of ancient customs and ancient opinions, Christmas has been celebrated for centuries with much of the pomp and pageantry of the Middle Ages. The procession song of the Boar's Head, the " Gaudeamus Omnes," the singing of the surpliced choir in the college chapel (as shown in our frontispiece ), are still observed as in scarce any place else. And in the Bodleian Library may still be seen one of the oldest collections of carols known to exist. The volume, of which only a few pages remain, was printed in the year 1521, by Wynkin de Worde, and is entitled "Chrismasse Carolles." For some reason Oxford is particularly favourable to the laurel, and as a decorative evergreen in the chapels of the different colleges, it is used to the entire displacement of holly or ivy.

There are many other customs in the large cities, and oldfashioned traditions in the country, still preserved in many parts of England, which limit of space forbids us to mention; and though some of these may have already died out and others are now gradually becoming extinct as the years roll on, we are sure of one thing, namely, that England will ever be the home of Christmas gatherings and rejoicings of some sort; and if the old-time pastimes and quaint old ceremonies are giving way to others of a different sort, let us hope that the English people will ever thankfully remember, in their mirth and Christmas celebrations, the occasion when He who made such happiness possible, and who has made us, as a nation , what we are, was born in a stable and cradled in a manger.

Sound over all waters, reach out from all lands,
The chorus of voices, the clasping of hands,
Sing hymns that were sung by the stars of the morn ,
Sing songs of the angels when Jesus was born !

—Whittier.

Clairvoyance

In the darkest corner, where the firelight could not reach him, he sat listening to the stories. His young hostess occupied the corner on the other side; she was also screened by shadows; and between them stretched the horseshoe of eager, frightened faces that seemed all eyes. Behind yawned the blackness of the big room, running as it were without a break into the night.

Someone crossed on tiptoe and drew a blind up with a rattle, and at the sound all started: through the window, opened at the top, came a rustle of the poplar leaves that stirred like footsteps in the wind. “There’s a strange man walking past the shrubberies,” whispered a nervous girl; “I saw him crouch and hide. I saw his eyes!” “Nonsense!” Came sharply from a male member of the group; “it’s far too dark to see. You heard the wind.” For mist had risen from the river just below the lawn, pressing close against the windows of the old house like a soft grey hand, and through it the stir of leaves was faintly audible. … Then, while several called for lights, others remembered that hop-pickers were still about in the lanes, and the tramps this autumn overbold and insolent. All, perhaps, wished secretly for the sun. Only the elderly man in the corner sat quiet and unmoved, contributing nothing. He had told no fearsome story. He had evaded, indeed, many openings expressly made for him, though fully aware that to his well-known interest in psychical things was partly due his presence in the weekend party. “I never have experiences—that way,” he said shortly when someone asked him point blank for a tale; “I have no unusual powers.” There was perhaps the merest hint of contempt in his tone, but the hostess from her darkened corner quickly and tactfully covered his retreat. And he wondered. For he knew why she invited him. The haunted room, he was well aware, had been specially allotted to him.

And then, most opportunely, the door opened noisily and the host came in. He sniffed at the darkness, rang at once for lamps, puffed at his big curved pipe, and generally, by his mere presence, made the group feel rather foolish. Light streamed past him from the corridor. His white hair shone like silver. And with him came the atmosphere of common sense, of shooting, agriculture, motors, and the rest. Age entered at that door. And his young wife sprang up instantly to greet him, as though his disapproval of this kind of entertainment might need humouring.

It may have been the light—that witchery of half-lights from the fire and the corridor, or it may have been the abrupt entrance of the Practical upon the soft Imaginative that traced the outline with such pitiless, sharp conviction. At any rate, the contrast—for those who had this inner clairvoyant sight all had been prating of so glibly!—was unmistakably revealed. It was poignantly dramatic, pain somewhere in it—naked pain. For, as she paused a moment there beside him in the light, this childless wife of three years’ standing, picture of youth and beauty, there stood upon the threshold of that room the presence of a true ghost story.

And most marevellously she changed—her lineaments, her very figure, her whole presentment. Etched against the gloom, the delicate, unmarked face shone suddenly keen and anguished, and a rich maturity, deeper than any mere age, flushed all her little person with its secret grandeur. Lines started into being upon the pale skin of the girlish face, lines of pleading, pity, and love the daylight did not show, and with them an air of magic tenderness that betrayed, though for a second only, the full soft glory of a motherhood denied, yet somehow mysteriously enjoyed. About her slenderness rose all the deep-bosomed sweetness of maternity, a potential mother of the world, and a mother, though she might know no dear fulfilment, who yet yearned to sweep into her immense embrace all the little helpless things that ever lived.

Light, like emotion, can play strangest tricks. The change pressed almost upon the edge of revelation. … Yet, when a moment later lamps were brought, it is doubtful if any but the silent guest who had told no marvellous tale, knew no psychical experience, and disclaimed the smallest clairvoyant faculty, had received and registered the vivid, poignant picture. For an instant it had flashed there, mercilessly clear for all to see who were not blind to subtle spiritual wonder thick with pain. And it was not so much mere picture of youth and age ill-matched, as of youth that yearned with the oldest craving in the world, and of age that had slipped beyond the power of sympathetically divining it. … It passed, and all was as before.

The husband laughed with genial good-nature, not one whit annoyed. “They’ve been frightening you with stories, child,” he said in his jolly way, and put a protective arm about her. “Haven’t they now? Tell me the truth. Much better,” he added, “have joined me instead at billiards, or for a game of Patience, eh?” She looked up shyly into his face, and he kissed her on the forehead. “Perhaps they have—a little, dear,” she said, “but now that you’ve come, I feel all right again.” “Another night of this,” he added in a graver tone, “and you’d be at your old trick of putting guests to sleep in the haunted room. I was right after all, you see, to make it out of bounds.” He glanced fondly, paternally down upon her. Then he went over and poked the fire into a blaze. Someone struck up a waltz on the piano, and couples danced. All trace of nervousness vanished, and the butler presently brought in the tray with drinks and biscuits. And slowly the group dispersed. Candles were lit. They passed down the passage into the big hail, talking in lowered voices of tomorrow’s plans. The laughter died away as they went up the stairs to bed, the silent guest and the young wife lingering a moment over the embers.

“You have not, after all then, put me in your haunted room?” he asked quietly. “You mentioned, you remember, in your letter—”

“I admit,” she replied at once, her manner gracious beyond her years, her voice quite different, “that I wanted you to sleep there—someone, I mean, who really knows, and is not merely curious. But—forgive my saying so—when I saw you”—she laughed very slowly—“and when you told no marvellous story like the others, I somehow felt—”

“But I never see anything—” he put in hurriedly.

“You feel, though,” she interrupted swiftly, the passionate tenderness in her voice but half suppressed. “I can tell it from your—”

“Others, then,” he interrupted abruptly, almost bluntly, “have slept there—sat up, rather?”

“Not recently. My husband stopped it.” She paused a second, then added, “I had that room—for a year—when first we married.”

The other’s anguished look flew back upon her little face like a shadow and was gone, while at the sight of it there rose in himself a sudden deep rush of wonderful amazement beckoning almost towards worship. He did not speak, for his voice would tremble.

“I had to give it up,” she finished, very low.

“Was it so terrible?” after a pause he ventured.

She bowed her head. “I had to change,” she repeated softly.

“And since then—now—you see nothing?” he asked.

Her reply was singular. “Because I will not, not because it’s gone.” … He followed her in silence to the door, and as they passed along the passage, again that curious great pain of emptiness, of loneliness, of yearning rose upon him, as of a sea that never, never can swim beyond the shore to reach the flowers that it loves …

“Hurry up, child, or a ghost will catch you,” cried her husband, leaning over the banisters, as the pair moved slowly up the stairs towards him. There was a moment’s silence when they met. The guest took his lighted candle and went down the corridor. Good nights were said again.

They moved away, she to her loneliness, he to his unhaunted room. And at his door he turned. At the far end of the passage, silhouetted against the candlelight, he watched them—the fine old man with his silvered hair and heavy shoulders, and the slim young wife with that amazing air as of some great bountiful mother of the world for whom the years yet passed hungry and unharvested. They turned the corner, and he went in and closed his door.

Sleep took him very quickly, and while the mist rose up and veiled the countryside, something else, veiled equally for all other sleepers in that house but two, drew on towards its climax. … Some hours later he awoke; the world was stills and it seemed the whole house listened; for with that clear vision which some bring out of sleep, he remembered that there had been no direct denial, and of a sudden realised that this big, gaunt chamber where he lay was after all the haunted room. For him, however, the entire world, not merely separate rooms in it, was ever haunted; and he knew no terror to find the space about him charged with thronging life quite other than his own. … He rose and lit the candle, crossed over to the window where the mist shone grey, knowing that no barriers of walls or door or ceiling could keep out this host of Presences that poured so thickly everywhere about him. It was like a wall of being, with peering eyes, small hands stretched out, a thousand pattering wee feet, and tiny voices crying in a chorus very faintly and beseeching. … The haunted room! Was it not, rather, a temple vestibule, prepared and sanctified by yearning rites few men might ever guess, for all the childless women of the world? How could she know that he would understand—this woman he had seen but twice in all his life? And how entrust to him so great a mystery that was her secret? Had she so easily divined in him a similar yearning to which, long years ago, death had denied fulfilment? Was she clairvoyant in the true sense, and did all faces bear on them so legibly this great map that sorrow traced? …

And then, with awful suddenness, mere feelings dipped away, and something concrete happened. The handle of the door had faintly rattled. He turned. The round brass knob was slowly moving. And first, at the sight, something of common fear did grip him, as though his heart had missed a beat, but on the instant he heard the voice of his own mother, now long beyond the stars, calling to him to go softly yet with speed. He watched a moment the feeble efforts to undo the door, yet never afterwards could swear that he saw actual movement, for something in him, tragic as blindness, rose through a mist of tears and darkened vision utterly. …

He went towards the door. He took the handle very gently, and very softly then he opened it. Beyond was darkness. He saw the empty passage, the edge of the banisters where the great hall yawned below, and, dimly, the outline of the Alpine photograph and the stuffed deer’s head upon the wall. And then he dropped upon his knees and opened wide his arms to something that came in upon uncertain, viewless feet. All the young winds and flowers and dews of dawn passed with it … filling him to the brim … covering closely his breast and eyes and lips. There clung to him all the small beginnings of life that cannot stand alone … the little helpless hands and arms that have no confidence … and when the wealth of tears and love that flooded his heart seemed to break upon the frontiers of some mysterious yet impossible fulfilment, he rose and went with curious small steps towards the window to taste the cooling, misty air of that other dark Emptiness that waited so patiently there above the entire world. He drew the sash up. The air felt soft and tender as though there were somewhere children in it too—children of stars and flowers, of mists and wings and music, all that the Universe contains unborn and tiny. … And when at length he turned again the door was closed. The room was empty of any life but that which lay so wonderfully blessed within himself. And this, he felt, had marvelously increased and multiplied. …

Sleep then came back to him, and in the morning he left the house before the others were astir, pleading some overlooked engagement. For he had seen Ghosts indeed, but yet no ghost that he could talk about with others round an open fire.

Clouds and Mountains

There are natures of the mystical, contemplative order who seek instinctively to correlate their scenery with some mood or aspiration of their inner life -who are not satis fied till they have linked it on somewhere intelligibly with their deepest being. Before a given landscape, that is, they find the explanation of their emotion by translating the colour, distance, confor mation and so forth into definite spiritual sensations; passing thus, without too great confusion, from the finite to the infinite. Until this is successfully accomplished there is a sense of disquietude, almost of pain; the loveliness blinds. But, once that inner key is found, the result is peace; the beauty becomes comprehensible with a personal message as it were. They dramatise the View in the terms of soul: doors open; veils lift; there come—wings.

The kind of scenery that best does this varies, of course, with individual temperament. For some, the changing sea; for others, the monotony of great plains, or the mystery of forests; for others, again -the majority, perhaps -the grandeur and terror of moun tains. But to all who under stand this process of the mind the world appears as the ex pression of something spiritual and alive, and common objects become a source of very vivid Such persons en revelation. dow ” common objects ” with something of their own life; nothing seems quite the same once their transforming im agination has looked upon it. The things they see, as Lotze puts it, “float off visions,” imperceptible to most; ” even the dead weights and supports of buildings become changed into so many limbs of a living body, whose inner tensions pass over into themselves.” The essence of which intuition Blake has still better ex pressed: “The tree which moves some to tears of joy is in the eyes of others only a green thing standing in the way.”

To me, personally, however, it always seems that the kind of scenery which, more than any other, admits of this transformation, of this spiritual alchemy, is the scenery of cloud and sky. There is that about it which suffers the change without violence. It belongs, really, to the same category as the vast scenery of dreams—to that which is phantasmal, protaean, infinitely fine; capable of interpreting the gentlest moods of the ‘soul, as well as her great terrors. Cloud-scenery, especially when sketched against big mountains, has the two qualities of expressing immense power and exceeding delicacy: power, by means of sheer size, depth and grandeur of form; delicacy, by the silken tracery of the torn edges that float away into the viewless air. Cloud -scenery touches all notes in the scale, Tuns through the entire gamut of the soul’s emotions. The mind wanders delightlully beyond the confines—of ~ sense into the region of un. ore realities; but the solid background of the mountains brings it back again, and sup- Pies the substantial foundation from which such dreams may be indulged without foolishness. Fantasy, thus rooted in reality, is surely an exercise of the imagination that produces useful, not harmful, results. To be “in the clouds” among the mountains is an experience of value, but to be among the mountains, and above the clouds, comes to many as almost an entirely new revelation. The whole strange world of dreams slides across th: frontier into waking life. The result is a kind of exquisite bewilderment.

The immensity of cloud-scenery has already been noticed Let the eye on a June day travel up and down the blue lanes of sky between the masses; and with the eye send also the imagination. The gradual comprehension of the piled ve heaped-up vapours ‘holds in the end something that appals There is a touch of genuine awe in the impression produced by those slow-moving chains of Mist Mountains, strewn through half the circle of the sky. shedding islands and promontories as they go, fur- rowed, cleft and peaked, their towered buk forever changing. The imagination comes back tired and panting; “lost, dizzy, shelterless,” Shelley puts it, or thinking, perhaps of the line in the Hebrew poem: “Knowest thou the balancing at the clouds?” Yet this is only to se them from below: To see them from above (as in our illustrations) slashed and pierced by the ribs and shoulders ot the mountains beyond, seething in an ocean whose waves are silent and whose foam no wind can scatter, is to know an aspect of Nature in which the chief ingredient, as it seems to me, is sheer bewilderment. From some high peak to look down upon the world, silent, still, wrapped in this garment of unwoven mist, all hushed beneath thick curtains of vapour which presently the wind shall tear aside to show green valley and the houses of men, is to surprise Nature, as it were, in the most secret chambers of her loveliness. And it is thus bewildering, I suppose, chiefly because there is nothing except the piece of solid rock on which the feet rest to recall the world of known values.

Even in the lower mountains the effect is one of singular charm, and from the summits of the Jura, for instance, especially in the winter months, it may frequently be witnessed with striking success. From the rocky ledges of La Tourne, which rises on y some 5,000ft. above the sea (where the Paris railway runs between Pontarlier and Neuchâtel), it is no uncommon thing in December or January to stand with the mist level to one’s feet, and the entire surface of the lower world blotted out beneath a sea of cloud that has no single break. Overhead the sky is speckless; below it, uniform as a giant counterpane, spreads in every direction the surface of this continent of cloud. The towns and villages that cluster along the Lake of Neuchâtel lie obliterated, the forests hidden, bells muffled; the roar of trains and water falls curiously hushed; and nothing visible but this sea of motionless vapour, ribbed like sand, or slightly waved, perhaps, like the ocean, stretching over lake and land as far as the skirts of the high Alps, a hundred kilomètres away. Here and there one sees the tips of Jura peaks-Boudry, Chasseral, Tête de Rang -clustered with ragged pines, like islands floating on the surface of a dream-sea in dazzling sunshine. But, with the exception of these, and of the great buzzards that occasionally plunge up out of the soft foamy mist into momentary sunlight, to disappear a few seconds later below the surface, there is nothing to remind one of the known world that lies hidden below the thick fleece that looks soft as cotton -wool, and of incredible depth. There is nothing to rest the eye on till it finds the distant snowfields of the chain of high Alps, stretching from Säntis to Mont Blanc; and even these look so dreamlike that one thinks of them almost as huge sails waiting a wind that shall blow them below the rim of the great silent sea.

In the high Alps, however, the scene is of another kind. The wind currents that forever suck through the deep valleys marshal the details with even more bewildering effects; the black depths, suddenly revealed and as suddenly closed again. the awful chasms, opened and shut so swiftly, throw the imagi nation into a state of disorder that adds enormously to the confusing grandeur of the spectacle. Only a few days ago, while climbing across the middle slopes of the Blümlisalp, I was fortunate enough to see the pageant in all its splendour. The hot spring sunshine joined forces with the snow-cooled air to produce a vast chaos of cloudland. Far below, the huge trough of the Oschinen See was filled with seething vapour, that rose and fell as the winds directed it, allowing occasional glimpses into the green glacier water through profound tunnels of mist, yet, as a whole, climbing gradually upwards to where we stood. Overhead, the summits rose clear in a sky of summer blue, with the single exception of the great Doldenhorn, where an immense cloud, forever shifting, and shedding whole precipices on its way, moved off laboriously till it was caught by the air-draughts from the Gastern Thal, and mysteriously spirited out of sight altogether.

But, meanwhile, the sea of vapour at our feet had risen till it spread in a single plain of white that somehow made one think of Shelley’s “platforms of the wind” become visible. This sea was without a break. Apparently, too, it was motionless; yet. on looking closer through field -glasses, it showed itself really alive with movement: the rising and falling of waves, rifts with fringed and jagged edges shooting in all directions, though never high enough to destroy the general effect of calm surface. There were swift draughts and whirlwinds astir through the entire mass. It was the glasses, of course, that betrayed the colossal scale of the thing. One thought somehow of a time of chaos when the earth was without form and void and darkness filled the face of the deep. It all weighed so little yet had so vastly ponderous an air. The sun blazed down upon it. Here, surely, were the suds that formed the raw material of the worlds suddenly arrested in mid boiling-frozen. Yet where we stood no wind reached us. Behind and about us rose the great still summits of the Blümlisalp and the Doldenhorn, with black pyramids of rock pushing their giant heads beyond all reach of turmoil. And it was while we stood there, forcing the imagination to reduce the wonder and beauty of it all to some comprehensible scale, that a further detail, not properly in the picture, came to add to the grandeur of the scene. Far below us, from some steep slope hidden beneath the sea of mist, there rose a curious long-drawn sound that at first suggested nothing we could recognise. It was only a few minutes later when the thunder followed that we realised an avalanche had plunged into the gulf. First we heard the hissing of the sheet of sliding snow—that awful hissing that more tan anything else strikes terror to the heart of the climber: herse up to us through the mist as the sound of an explosion might through the depths of the sea. Then, as the mass fell from ledge to ledge and finally dropped over the last dizzy cliff into the Oschmen See, we heard the thundering roar that echoed below, behind and overhead, and later felt the icy wind that followed the displacement of the air. Yet no signs were otherwise visible, The surface of the mist-sea remain untroubled. Nothing stirred: only the mighty sounds and the message of the loosed wind. And, far overhead, the iron battle ments of rock stood serene and terrible, their foundations rising out of the vast platform of vapour that wrapped them about like an ocean, their summits of shining ice inhabited by the flames of the sunshine.

Yet, several hours later, when we watched the same mountains from the safety of the comfortable Gemmi Hotel and listened to the warnings of Herr Dettlebach, the proprietor, about spring avalanches, it all seemed somehow unreal—the scenery all incredible and phantasmal as with the colouring of a splendid dream. The clouds had risen; like fragments of flying fire they floated ar overhead now in the sunset. It became impossible to see again that ocean of mist. What we had seen was no scenery of the known world. It belonged, surely, to the scenery of such dreams as carry the imagination into the Beyond—into infinite distances above the clouds.

XIII

CONFESSION

The fog swirled slowly round him, driven by a heavy movement of its own, for of course there was no wind. It hung in poisonous thick coils and loops; it rose and sank; no light penetrated it directly from street lamp or motor-car, though here and there some big shop-window shed a glimmering patch upon its ever-shifting curtain.

O’Reilly’s eyes ached and smarted with the incessant effort to see a foot beyond his face. The optic nerve grew tired, and sight, accordingly, less accurate. He coughed as he shuffled forward cautiously through the choking gloom. Only the stifled rumble of crawling traffic persuaded him he was in a crowded city at all—this, and the vague outlines of groping figures, hugely magnified, emerging suddenly and disappearing again, as they fumbled along inch by inch towards uncertain destinations.

The figures, however were human beings; they were real. That much he knew. He heard their muffled voices, now close, now distant, strangely smothered always. He also heard the tapping of innumerable sticks, feeling for iron railings or the kerb. These phantom outlines represented living people. He was not alone.

It was the dread of finding himself quite alone that haunted him, for he was still unable to cross an open space without assistance. He had the physical strength, it was the mind that failed him. Midway the panic terror might descend upon him, he would shake all over, his will dissolve, he would shriek for help, run wildly—into the traffic probably—or, as they called it in his North Ontario home, “throw a fit” in the street before advancing wheels. He was not yet entirely cured, although under ordinary conditions he was safe enough, as Dr. Henry had assured him.

When he left Regent’s Park by Tube an hour ago the air was clear, the November sun shone brightly, the pale blue sky was cloudless, and the assumption that he could manage the journey across London Town alone was justified. The following day he was to leave for Brighton for the week of final convalescence: this little preliminary test of his powers on a bright November afternoon was all to the good. Doctor Henry furnished minute instructions: “You change at Piccadilly Circus—without leaving the underground station, mind—and get out at South Kensington. You know the address of your V.A.D. friend. Have your cup of tea with her, then come back the same way to Regent’s Park. Come back before dark—say six o’clock at latest. It’s better.” He had described exactly what turns to take after leaving the station, so many to the right, so many to the left; it was a little confusing, but the distance was short. “You can always ask. You can’t possibly go wrong.”

The unexpected fog, however, now blurred these instructions in a confused jumble in his mind. The failure of outer sight reacted upon memory. The V.A.D. besides had warned him her address was “not easy to find the first time. The house lies in a backwater. But with your ‘backwoods’ instincts you’ll probably manage it better than any Londoner!” She, too, had not calculated upon the fog.

When O’Reilly came up the stairs at South Kensington Station, he emerged into such murky darkness that he thought he was still underground. An impenetrable world lay round him. Only a raw bite in the damp atmosphere told him he stood beneath an open sky. For some little time he stood and stared—a Canadian soldier, his home among clear brilliant spaces, now face to face for the first time in his life with that thing he had so often read about—a bad London fog. With keenest interest and surprise he “enjoyed” the novel spectacle for perhaps ten minutes, watching the people arrive and vanish, and wondering why the station lights stopped dead the instant they touched the street—then, with a sense of adventure—it cost an effort—he left the covered building and plunged into the opaque sea beyond.

Repeating to himself the directions he had received—first to the right, second to the left, once more to the left, and so forth—he checked each turn, assuring himself it was impossible to go wrong. He made correct if slow progress, until someone blundered into him with an abrupt and startling question: “Is this right, do you know, for South Kensington Station?”

It was the suddenness that startled him; one moment there was no one, the next they were face to face, another, and the stranger had vanished into the gloom with a courteous word of grateful thanks. But the little shock of interruption had put memory out of gear. Had he already turned twice to the right, or had he not? O’Reilly realized sharply he had forgotten his memorized instructions. He stood still, making strenuous efforts at recovery, but each effort left him more uncertain than before. Five minutes later he was lost as hopelessly as any townsman who leaves his tent in the backwoods without blazing the trees to ensure finding his way back again. Even the sense of direction, so strong in him among his native forests, was completely gone. There were no stars, there was no wind, no smell, no sound of running water. There was nothing anywhere to guide him, nothing but occasional dim outlines, groping, shuffling, emerging and disappearing in the eddying fog, but rarely coming within actual speaking, much less touching, distance. He was lost utterly; more, he was alone.

Yet not quite alone—the thing he dreaded most. There were figures still in his immediate neighborhood. They emerged, vanished, reappeared, dissolved. No, he was not quite alone. He saw these thickenings of the fog, he heard their voices, the tapping of their cautious sticks, their shuffling feet as well. They were real. They moved, it seemed, about him in a circle, never coming very close.

“But they’re real,” he said to himself aloud, betraying the weak point in his armour. “They’re human beings right enough. I’m positive of that.”

He had never argued with Dr. Henry—he wanted to get well; he had obeyed implicitly, believing everything the doctor told him—up to a point. But he had always had his own idea about these “figures,” because, among them, were often enough his own pals from the Somme, Gallipoli, the Mespot horror, too. And he ought to know his own pals when he saw them! At the same time he knew quite well he had been “shocked,” his being dislocated; half dissolved as it were, his system pushed into some lopsided condition that meant inaccurate registration. True. He grasped that perfectly. But, in that shock and dislocation, had he not possibly picked up another gear? Were there not gaps and broken edges, pieces that no longer dovetailed, fitted as usual, interstices, in a word? Yes, that was the word—interstices. Cracks, so to speak, between his perception of the outside world and his inner interpretation of these? Between memory and recognition? Between the various states of consciousness that usually dovetailed so neatly that the joints were normally imperceptible?

His state, he well knew, was abnormal, but were his symptoms on that account unreal? Could not these “interstices” be used by—others? When he saw his “figures,” he used to ask himself: “Are not these the real ones, and the others—the human beings—unreal?”

This question now revived in him with a new intensity. Were these figures in the fog real or unreal? The man who had asked the way to the station, was he not, after all, a shadow merely?

By the use of his cane and foot and what of sight was left to him he knew that he was on an island. A lamppost stood up solid and straight beside him, shedding its faint patch of glimmering light. Yet there were railings, however, that puzzled him, for his stick hit the metal rods distinctly in a series. And there should be no railings round an island. Yet he had most certainly crossed a dreadful open space to get where he was. His confusion and bewilderment increased with dangerous rapidity. Panic was not far away.

He was no longer on an omnibus route. A rare taxi crawled past occasionally, a whitish patch at the window indicating an anxious human face; now and again came a van or cart, the driver holding a lantern as he led the stumbling horse. These comforted him, rare though they were. But it was the figures that drew his attention most. He was quite sure they were real. They were human beings like himself.

For all that, he decided he might as well be positive on the point. He tried one accordingly—a big man who rose suddenly before him out of the very earth.

“Can you give me the trail to Morley Place?” he asked.

But his question was drowned by the other’s simultaneous inquiry in a voice much louder than his own.

“I say, is this right for the Tube station, d’you know? I’m utterly lost. I want South Ken.”

And by the time O’Reilly had pointed the direction whence he himself had just come, the man was gone again, obliterated, swallowed up, not so much as his footsteps audible, almost as if—it seemed again—he never had been there at all.

This left an acute unpleasantness in him, a sense of bewilderment greater than before. He waited five minutes, not daring to move a step, then tried another figure, a woman this time who, luckily, knew the immediate neighbourhood intimately. She gave him elaborate instructions in the kindest possible way, then vanished with incredible swiftness and ease into the sea of gloom beyond. The instantaneous way she vanished was disheartening, upsetting; it was so uncannily abrupt and sudden. Yet she comforted him. Morley Place, according to her version, was not two hundred yards from where he stood. He felt his way forward, step by step, using his cane, crossing a giddy open space kicking the kerb with each boot alternately, coughing and choking all the time as he did so.

“They were real, I guess, anyway,” he said aloud. “They were both real enough all right. And it may lift a bit soon!” He was making a great effort to hold himself in hand. He was already fighting, that is. He realized this perfectly. The only point was—the reality of the figures. “It may lift now any minute,” he repeated louder. In spite of the cold, his skin was sweating profusely.

But, of course, it did not lift. The figures, too, became fewer. No carts were audible. He had followed the woman’s directions carefully, but now found himself in some by-way, evidently, where pedestrians at the best of times were rare. There was dull silence all about him. His foot lost the kerb, his cane swept the empty air, striking nothing solid, and panic rose upon him with its shuddering, icy grip. He was alone, he knew himself alone, worse still—he was in another open space.

It took him fifteen minutes to cross that open space, most of the way upon his hands and knees, oblivious of the icy slime that stained his trousers, froze his fingers, intent only upon feeling solid support against his back and spine again. It was an endless period. The moment of collapse was close, the shriek already rising in his throat, the shaking of the whole body uncontrollable, when—his outstretched fingers struck a friendly kerb, and he saw a glimmering patch of diffused radiance overhead. With a great, quick effort he stood upright, and an instant later his stick rattled along an area railing. He leaned against it, breathless, panting, his heart beating painfully while the street lamp gave him the further comfort of its feeble gleam, the actual flame, however, invisible. He looked this way and that; the pavement was deserted. He was engulfed in the dark silence of the fog.

But Morley Place, he knew, must be very close by now. He thought of the friendly little V.A.D. he had known in France, of a warm bright fire, a cup of tea and a cigarette. One more effort, he reflected, and all these would be his. He pluckily groped his way forward again, crawling slowly by the area railings. If things got really bad again, he would ring a bell and ask for help, much as he shrank from the idea. Provided he had no more open spaces to cross, provided he saw no more figures emerging and vanishing like creatures born of the fog and dwelling within it as within their native element—it was the figures he now dreaded more than anything else, more even than the loneliness—provided the panic sense——

A faint darkening of the fog beneath the next lamp caught his eye and made him start. He stopped. It was not a figure this time, it was the shadow of the pole grotesquely magnified. No, it moved. It moved towards him. A flame of fire followed by ice flowed through him. It was a figure—close against his face. It was a woman.

The doctor’s advice came suddenly back to him, the counsel that had cured him of a hundred phantoms:

“Do not ignore them. Treat them as real. Speak and go with them. You will soon prove their unreality then. And they will leave you....”

He made a brave, tremendous effort. He was shaking. One hand clutched the damp and icy area railing.

“Lost your way like myself, haven’t you, ma’am?” he said in a voice that trembled. “Do you know where we are at all? Morley Place I’m looking for——”

He stopped dead. The woman moved nearer and for the first time he saw her face clearly. Its ghastly pallor, the bright, frightened eyes that stared with a kind of dazed bewilderment into his own, the beauty above all, arrested his speech midway. The woman was young, her tall figure wrapped in a dark fur coat.

“Can I help you?” he asked impulsively, forgetting his own terror for the moment. He was more than startled. Her air of distress and pain stirred a peculiar anguish in him. For a moment she made no answer, thrusting her white face closer as if examining him, so close, indeed, that he controlled with difficulty his instinct to shrink back a little.

“Where am I?” she asked at length, searching his eyes intently. “I’m lost—I’ve lost myself. I can’t find my way back.” Her voice was low, a curious wailing in it that touched his pity oddly. He felt his own distress merging in one that was greater.

“Same here,” he replied more confidently. “I’m terrified of being alone, too. I’ve had shell-shock, you know. Let’s go together. We’ll find a way together——”

“Who are you!” the woman murmured, still staring at him with her big bright eyes, their distress, however, no whit lessened. She gazed at him as though aware suddenly of his presence.

He told her briefly. “And I’m going to tea with a V.A.D. friend in Morley Place. What’s your address? Do you know the name of the street?”

She appeared not to hear him, or not to understand exactly; it was as if she was not listening again.

“I came out so suddenly, so unexpectedly,” he heard the low voice with pain in every syllable; “I can’t find my home again. Just when I was expecting him too——” She looked about her with a distraught expression that made O’Reilly long to carry her in his arms to safety then and there. “He may be there now—waiting for me at this very moment—and I can’t get back.” And so sad was her voice that only by an effort did O’Reilly prevent himself putting out his hand to touch her. More and more he forgot himself in his desire to help her. Her beauty, the wonder of her strange bright eyes in the pallid face, made an immense appeal. He became calmer. This woman was real enough. He asked again the address, the street and number, the distance she thought it was. “Have you any idea of the direction, ma’am, any idea at all? We’ll go together and——”

She suddenly cut him short. She turned her head as if to listen, so that he saw her profile a moment, the outline of the slender neck, a glimpse of jewels just below the fur.

“Hark! I hear him calling! I remember...!” And she was gone from his side into the swirling fog.

Without an instant’s hesitation O’Reilly followed her, not only because he wished to help, but because he dared not be left alone. The presence of this strange, lost woman comforted him; he must not lose sight of her, whatever happened. He had to run, she went so rapidly, ever just in front, moving with confidence and certainty, turning right and left, crossing the street, but never stopping, never hesitating, her companion always at her heels in breathless haste, and with a growing terror that he might lose her any minute. The way she found her direction through the dense fog was marvellous enough, but O’Reilly’s only thought was to keep her in sight, lest his own panic redescend upon him with its inevitable collapse in the dark and lonely street. It was a wild and panting pursuit, and he kept her in view with difficulty, a dim fleeting outline always a few yards ahead of him. She did not once turn her head, she uttered no sound, no cry; she hurried forward with unfaltering instinct. Nor did the chase occur to him once as singular; she was his safety, and that was all he realized.

One thing, however, he remembered afterwards, though at the actual time he no more than registered the detail, paying no attention to it—a definite perfume she left upon the atmosphere, one, moreover, that he knew, although he could not find its name as he ran. It was associated vaguely, for him, with something unpleasant, something disagreeable. He connected it with misery and pain. It gave him a feeling of uneasiness. More than that he did not notice at the moment, nor could he remember—he certainly did not try—where he had known this particular scent before.

Then suddenly the woman stopped, opened a gate and passed into a small private garden—so suddenly that O’Reilly, close upon her heels, only just avoided tumbling into her. “You’ve found it?” he cried. “May I come in a moment with you? Perhaps you’ll let me telephone to the doctor.”

She turned instantly. Her face close against his own, was livid.

“Doctor!” she repeated in an awful whisper. The word meant terror to her. O’Reilly stood amazed. For a second or two neither of them moved. The woman seemed petrified.

“Dr. Henry, you know,” he stammered, finding his tongue again. “I’m in his care. He’s in Harley Street.”

Her face cleared as suddenly as it had darkened, though the original expression of bewilderment and pain still hung in her great eyes. But the terror left them, as though she suddenly forgot some association that had revived it.

“My home,” she murmured. “My home is somewhere here. I’m near it. I must get back—in time—for him. I must. He’s coming to me.” And with these extraordinary words she turned, walked up the narrow path, and stood upon the porch of a two-storey house before her companion had recovered from his astonishment sufficiently to move or utter a syllable in reply. The front door, he saw, was ajar. It had been left open.

For five seconds, perhaps for ten, he hesitated; it was the fear that the door would close and shut him out that brought the decision to his will and muscles. He ran up the steps and followed the woman into a dark hall where she had already preceded him, and amid whose blackness she now had finally vanished. He closed the door, not knowing exactly why he did so, and knew at once by an instinctive feeling that the house he now found himself in with this unknown woman was empty and unoccupied. In a house, however, he felt safe. It was the open streets that were his danger. He stood waiting, listening a moment before he spoke; and he heard the woman moving down the passage from door to door, repeating to herself in her low voice of unhappy wailing some words he could not understand:

“Where is it? Oh, where is it? I must get back....”

O’Reilly then found himself abruptly stricken with dumbness, as though, with these strange words, a haunting terror came up and breathed against him in the darkness.

“Is she after all a figure?” ran in letters of fire across his numbed brain. “Is she unreal—or real?”

Seeking relief in action of some kind, he put out a hand automatically, feeling along the wall for an electric switch, and though he found it by some miraculous chance, no answering glow responded to the click.

And the woman’s voice from the darkness: “Ah! Ah! At last I’ve found it. I’m home again—at last...!” He heard a door open and close upstairs. He was on the ground-floor now—alone. Complete silence followed.

In the conflict of various emotions—fear for himself lest his panic should return, fear for the woman who had led him into this empty house and now deserted him upon some mysterious errand of her own that made him think of madness—in this conflict that held him a moment spell-bound, there was a yet bigger ingredient demanding instant explanation, but an explanation that he could not find. Was the woman real or was she unreal? Was she a human being or a “figure”? The horror of doubt obsessed him with an acute uneasiness that betrayed itself in a return of that unwelcome inner trembling he knew was dangerous.

What saved him from a crise that must have had most dangerous results for his mind and nervous system generally, seems to have been the outstanding fact that he felt more for the woman than for himself. His sympathy and pity had been deeply moved; her voice, her beauty, her anguish and bewilderment, all uncommon, inexplicable, mysterious, formed together a claim that drove self into the background. Added to this was the detail that she had left him, gone to another floor without a word, and now, behind a closed door in a room upstairs, found herself face to face at last with the unknown object of her frantic search—with “it,” whatever “it” might be. Real or unreal, figure or human being, the overmastering impulse of his being was that he must go to her.

It was this clear impulse that gave him decision and energy to do what he then did. He struck a match, he found a stump of candle, he made his way by means of this flickering light along the passage and up the carpetless stairs. He moved cautiously, stealthily, though not knowing why he did so. The house, he now saw, was indeed untenanted; dust-sheets covered the piled-up furniture; he glimpsed through doors ajar, pictures were screened upon the walls, brackets draped to look like hooded heads. He went on slowly, steadily, moving on tiptoe as though conscious of being watched, noting the well of darkness in the hall below, the grotesque shadows that his movements cast on walls and ceiling. The silence was unpleasant, yet, remembering that the woman was “expecting” someone, he did not wish it broken. He reached the landing and stood still. Closed doors on both sides of a corridor met his sight, as he shaded the candle to examine the scene. Behind which of these doors, he asked himself, was the woman, figure or human being, now alone with “it”?

There was nothing to guide him, but an instinct that he must not delay sent him forward again upon his search. He tried a door on the right—an empty room, with the furniture hidden by dust-sheets, and the mattress rolled up on the bed. He tried a second door, leaving the first one open behind him, and it was, similarly, an empty bedroom. Coming out into the corridor again he stood a moment waiting, then called aloud in a low voice that yet woke echoes unpleasantly in the hall below: “Where are you? I want to help—which room are you in?”

There was no answer; he was almost glad he heard no sound, for he knew quite well that he was waiting really for another sound—the steps of him who was “expected.” And the idea of meeting with this unknown third sent a shudder through him, as though related to an interview he dreaded with his whole heart, and must at all costs avoid. Waiting another moment or two, he noted that his candle-stump was burning low, then crossed the landing with a feeling, at once of hesitation and determination, towards a door opposite to him. He opened it; he did not halt on the threshold. Holding the candle at arm’s length, he went boldly in.

And instantly his nostrils told him he was right at last, for a whiff of the strange perfume, though this time much stronger than before, greeted him, sending a new quiver along his nerves. He knew now why it was associated with unpleasantness, with pain, with misery, for he recognized it—the odour of a hospital. In this room a powerful an�sthetic had been used—and recently.

Simultaneously with smell, sight brought its message too. On the large double bed behind the door on his right lay, to his amazement, the woman in the dark fur coat. He saw the jewels on the slender neck; but the eyes he did not see, for they were closed—closed, too, he grasped at once, in death. The body lay stretched at full length, quite motionless. He approached. A dark thin streak that came from the parted lips and passed downwards over the chin, losing itself then in the fur collar, was a trickle of blood. It was hardly dry. It glistened.

Strange it was perhaps that, while imaginary fears had the power to paralyse him, mind and body, this sight of something real had the effect of restoring confidence. The sight of blood and death, amid conditions often ghastly and even monstrous, was no new thing to him. He went up quietly, and with steady hand he felt the woman’s cheek, the warmth of recent life still in its softness. The final cold had not yet mastered this empty form whose beauty, in its perfect stillness, had taken on the new strange sweetness of an unearthly bloom. Pallid, silent, untenanted, it lay before him, lit by the flicker of his guttering candle. He lifted the fur coat to feel for the unbeating heart. A couple of hours ago at most, he judged, this heart was working busily, the breath came through those parted lips, the eyes were shining in full beauty. His hand encountered a hard knob—the head of a long steel hat-pin driven through the heart up to its hilt.

He knew then which was the figure—which was the real and which the unreal. He knew also what had been meant by “it.”

But before he could think or reflect what action he must take, before he could straighten himself even from his bent position over the body on the bed, there sounded through the empty house below the loud clang of the front door being closed. And instantly rushed over him that other fear he had so long forgotten—fear for himself. The panic of his own shaken nerves descended with irresistible onslaught. He turned, extinguishing the candle in the violent trembling of his hand, and tore headlong from the room.

The following ten minutes seemed a nightmare in which he was not master of himself and knew not exactly what he did. All he realized was that steps already sounded on the stairs, coming quickly nearer. The flicker of an electric torch played on the banisters, whose shadows ran swiftly sideways along the wall as the hand that held the light ascended. He thought in a frenzied second of police, of his presence in the house, of the murdered woman. It was a sinister combination. Whatever happened, he must escape without being so much as even seen. His heart raced madly. He darted across the landing into the room opposite, whose door he had luckily left open. And by some incredible chance, apparently, he was neither seen nor heard by the man who, a moment later, reached the landing, entered the room where the body of the woman lay, and closed the door carefully behind him.

Shaking, scarcely daring to breathe lest his breath be audible, O’Reilly, in the grip of his own personal terror, remnant of his uncured shock of war, had no thought of what duty might demand or not demand of him. He thought only of himself. He realized one clear issue—that he must get out of the house without being heard or seen. Who the new-comer was he did not know, beyond an uncanny assurance that it was not him whom the woman had “expected,” but the murderer himself, and that it was the murderer, in his turn, who was expecting this third person. In that room with death at his elbow, a death he had himself brought about but an hour or two ago, the murderer now hid in waiting for his second victim. And the door was closed.

Yet any minute it might open again, cutting off retreat.

O’Reilly crept out, stole across the landing, reached the head of the stairs, and began, with the utmost caution, the perilous descent. Each time the bare boards creaked beneath his weight, no matter how stealthily this weight was adjusted, his heart missed a beat. He tested each step before he pressed upon it, distributing as much of his weight as he dared upon the banisters. It was a little more than half-way down that, to his horror, his foot caught in a projecting carpet tack; he slipped on the polished wood, and only saved himself from falling headlong by a wild clutch at the railing, making an uproar that seemed to him like the explosion of a hand-grenade in the forgotten trenches. His nerves gave way then, and panic seized him. In the silence that followed the resounding echoes he heard the bedroom door opening on the floor above.

Concealment was now useless. It was impossible, too. He took the last flight of stairs in a series of leaps, four steps at a time, reached the hall, flew across it, and opened the front door, just as his pursuer, electric torch in hand, covered half the stairs behind him. Slamming the door, he plunged headlong into the welcome, all-obscuring fog outside.

The fog had now no terrors for him, he welcomed its concealing mantle; nor did it matter in which direction he ran so long as he put distance between him and the house of death. The pursuer had, of course, not followed him into the street. He crossed open spaces without a tremor. He ran in a circle nevertheless, though without being aware he did so. No people were about, no single groping shadow passed him; no boom of traffic reached his ears, when he paused for breath at length against an area railing. Then for the first time he made the discovery that he had no hat. He remembered now. In examining the body, partly out of respect, partly perhaps unconsciously, he had taken it off and laid it—on the very bed.

It was there, a tell-tale bit of damning evidence, in the house of death. And a series of probable consequences flashed through his mind like lightning. It was a new hat fortunately; more fortunate still, he had not yet written name or initials in it; but the maker’s mark was there for all to read, and the police would go immediately to the shop where he had bought it only two days before. Would the shop-people remember his appearance? Would his visit, the date, the conversation be recalled? He thought it was unlikely; he resembled dozens of men; he had no outstanding peculiarity. He tried to think, but his mind was confused and troubled, his heart was beating dreadfully, he felt desperately ill. He sought vainly for some story to account for his being out in the fog and far from home without a hat. No single idea presented itself. He clung to the icy railings, hardly able to keep upright, collapse very near—when suddenly a figure emerged from the fog, paused a moment to stare at him, put out a hand and caught him, and then spoke:

“You’re ill, my dear sir,” said a man’s kindly voice. “Can I be of any assistance? Come, let me help you.” He had seen at once that it was not a case of drunkenness. “Come, take my arm, won’t you? I’m a physician. Luckily, too, you are just outside my very house. Come in.” And he half dragged, half pushed O’Reilly, now bordering on collapse, up the steps and opened the door with his latch-key.

“Felt ill suddenly—lost in the fog ... terrified, but be all right soon, thanks awfully——” the Canadian stammered his gratitude, but already feeling better. He sank into a chair in the hall, while the other put down a paper parcel he had been carrying, and led him presently into a comfortable room; a fire burned brightly; the electric lamps were pleasantly shaded; a decanter of whisky and a siphon stood on a small table beside a big arm-chair; and before O’Reilly could find another word to say the other had poured him out a glass and bade him sip it slowly, without troubling to talk till he felt better.

“That will revive you. Better drink it slowly. You should never have been out a night like this. If you’ve far to go, better let me put you up——”

“Very kind, very kind, indeed,” mumbled O’Reilly, recovering rapidly in the comfort of a presence he already liked and felt even drawn to.

“No trouble at all,” returned the doctor. “I’ve been at the front, you know. I can see what your trouble is—shell-shock, I’ll be bound.”

The Canadian, much impressed by the other’s quick diagnosis, noted also his tact and kindness. He had made no reference to the absence of a hat, for instance.

“Quite true,” he said. “I’m with Dr. Henry, in Harley Street,” and he added a few words about his case. The whisky worked its effect, he revived more and more, feeling better every minute. The other handed him a cigarette; they began to talk about his symptoms and recovery; confidence returned in a measure, though he still felt badly frightened. The doctor’s manner and personality did much to help, for there was strength and gentleness in the face, though the features showed unusual determination, softened occasionally by a sudden hint as of suffering in the bright, compelling eyes. It was the face, thought O’Reilly, of a man who had seen much and probably been through hell, but of a man who was simple, good, sincere. Yet not a man to trifle with; behind his gentleness lay something very stern. This effect of character and personality woke the other’s respect in addition to his gratitude. His sympathy was stirred.

“You encourage me to make another guess,” the man was saying, after a successful reading of the impromptu patient’s state, “that you have had, namely, a severe shock quite recently, and”—he hesitated for the merest fraction of a second—“that it would be a relief to you,” he went on, the skilful suggestion in the voice unnoticed by his companion, “it would be wise as well, if you could unburden yourself to—someone—who would understand.” He looked at O’Reilly with a kindly and very pleasant smile. “Am I not right, perhaps?” he asked in his gentle tone.

“Someone who would understand,” repeated the Canadian. “That’s my trouble exactly. You’ve hit it. It’s all so incredible.”

The other smiled. “The more incredible,” he suggested, “the greater your need for expression. Suppression, as you may know, is dangerous in cases like this. You think you have hidden it, but it bides its time and comes up later, causing a lot of trouble. Confession, you know”—he emphasized the word—“confession is good for the soul!”

“You’re dead right,” agreed the other.

“Now if you can, bring yourself to tell it to someone who will listen and believe—to myself, for instance. I am a doctor, familiar with such things. I shall regard all you say as a professional confidence, of course; and, as we are strangers, my belief or disbelief is of no particular consequence. I may tell you in advance of your story, however—I think I can promise it—that I shall believe all you have to say.”

O’Reilly told his story without more ado, for the suggestion of the skilled physician had found easy soil to work in. During the recital his host’s eyes never once left his own. He moved no single muscle of his body. His interest seemed intense.

“A bit tall, isn’t it?” said the Canadian, when his tale was finished. “And the question is——” he continued with a threat of volubility which the other checked instantly.

“Strange, yes, but incredible, no,” the doctor interrupted. “I see no reason to disbelieve a single detail of what you have just told me. Things equally remarkable, equally incredible, happen in all large towns, as I know from personal experience. I could give you instances.” He paused a moment, but his companion, staring into his eyes with interest and curiosity, made no comment. “Some years ago, in fact,” continued the other, “I knew of a very similar case—strangely similar.”

“Really! I should be immensely interested——”

“So similar that it seems almost a coincidence. You may find it hard, in your turn, to credit it.” He paused again, while O’Reilly sat forward in his chair to listen. “Yes,” pursued the doctor slowly, “I think everyone connected with it is now dead. There is no reason why I should not tell it, for one confidence deserves another, you know. It happened during the Boer War—as long ago as that,” he added with emphasis. “It is really a very commonplace story in one way, though very dreadful in another, but a man who has served at the front will understand and—I’m sure—will sympathize.”

“I’m sure of that,” offered the other readily.

“A colleague of mine, now dead, as I mentioned—a surgeon, with a big practice, married a young and charming girl. They lived happily together for several years. His wealth made her very comfortable. His consulting-room, I must tell you, was some distance from his house—just as this might be—so that she was never bothered with any of his cases. Then came the war. Like many others, though much over age, he volunteered. He gave up his lucrative practice and went to South Africa. His income, of course, stopped; the big house was closed; his wife found her life of enjoyment considerably curtailed. This she considered a great hardship, it seems. She felt a bitter grievance against him. Devoid of imagination, without any power of sacrifice, a selfish type, she was yet a beautiful, attractive woman—and young. The inevitable lover came upon the scene to console her. They planned to run away together. He was rich. Japan they thought would suit them. Only, by some ill luck, the husband got wind of it and arrived in London just in the nick of time.”

“Well rid of her,” put in O’Reilly, “I think.”

The doctor waited a moment. He sipped his glass. Then his eyes fixed upon his companion’s face somewhat sternly.

“Well rid of her, yes,” he continued, “only he determined to make that riddance final. He decided to kill her—and her lover. You see, he loved her.”

O’Reilly made no comment. In his own country this method with a faithless woman was not unknown. His interest was very concentrated. But he was thinking, too, as he listened, thinking hard.

“He planned the time and place with care,” resumed the other in a lower voice, as though he might possibly be overheard. “They met, he knew, in the big house, now closed, the house where he and his young wife had passed such happy years during their prosperity. The plan failed, however, in an important detail—the woman came at the appointed hour, but without her lover. She found death waiting for her—it was a painless death. Then her lover, who was to arrive half an hour later, did not come at all. The door had been left open for him purposely. The house was dark, its rooms shut up, deserted; there was no caretaker even. It was a foggy night, just like this.”

“And the other?” asked O’Reilly in a failing voice. “The lover——”

“A man did come in,” the doctor went on calmly, “but it was not the lover. It was a stranger.”

“A stranger?” the other whispered. “And the surgeon—where was he all this time?”

“Waiting outside to see him enter—concealed in the fog. He saw the man go in. Five minutes later he followed, meaning to complete his vengeance, his act of justice, whatever you like to call it. But the man who had come in was a stranger—he came in by chance—just as you might have done—to shelter from the fog—or——”

O’Reilly, though with a great effort, rose abruptly to his feet. He had an appalling feeling that the man facing him was mad. He had a keen desire to get outside, fog or no fog, to leave this room, to escape from the calm accents of this insistent voice. The effect of the whisky was still in his blood. He felt no lack of confidence. But words came to him with difficulty.

“I think I’d better be pushing off now, doctor,” he said clumsily. “But I feel I must thank you very much for all your kindness and help.” He turned and looked hard into the keen eyes facing him. “Your friend,” he asked in a whisper, “the surgeon—I hope—I mean, was he ever caught?”

“No,” was the grave reply, the doctor standing up in front of him, “he was never caught.”

O’Reilly waited a moment before he made another remark. “Well,” he said at length, but in a louder tone than before, “I think—I’m glad.” He went to the door without shaking hands.

“You have no hat,” mentioned the voice behind him. “If you’ll wait a moment I’ll get you one of mine. You need not trouble to return it.” And the doctor passed him, going into the hall. There was a sound of tearing paper, O’Reilly left the house a moment later with a hat upon his head, but it was not till he reached the Tube station half an hour afterwards that he realized it was his own.

Discovering Russia on Foot

Books of travel one reads more and more with a sense of weariness, for the art of making one see and feel the countries described is surely an exceedingly rare one. There are often pages of fine description, there are adventures, there is the interest of obstacles and difficulties overcome, and there are—maps. And in the end the reader’s mind becomes itself a composite map in which the various countries lie jumbled up together with colours like a patchwork quilt. For, as a rule, the writer describes the detail of the scenery instead of the more valuable interpretative effect the scenery produces upon himself. Yet it is this latter that makes one see and feel the country, and the writer should boldly tell about himself, without false modesty. Then, if he has the poet’s heart in him as well, he introduces living pictures into our mind. We close the book, having really travelled with him. He has widened our experience and feeling, not merely added to our knowledge of facts and names and distances, however finely described. It is, we claim, the poet’s rare prerogative to accomplish this very high achievement. It is a keen delight to recognise it, for the emotion roused in reading such a book is the same as the emotion that good poetry stirs; and whether you come across it in its simplest form, as in the Man-Eaters of Tsavo, in more passionate, vivid shape, as in Masefield’s Multitude and Solitude, or in its still more highly-finished aspect, as in Hilaire Belloc’s wonderful presentment of the very souls of towns and places, the result is one and the same: the thrill and beauty of good poetry.

In Undiscovered Russia, Mr. Stephen Graham has written a haunting book of travel that might equally well have been in the form of poetry, for, from beginning to end, it is a genuine poem. He did this a year ago in his delightful Vagabond in the Caucasus. He has done it again in Undiscovered Russia, only with more passion, greater skill and a finer perception of the beauty of scenery and of human nature than before. He has told us of his long journey on foot for many weeks (some of it in shoes of birch-bark!) from Archangel on the White Sea down to Rostov on the Don in a long, beautiful poem of adventure and delight that sets this book among the very best of its rare kind. And he has done this well because he felt it deeply, and gives his feelings with an honest modesty that is both engaging and illuminating. “I love Russia. She is something more to me than my native land. I have lived among beautiful people leading serene and tranquil lives far from the Western hurly-burly. These have been so mystically pure that I could never be quite sure that they had not foreseen my coming in a dream. England knows not such. To me they are a revelation of love.” Here speaks the poet who feels the thing from within himself, not merely observes it from outside. “You wish to see Russia as it remains in the old unknown parts,” a woman said to him; “then you should go to the North, for there all that Russia ever was is conserved in the forests as in ice—in the provinces of Archangel and Vologda—where there are no railways and no intercourse with the advanced world of the twentieth century.” And he went, slept with the peasants and the hunters, lived with the boatmen and the bargemen, tramped with revolutionary students, and took into his own heart the strange, wild spirit of this enormous country that he has now given out in this volume of thrilling beauty and delight. You see with him the weird wonder of the northern White Night, where for two months the sun is above the horizon; you feel the awful mystery of the leagues of untrodden forest; you catch fish with him at midnight on the broad Dwina while the sun shines hotly on the waters; you hear the balalaikas twang in villages so remote from civilisation that the people have but a single, common surname, applied also to the hamlet itself; and you share strange gospels, taste ancient superstitions, hear the footfall of forest ghosts and devils, or go into the heart of it to pluck the flower of happiness that blossoms at midnight on the Eve of St. John. “I gave my heart to Russia. She is a woman. Behind her eyes are forests of pines and unexplored darkness; in her hand she carries blossoms. She is the mother of nations.” “How do you feel Russia?” Vassily Vassilievitch, the painter, whose pictures add so greatly to the book, enquired of him. “Do not answer ‘good’ or ‘bad’ or ‘interesting’; you understand what I mean.” And Mr. Graham’s answer was like this: “I feel her old, fragrant, melancholy, like the black earth.”

One feels, in reading these pages, that the volume is peculiarly well named, and that the real Russia is as yet almost entirely undiscovered to Western eyes. Joseph Conrad and Stephen Graham have both explained a part of her; and it is highly interesting to read the latter’s chapters on the Colony of Exiled Revolutionary Students at Liavlia, side by side with the wonderful psychological study in Under Western Eyes. Mr. Graham’s sojourn with these students is an interlude of vivid and instructive interest. They were banished for periods of months or years to the safety of this remote place, where they lived a comparative freedom under the eyes of the police, and Mr. Graham dwelt among them as one of themselves. “My first impression was that I had come to a convict settlement, but as none of the exiles had been convicted definitely of a crime, the term was evidently inappropriate. Every one of the prisoners had been brought to trial before the martial courts and had been found ‘Not Guilty’—not guilty, but also not innocent, for they had evidently dabbled in terrorism and propagandism, and though no case could be made out against them, it would have been dangerous to release them. … The Government had banished them ‘under administrative order’ to this forest-girdled village, where further plotting would be absurd, and escape impossible.” Each one received a small monthly sum for food and clothing, and they could hunt, fish, receive their friends and make merry. They did all this, and in so doing largely forgot their secret terrible ambitions. Mr. Graham suggests that much of the student movement is due to idle brooding and the like. He tells Tchekof’s typical story of the Russian who went to buy a pistol to shoot his wife and her lover with, and, seeing a net for catching quails on the shop counter, bought that instead and forgot all about his private evils. This contradictory element in the Russian character, which is so intensely perplexing to Europeans, is further very fully dealt with in Maurice Baring’s detailed study of The Russian People, where, in his chapter on “the Russian character,” he ascribes much of it to the influence of climate. “It leads him, firstly, to battle with the hostile forces of nature in order to live, and consequently develops in him qualities of tenacity, energy and strength; and secondly, it leads him to bow down and submit to the overwhelming and insuperable forces of nature, against which all struggle is hopeless. Thus it is that he develops qualities of patience, resignation and weakness. This, again, accounts for that mixture in the Russian which more than all things puzzles the Western European, namely, the blend of roughness and good-nature, of kindness and brutal insensibility.” And both writers agree that the Russian peasant is essentially humane and gentle, and more humane than Europeans of the same class. He will calmly beat a man to death for stealing a horse, yet will also show a compassionate and generous hospitality that is tender in the last degree. It is a curious and deeply interesting chapter in human nature, and those who feel the spell of it should read carefully Mr. Baring’s treatment and explanation of the paradox.

There are many things in Undiscovered Russia we should like to dwell upon, or at least to mention, but the wonderful adventures this “vagabond” encountered would lose their charm and interest in the process of condensation. It would be to spoil the flavour of a remarkably interesting book of travel. Mr. Graham’s experiences with the pilgrims, with the monks in lonely monasteries, with the police when he was arrested, and with many another figure of mystery, terror and beauty which flits across his enchanted stage—these must be sought in the original. And, meanwhile, we wish greater strength to his wandering feet, increasing power to feel beauty and interpret it, and a yet greater expansion of that love which he clearly feels for the suffering millions of this strange country he seeks to make his own. His field is a big one, and he is well qualified to exploit it for our benefit. Undiscovered Russia deals, as he says himself, with but a fringe of it. And greater discoveries lie, we feel convinced, for him ahead.

Down the Danube in a Canadian Canoe

I

It was a brilliant day in early June when we launched our canoe on the waters of the Danube, not one hundred yards from its source in the Black Forest, and commenced our journey of four and twenty hundred miles to the Black Sea. Two weeks before we had sent her from London to Donaueschingen by freight, and when the railway-company telegraphed the word arrived we posted after her with tent, kit-bags, blankets, cameras, and cooking-apparatus.

Donaueschingen is an old-fashioned little town on the southern end of the Schwarzwald plateau, and the railway that runs through it brings it apparently no nearer to the world. It breathes a spirit of remoteness and tranquillity born of the forests that encircle it, and that fill the air with pleasant odours and gentle murmurings.

There, lying snugly on a shelf in the goods-shed, we found our slender craft, paddles and boat-hook tied securely to the thwarts—and without a crack! “No duty to pay,” said the courteous official, after examining an enormous book, “and only seventeen marks for freight-charges the whole way from Oxford.” She was sixteen feet long (with a beam of thirty-four inches), and had the slim graceful lines and deep curved ribs of the true Eice Lake (Ontario) build. Two or three inches would float her, and yet she could ride safely at top speed over the waves of a rapid that would have capsized a boat twice her size. Splendid little craft, she bore us faithfully and well, almost like a thing of life and intelligence, round many a ticklish corner and under more than one dangerous bridge, though this article will only outline some of our adventures in her over the first thousand miles as far as Budapest.

From the yard of the Schuetzen Inn, where she lay all night, we carried her on our shoulders below the picturesque stone bridge and launched her in a pool where the roach and dace fairly made the water dance. You could toss a stone over the river here without an effort, and when we had said farewell to the kindly villagers and steered out into midstream, there was so little water that the stroke of the paddle laid bare the shining pebbles upon the bottom and grated along the bed.

“Happy journey!” cried the townsfolk standing on the bank in blue trousers and waving their straw hats. “And quick return,” added the hotelkeeper, who had overcharged us abominably in every possible item. We bore him little malice, however, for there were no inns or hotel-bills ahead of us; and uncommonly lighthearted were we as the canoe felt the stream move beneath her and slipped away at a good speed down the modest little river that must drop twenty-two hundred feet before it pours its immense volume through three arms into the Black Sea.

At first our progress was slow. Patches of white weeds everywhere choked the river and often brought us to a complete standstill, and in less than ten minutes we were aground in a shallow. We had to tuck up our trousers and wade. This was a frequent occurrence during the day and we soon realised that the hundred and twenty-five miles to Ulm, before the tributaries commence to pour in their icy floods from the Alps, would be slow and difficult. But what of that? It was glorious summer weather; the mountain airs were intoxicating, and the scenery charming beyond words. Nowhere that day was the river more than forty yards across, or over three feet deep. The white weeds lay over the surface like thick cream, but the canoe glided smoothly over them, swishing as she passed. Her slim nose opened a pathway that her stern left gently hissing with bubbles as the leaves rose again to the surface; and behind us there was ever a little milk-white track in which the blossoms swam and danced in the sunshine as the current raced merrily along the new channel thus made for it.

Winding in and out among broad fields and acres of reeds we dropped gently down across the great plateau of the Black Forest mountains. The day was hot and clear, and overhead a few white clouds sailed with us, as it were for company’s sake, down the blue reaches of the sky. Usually we coasted along the banks, the reeds touching the sides of the canoe and the wind playing over hosts of nodding flowers and fields level to our eyes with standing hay, while, in the distance, the mountain-slopes, speckled with blue shadows, were ever opening into new vistas and valleys. Here the peaceful Danube still dreams, lying in her beauty-sleep as it were, and with no hint of the racing torrent that comes later with full waking. Pretty villages appeared along the banks at intervals. Pforen was the first, snugly gathered into the nook of the hills; a church, a few red-roofed houses, a wooden bridge, and a castle with a fine stork staring down at us from her nest in the ruined tower. The peasants were away in the fields and we drifted lazily by without so much as a greeting. Neidingen was the second, where a huge crucifix presided over the centre of the quaint bridge, and where we landed to buy butter, potatoes, and onions. Gutmadingen was the third; and here a miller and his men helped our portage over the weir while his wife stood in the hot sunshine and asked questions.

“Where are you going to?”

“The Black Sea.” She had never heard of it, and evidently thought we were making fun of her. “Ulm, then,” Ah! Ulm she knew. “But it’s an enormous distance! And is the tent for rain?” she asked.

“No; for sleeping in at night.”

“Ach was!” she exclaimed. “Well, I wouldn’t sleep a night in that tent, or go a yard in that boat, for anything you could give me.”

The miller was more appreciative. He gave us a delicious drink—a sort of mead, which was most refreshing and which, he assured us, would not affect the head in the least—and told us there were twenty-four more weirs before we reached Ulm, the beginning of navigation. But none the less he, too, had his questions to ask.

“I thought all the Englishmen had gone to the war. The papers here say that England is quite empty.”

The temptation was too great to resist. “No,” we said gravely, “only the big ones went to the war. [We were both over six feet.] England is still full of men of the smaller sizes like ourselves.” The expression on his face lightened our work considerably for the next mile.

Soon after the river left the plateau behind it and took a sudden leap into the Donauthal. We shot round a corner about six o’clock and came upon a little willow-island in midstream. Here we landed and pitched our tent on the long grass, made a fire, peeled the onions, fried our strips of beef with the potatoes, and made excellent tea. On all sides the pines crept down close into the narrowing valley. In the evening sunlight, with long shadows slanting across the hills, we smoked our pipes after our meal. There were no flies and the air was cool and sweet. Presently the moon rose over the ridge of forest behind us and the lights of Immendingen, twinkling through the shadows, were just visible a mile below us. The night was cool and the river hurried almost silently past our tent door. When at length we went to bed, on cork mattresses with india-rubber sheets under us and thick Austrian blankets over us, everything was sopping with dew.

The bells of Immendingen coming down the valley were the first sounds we heard as we went to bathe at seven o’clock next morning in the cold sparkling water; and later, when we scrambled over the great Immendingen weir no villagers came to look on and say “Engländer, Engländer” for it was Sunday morning and they were all at Mass.

The valley grew narrower and limestone cliffs shone white through the sombre forests. It was very lonely between the villages. The river, now sixty yards wide, swept in great semicircular reaches under the very shadow of the hills; storks stood about fishing in the shallows; wild swans flew majestically in front of us—we came across several nests with eggs—and duck were plentiful everywhere. Once, in an open space on the hills, we saw a fine red fox motionless in his observation of some duck—and ourselves. Presently he trotted away into the cover of the woods and the ducks quacked their thanks to us. Then suddenly, above Mbhringen, just when we were congratulating ourselves that wading was over for good, the river dwindled away into a thin trickling line of water that showed the shape of every single pebble in its bed. We went aground continually. Half the Danube had escaped through fissures in the ground. It comes out again, on the other side of the mountains, as the river Ach, and flows into the Lake of Constance. The river was now less in volume than when we started, clear as crystal, dancing in the sunshine, weaving like a silver thread through the valley, and making delightful music over the stones. Yet most of our journey that day was wading. Trousers were always tucked up to the knees, and we had to be ready to jump out at a moment’s notice. Before the numberless little rapids the question was: “Is there enough water to float us? Can we squeeze between those rocks? Is that wave a hidden stone, or merely the current?” The steersman stood up to get a better view of the channel and avoid the sun’s glare on the water, and in this way we raced down many a bit of leaping, hissing water; and, incidentally, had many a sudden shock before the end, tumbling out headlong, banging against stones, and shipping water all the time. The canoe got sadly scratched, and we decided at length to risk no more of these baby-rapids. A torn canoe in the Black Forest, miles from a railway, spelt helplessness. Thereafter we waded the rapids. It was a hot and laborious process—the feet icy cold, the head burning hot, and the back always bent double. Weirs, too, became frequent, and unloading and reloading was soon reduced to a science. In the afternoon the villagers poured out to stare and look on. They rarely offered to help, but stood round as close as possible while we unloaded, examining articles, and asking questions all the time. They had no information to give. Few of them knew anything of the river ten miles below their particular village, and none had ever been to Ulm. Now and then there was a sceptical “Dass ist unmoglich (that’s impossible),” when we mentioned Ulm as our goal. “Ach je! They’re mad—in that boat!”

From Donaueschingen to Ulm there is a weir in every five miles, and our progress was slow. Whenever the river grew deep we learned to know that a dam was near; and below a dam there was scarcely enough water to float an eggshell. But there was no occasion to hurry; everything was done in leisurely fashion in this great garden of Würtemburg, and most of the villages were sound asleep. At Mohringen, indeed, we got the impression that the village had slept for at least a hundred years and that our bustling arrival had suddenly awakened it. It lay in a clearing of the forest, in a charming mossy bed that no doubt made sleep a delightful necessity. The miller invited us to the inn, where we found a score of peasants in their peaked hats and black suits of broadcloth sitting each in front of a foaming tankard; but they drank so slowly that a hundred years did not seem too long to finish a tankard. There was very little conversation, and they stared unconscionably, bowing gravely when we ordered their stone mugs to be refilled and regarding us all the time with steady, expressionless interest. In due time, however, they digested us, and then the stream of inevitable questions burst forth.

“You bivouac? You go to the sea? If you ever get to Ulm! You have come the whole way from London in that shell?”

We gulped down the excellent cold beer and hurried away. The river dwindled to a width of a dozen yards and wading was incessant. We lightened the canoe as much as possible, but, our kit having been already reduced to what seemed only strictly necessary, there was little enough to throw away—a tin plate, a tin cup, a fork, a spoon, a knife, and a red cushion. These we piled up in a little mound upon the bank with a branch stuck in the ground to draw attention. I wonder who is now using those costly articles.

Another series of picturesque villages glided past us: Tuttlingen, famous (as the dirty water proclaimed) for its tanneries, and where a couple of hundred folk in their Sunday clothes watched our every movement as we climbed round two high and difficult weirs; Nendringen, where a kind and silent miller gave us of his cool mead; Mülheim straggling halfway up the hills with its red-brown roofs and church and castle all mingled together in most picturesque confusion, as if it had slipped down from the summit and never got straight again; and Friedigen, where we laid in fresh supplies, and found two Germans who had spent years in California, and whose nasal voices sounded strangely out of place among their guttural neighbours. “Camp anywheres you please,” they said, “and no one’ll objec’ to your fires so long as you put ’em out.”

I forget how many more villages ending in ingen we passed; but now that the heat of the day, and the labour and toil of wading are forgotten, they come before me again with their still, peaceful loveliness like a string of quaint jewels strung along the silver thread of the river.

Soon the water increased and the canoe sped onwards among the little waves and rapids like a winged thing. The mountains became higher, the valley narrower. Limestone cliffs, scooped and furrowed by the eddies of a far larger Danube thousands of years before, rose gleaming out of the pinewoods about their base. We plunged in among the Swabian Alps, and the river tumbled very fast and noisily along a rock-strewn bed. It darted across from side to side, almost as though the cliffs were tossing it across in play to each other. One moment we were in blazing sunlight, the next in deep shadow under the cliffs. There was no room for houses, and no need for bridges; boats we never saw; big, grey fish-hawks, circling buzzards, storks by the score had this part of the river all to themselves.

Suddenly we turned a sharp corner and shot at full speed into an immense cauldron. It was a perfect circle, half a mile in diameter, bound in by the limestone cliffs. The more ancient river had doubtless filled it with a terrifying whirlpool, for the rocks were strangely scooped and eaten into curves hundreds of feet above us. But now its bottom was a clean flat field, where the little stream, with its audacious song, whipped along at the very foot of the cliffs on one side of the circle.

It was a lonely secluded spot, the very place for a camp. Though only five o’clock on a June afternoon the cliffs kept out the sunshine. We sank the canoe, to soak up cracks and ease strained ribs, and soon had our tent up, and a fire burning. Then we climbed the cliffs. It was a puzzle to see how the river got in or got out. As we climbed we came across deep recesses and funnel-shaped holes, caves with spiral openings in the roof, and pillars shaped like an hourglass. Across the gulf the ruined castle of Kallenberg stood on a point of rock that was apparently inaccessible, and when the evening star shone over its broken battlements, it might well have been a ghostly light held aloft by the shades of the robber-barons who once lived in it. When we went to bed at ten o’clock the full moon shone upon the white cliffs with a dazzling brilliance that seemed to turn them into ice, while the deep shadows over the river made the scene strangely impressive. Only the tumbling of the water and the chirping of the crickets broke the silence. In the night we woke and thought we heard people moving round the tent, but, on going out to see, the canoe was still safe, and the white moonshine revealed no figures. It was doubtless the river talking in its sleep, or the wind wandering lost among the bushes.

At five o’clock next morning I looked out of the tent and found our cauldron full of seething mist through which the sunshine was just beginning to force a way. An hour later the tent was too hot for comfort.

All day we followed the gorge, with many a ruined castle of impregnable position looking down upon us from the cliffs. The valley widened about noon, and fields ablaze with poppies lay in the sun, while tall yellow flags fringed the widening river. In another great circle, similar in formation to that of Kallenberg, but five times as large, we found the monastery of Beuron with its eighty monks and fifty lay-brothers. We bathed and put on our celluloid collars (full dress in an outfit where weight is of supreme importance) and went up to the gates. A bearded monk, acting as doorkeeper, thrust a smiling face through the wicket in answer to our summons and informed us with genuine courtesy that the monastery was not open to visitors at this time of year.

“There are many visitors in summer, I regret,” he explained.

“Visitors! How do they get here?”

“By road; they come from long distances, driving and walking.”

“But we may never be here again; we are on our way to the Black Sea.”

“Ah, then you will see far more wonderful things than this in your journey.” He remained firm; so, by way of consolation we went to the Gasthaus Zur Zonne and enjoyed a meal—the first for a week that we had not cooked ourselves.

It was a quiet, out-of-the-world spot. Monks were everywhere working in the fields, ploughing and haymaking; and it was here I first saw sheep following a shepherd. A curious covered bridge, lined with crucifixes, crossed the river, and we took an interesting photograph of a monk in a black straw hat and gown going over it with a cloud of dust in the blazing sunshine followed by fifty sheep. There was contentment on all faces, but the place must be dreadfully lonely and desolate in winter. We bought immense loaves in the monks’ bakery, and matches, cigars, sugar, and meat in a devotionshandlung (store for religious articles)!

Sigmaringen, with its old rock-perched castle and its hundred turrets gleaming in the sun, was reached just in time to find shelter from a thunderstorm that seemed to come out of a clear sky. There was a hurricane of wind, and the rain filled the quaint old streets with dashing spray. In an hour it cleared away, and we pushed on again; but the river had meanwhile risen nearly a foot. The muddy water rushed by with turbulent eddies, and the bridges were crowded with people to see us pass. They stood in silent dark rows without gesture or remark, and stared.

Suddenly the storm broke again with redoubled fury. Up went their umbrellas, and we heard their guttural laughter. In a few minutes we were soaked, and no doubt cut a sorry figure as we launched the canoe at the foot of the big weir and vanished into the gathering darkness. We swirled between the pillars of another bridge in sheets of rain and the outlook for a dry camp and a fire was decidedly poor. It was after nine o’clock when we landed in despair under a clump of trees on the left bank, and found to our delight that they concealed a solitary wedge of limestone cliff, and that in this cliff there was an arch, and under that arch a quantity of dry wood. A fire was soon blazing in the strip under the arch—some three feet wide—and the tent stood beneath the dripping trees. Our waterproof sheets and cork mattresses kept us dry, though all night the rain poured down, while outside we could hear the swollen river rushing past with a seething roar.

Next day the rapids began in earnest. Rapids are to canoers what fences are to fox-hunters. The first wave curls over in front of the canoe, there is a hiss and a bump, a slap of wet spray in the face, and then the canoe leaps under you and rushes headlong. At Riedlingen, while carrying the canoe across a slippery weir, we fell, boat and all, into the deep hole below the fall, luckily with no worse result than a wetting, for our kit was safely piled upon the bank. At Dietfurt we went into an apparently deserted village to buy milk, but the moment we entered the street it became alive. From every door poured men and women gaping, and the moment they spied the little yellow canoe upon the shore they rushed down in a flock shouting “E’ schiff! E’ schiff!” But, if they ran fast, we ran faster, and were off before the terrible onslaught of questions had even begun. The milk was a mere detail.

At Gutenstein, where we camped in a hayfield, the mowers woke us at dawn, peering into the mouth of the tent. But they made no objections and merely said “Gruss Gott” and “Gute Reise;” and for an hour afterwards I heard their scythes musically in my dreams as they cut a pathway for us to the river.

At Obermarchtal we left the mountains behind us, and with them, too, the memory of a pathetic figure. As we landed to go up to the little inn for eggs, an old man, leaning on a stick, hobbled down to meet us. His white hair escaped in disorder from beneath a peaked blue hat, and he wore a suit of a curious checked pattern that seemed wholly out of keeping with the dress of the country. At first, when he spoke, I could not understand him, and asked him in German to repeat his remarks.

“He’s talking English,” said my companion. “Can’t you hear?” And English it was. He invited us up to the inn and told us his story over a mug of beer.

“This is my native village. I was born and raised here, and sixty years ago I ran away from Germany to escape military service. I went to the United States and settled finally in Alabama. I had a shop in Mobile, down South in a nigger town, and as soon as I was ready I wrote to the girl I left here to come out to me. She came and we were married. I’ve had two wives since out there. Now they’re all buried in a little churchyard outside Mobile. And this is the first time I’ve been back in sixty years,” he went on after a gulp of beer. “The village ain’t changed one single bit. I feel as though I’d been sleepin’ and sorter dreamin’ all the while. … The shop’s sold and I’m takin’ a last look round at the ole place. There’s only one or two that remembers me, but I was born and raised here, and this is where I had my first love, and the place is full of memories, just chock full. No, I ain’t a goin’ to live here. I’m goin’ back to the States nex’ month, so as I can die there and lie beside the others in the cemetery at Mobile.”

The country became flatter and the mountains were soon a blue line on the horizon behind us. At Opfingen we crossed our last weir, and among the clouds in front of us saw the spire of Ulm cathedral, the tallest in the world. A fierce current swept us past banks fringed with myrtle bushes, poppies, and yellow flags. Poplars rose in lines over the country, bending their heads in the wind, and we camped at eight o’clock in a wood about a mile above the town. While dinner was cooking a dog rushed barking up to us followed by three men with guns. They were evidently German jager. Two of them were dressed like pattern plates out of a tailor’s guide to sportsmen—in spotless gaiters, pointed hats with feathers (like stage Tyrolese), guns with the latest slings, and silver whistles slung on coloured cord round their necks. They examined the canoe first, and then came up and examined us. One of them, who was probably the proprietor of the land, a surly gruff fellow, had evidently made up his mind that we were poachers. And I must admit that at first sight there was ground for suspicion, for no poacher could possibly have found fault with our appearance.

“What are you doing here?” he asked.

“Preparing to camp for the night,” we told him.

“When are you going on?”

“We intend to go into Ulm in the morning.”

“Where do you come from; are you Englishmen?”

“Yes; we come from London.”

“Ach was!” (they all say Ach was when they want to be witheringly scornful). “In that eggshell?”

“Certainly.”

“And where are you going to?”

“Odessa.”

They exchanged glances. “Evidently madmen, and not poachers,” said the face of the man with the biggest silver whistle plainer than any words could have spoken it. “Do you know these are private preserves?” was the next question.

“No.” My friend, a keen sportsman, sheltered himself scowling behind his alleged ignorance of German, (somehow he always knew our conversation afterwards to a word); but the penny whistle and the immaculate costume of the hunters in a scrubby wood where not even a rabbit lived, excited him to explosions of laughter which he concealed by frequent journeys to the tent.

“What’s in that tent?”

“Beds.” The chasseurs and the keeper went to examine, while the dog sniffed about everywhere. Our beds were not then untied, and the sportsman untied them; but they found only blankets and cork mattresses.

“You have no guns, or dogs, or fishing rods?” We shook our heads sulkily. “And you are only travelling peacefully for pleasure?”

“We are trying to,” we said meekly.

“Then you may sleep here if you go on again tomorrow; but don’t go into the woods after game.” Then the men moved off. Doubtless they were right to ask questions, yet we were so obviously travellers. “Still, our weatherworn appearance and unshaved faces probably made us look more than a little doubtful,” quoth my friend, who himself wore a slouch hat that did not add to the candour of his expression.

In the middle of dinner the men suddenly returned from another angle of the wood and examined everything afresh. We offered them some tea in a tin cup which they declined; and at last after watching us at our meal in silence for ten minutes they moved off, evidently still suspicious. Thereafter we always knew them as the chasseurs. They were not the only pests, however. Mosquitoes appeared later—our first—and that night we slept behind the mosquito-netting we had so carefully fitted to the mouth of the tent when we first erected it weeks before in the garden of a London square. During the night someone prowled about the tent. We heard twigs snapping and the footsteps among the bushes; but neither of us troubled ourselves to get up. If they took the canoe, they’d be drowned; and our other only valuables (a celluloid collar apiece, a clean suit for the big towns, and a map,) were safely inside the tent.

In the morning we shaved and washed carefully, and put on our full dress for the benefit of Ulm. We intended to paddle down quietly and stop at the Rowing Club wharf of which we had read; according to the map it was a mile, and the current easy and pleasant. We wished our entrance to be sober and in good taste. The best-laid plans, however, will sometimes go amiss when you’re canoeing on the Danube. We were halfway when we heard a roar like a train rushing over a hollow bridge. It grew louder every minute. In front of us the water danced and leaped, and before we knew what had happened we were plunging about among foaming waves and flying past the banks at something more than ten miles an hour.

“It’s the Iller,” cried my friend as the paddle was nearly wrested from his grasp. “It’s marked on the map just about here.”

It was the Iller. It had come in at an acute angle after running almost parallel with us for a little distance. It tumbled in at headlong speed, with an icy, turbulent flood of muddy water, and it gave the sedate Danube an impetus that it did not lose for another hundred miles below Ulm. For a space the two rivers declined to mingle. The noisy, dirty Iller, fresh from the Alps, kept to the right bank, going twice as fast as its more dignified companion on the left. A distinct line (as though drawn by a rope) divided them, in colour, speed, and height—the Iller remaining for a long time at least half an inch above the level of the Danube. At length they mingled more freely and swept us down upon Ulm in a torrent of rough, racing water. Our leisurely dignified entrance into Ulm was, like the suspicions of the chasseurs, a structure built on insufficient knowledge, a mere dream. Ulm lies on a curve of the river. Big bridges with nasty thick pillars (and whirlpools, therefore, behind them) stand at both entrance and exit. How we raced under the first bridge I shall never forget. We were halfway through the town, with the wet spray still on our cheeks, before the sound of the gurgling eddies below the bridge had ceased behind us. Where, oh, where was the friendly wharf of that Danube Rowing Club? The second bridge rose before us. There were crested waves under its arches. Already Ulm was almost a thing of the past; yet we had hoped to spend at least a week exploring its beauties.

“There it is,” cried my friend in the bows, “on the left bank! That old board—see it? That’s the wharf.”

We managed to turn in mid current and point the canoe upstream. Then, by paddling as hard as we could, we dropped down past the wharf at a pace that just enabled us to grasp the rings in the boards and come to a standstill. You’ll never forget Ulm if you arrive there, as we did, in a canoe, when the Iller is in flood.

II

We spent a week in the quaint old town of Ulm, but our adventures there have properly no part in our journey down the river. Only, in passing, I must mention the courtesy of the Danube Rowing Club. Fritz Miller (who rowed at Henley in 1900 for the Diamond Sculls) is the leading spirit in a list of members who showed us all possible kindness. They housed and mended our canoe, varnished it afresh, and gave us better maps. The secret charms of picturesque Ulm unknown to the tourist were shown to us; and in the evenings we used to meet for music and supper in a quaint little clubroom that hangs half of its Roman masonry over the rushing river.

Here the navigation of the Danube (such as it is) is said to begin. The fierce current allows no boats or steamers, but immense barges (called Ulmer schachtel) laden with merchandise, are floated down the current to the Bavarian towns below. On arrival they are sold for lumber, the return journey being impossible.

The Rowing Club takes out eights and fours. Rowing with all their might they move two miles an hour against the current; and it may well be imagined that, with this training, they are well-nigh the first rowing club in Germany.

There was a great deal of rain while we were in Ulm and we started again on a rapidly rising river, full of floating rubbish, and rushing at a pace that made it a pleasure merely to stand and watch it from the bank.

The Bavarian bank (Ulm is on the frontier line of Bavaria and Würtemburg) displayed black signboards with the kilometers marked in white. We timed our speed by one of Benson’s chronometers and found it to be over twelve miles an hour. It was like travelling over a smooth road behind fast horses. My notebook gives an average day, the day, for instance, we left Ulm.

June 19th. The members of the Rowing Club came down in force to see us off at eleven o’clock. Flags were flying in our honour and we heard the men shouting glückliche Reise as we shot the middle arch of the bridge on the waves of a rather nasty rapid. The bridge was lined with people, but we only faintly heard their cries for the thunder of the waves. This exceedingly rapid water makes awkward currents as it swirls round the pillars of the big bridges. Behind the arches are always whirlpools, which twist you sideways and toss you from them with ridiculous ease. A wrong turn of the steering paddle and the canoe would be sucked in instead of thrown out, and then—! At a little distance below the bridge the eddies of the whirlpool from adjacent pillars meet in a series of crested waves. The only safe channel lies exactly in the middle. The canoe rises, slaps down again, all its length a-quiver; the first wave breaks under the bows and some of the water comes in, but before enough is shipped to be dangerous the frail craft rises again with a leap to the next wave. Then the race begins. The least wrong twist to left or right and the waves break sideways into the canoe and down she goes. It takes so little water to sink a laden canoe.

Today, for the first time, we heard the famous song of the Danube—famous at least to us who had read of it in so many different accounts. It is a hissing, seething sound which rises everywhere from the river. You think steam must be escaping somewhere, or soda-water fizzing out from an immense syphon among the woods on the banks. It is said to be the friction of the pebbles along the bed of the river, caused by the terrific speed of so great a body of water. Under the canoe it made a peculiar buzzing sound accompanied by a distinct vibration of the thin basswood on which we knelt.

We swept through Bavaria much faster than we wished, but it was impossible to go slowly. The river communicated something of its hurry to ourselves, and in my mind the journey now presents itself something in the form of a series of brilliant cineomatographs. Delightful were our lunches at the quaint inns of remote villages—black bread, sausage, and such beer!—Lauingen, a town of the sixteenth century, where the spokesman of the crowd said, “I suppose you’re both single;” Donauworth, in a paradise of wild flowers, where the Lech tears in on the right with leaping waves; Neuberg, with a dangerous stone bridge and the worst rapids we had yet encountered. Then a long stretch where the swamps ceased and the woods began to change. Instead of endless willows we had pine, oak, sycamore, birch, and poplar. The river was a mile wide with outlets into lagoons, like Norfolk Broads, that ran parallel with us for miles and were probably empty mud flats at low water. Fishing-nets were hanging up to dry along the shore, and hay lay sunning itself on the narrow strips of the banks. We passed Ingolstadt, a military post, and then the river dipped down before us into blue hills and we came to Vohburg—destroyed by the Swiss in 1641, and now, apparently, nothing but a collection of quaint chimneys and storks’ nests—and, soon after it, Eining, near Abusina, a Roman frontier station established fifteen years before our era. Trajan’s wall crossed the river near here and extended north as far as Wiesbaden.

Then the river narrowed between precipitous limestone cliffs and we entered the gorge of Kehlheim. At its very mouth, between impregnable rocks, lay the monastery of Weltenburg, the oldest in Bavaria. The river sweeping round a bend into the rocky jaws made landing difficult; but we accomplished it, and entered the old courtyard through an iron gate with graceful stone pillars. There were everywhere signs of neglect and decay. The monks’ quarters formed one side of the square and the church another; a third side was a wall of rock; the fourth was the river. It was secluded, peaceful beyond description, absolutely out of the world. The air was cool, the shadows deep. Fruit-trees grew in the courtyard, and monks (there were only thirteen in all) in black gowns were piling up wood for the winter. A priest was intoning vespers in the church, which boasted a beautiful organ, marble altars, and elaborate carving of the usual gilded sort. The sunshine filled the painted air. Outside over the neglected walls crept vines, and at the far end of the courtyard a wild rose-tree, covered with sweet-smelling blossoms, grew at the foot of crumbling stone steps that led under shady trees to a chapel perched on the cliffs. We toiled up in the heat and were rewarded by a glorious view; from above the monastery was shut in like a nest between river and cliffs.

Later in the day we were driven by a violent thunderstorm to the first landing-place we could find. It was a few miles below Weltenburg in the very heart of the gorge. With surprising good fortune we found a cave leading deep into the mountain, and in less than ten minutes we were dry and snug before a fire burning cheerfully for dinner. It was a camp—the storm howling outside and the firelight dancing down behind us into the interior of the cave, which was unnecessarily full of bats.

At Batisbon, the Castra Regina of the Romans, we were solemnly warned not to attempt to pass under the bridge. “The whirlpools are savage,” they told us. “Of the seven arches of this six-hundred-year-old bridge, all but one are forbidden by the police.” Leaving the canoe half a mile above we landed and walked down the shore to examine. “Boats have gone through,” said a pompous man on the bridge as he pointed out the worst places to us, “but even if they got under the arch they have always been sucked in there!” He pointed to a white seething circle of water. “You’ll never get through that in your cockleshell, and you’ll be arrested even if you do.”

“Arrested—how?” we asked. By way of answer he raised his eyebrows and held up a fat hand in eloquent warning. However, we carefully selected our channel from the bridge, and twenty minutes later were coming down stream towards the arches as cautiously as our speed would permit. People ran along the shore waving their hats and shouting to us to stop. The bridge in front was black with the crowd waiting to see the verrückte Engländer upset. We reached the arch and recognised our channel. The water dropped suddenly in front of us and the canoe dipped her nose with it. We were off. The bank and the shouting people flew past us in a black streak. I was just able to recognise one man, our pompous friend, standing below the bridge shading his eyes with his hand, evidently determined to get the best view possible. The roar of voices dwindled behind us into a murmur and a minute later we were out of sight; Batisbon, bridge, whirlpools, and townsfolk were things of the past. We were not arrested, but perhaps the police are still trying to catch us.

After this came a dull spell as we crossed the great wheat-plain of Bavaria, winding for two days with many curves and little current. Every morning here the workers in the fields woke us early, and praised the boat, and asked us the usual questions, and told us the usual falsehoods about the depth of the river, the distances of the towns, the floods of past years, and all the rest of it. We made no halt at Straubing (Servio Durum of the Romans), or at Deggendorf where the Isar adds its quota of mountain-gathered waters.

Another day was very dismal—cold showers and storms of wind following one upon another. We crouched under bridges, trees, and anything else that gave cover, paddling fast between the squalls to keep ourselves warm. The plain of Straubing affords little shelter. Towards evening, however, the river made a welcome turn towards the mountains, and we camped on a high bank among clumps of willows with thick woods behind them. New potatoes, dried prunes, and onions in the stew-pot were points of light in a gusty and otherwise dismal meal. We pegged the tent inside and out. All night the wind tore at it, howling; but a gypsy-tent never comes down. The wind sweeps over it, and finding an ever lessening angle of resistance, only drives it more firmly into the ground.

Gradually, now, we were passing out of the lonely portions of the upper river. The country was becoming more populated; larger towns were near; railway-bridges spanned the river; steamers and tugs raced down, and toiled up it.

A few miles above Passau we camped on an island, and were visited by an inquisitive peasant, who saw our fire and came over from the mainland in a punt. “Are we trespassing?” I asked. “No; the island’s usually under water.” This was all he ever said in our hearing, though he stayed with us, it seemed, for hours. He was a surly-looking fellow in the roughest clothes, with trousers turned up to his knees, and bare feet. His curiosity was immense; with arms crossed and legs wide apart, he stood and stared in silence with expressionless features. We had some villainous Black Forest cigars, bearing on the label the words la noblesse, which we sometimes used to get rid of obnoxious people. We gave him two. Knowing nothing about the Greeks and those bearing gifts he nodded his thanks—and smoked both to the very end! Yet he never stirred, his eyes never left us. It was impossible to prepare our frugal dinner under this merciless scrutiny. At length I prevailed upon him to go over for some eggs, and to bring them to us in the morning for breakfast. He left without a word in his punt, and a sense of oppression seemed to go with him. But, just as dinner was over and we were settling round the fire to our tobacco, he suddenly reappeared. He had brought the eggs in his hat, and he was dressed this time in his Sunday clothes! For an hour he stood beside the fire, answering no questions, volunteering no remarks, till at length my friend went up, shook hands, wished him good night, and straightway disappeared into the tent. I did likewise, and then the fellow took the hint, and went.

This happened at a place called Pleinling. Another thing also happened there. On the smaller of the arms into which our island divided the river was a weir. With empty canoe, and dressed in shirt and trousers, we practised shooting this weir next morning. The day was hot, and our other things were meanwhile drying on the bank. The silent peasant came over to watch the proceedings, and with him came a picturesque old fellow, most talkative and entertaining, with white hair and a face like Liszt’s. When he saw us preparing to shoot the fall he was much excited. “Have you wives and children?” he asked shaking his head warningly. I went over first while my friend took the camera, and got his picture a second before the canoe plunged into the foam and upset. The old fellow, whose name was Jacob Meyer, was not in the least put out. He leaned on his scythe and watched me struggling in the water with the overturned canoe without making any effort to help. Afterwards, when we gave him a noblesse he took a lean, dirty little purse out of his pocket, and said, “How much am I to pay for it?” And when we promised to send him the photographs he asked the same question again.

Some hours later we reached Passau, a few miles from the Austrian frontier, and this last glimpse of Bavaria, after traversing its entire breadth, was the sweetest of all. But only from the river itself can you see the quaint old houses leaning over at all imaginable angles; the towers and crooked wooden balconies; gardens hanging from the second storeys; walls with ancient paintings dimmed by wind and weather; and decayed archways showing vistas of tumbling roofs, broken chimneys, and peeps of vivid blue sky at the far ends. The picture it made in my mind as we paddled through it in the late afternoon is uncommonly picturesque—a jumble of gables, towers, bridges, and the swift muddy Danube rushing past it all in such tremendous hurry.

Half a mile below, the Inn poured in from the Tyrolese Alps and carried us into the finest gorge we had so far seen. The newcomer brought cold air with it, and we swept into the gloomy ravine between high mountains with something like a genuine shudder. More and more swiftly ran the river as it compressed itself with an angry roar into a few hundred yards’ width and swirled into the hills raging at the indignity thus heaped upon it. It became very difficult now to choose camping-places, as the stream fills the entire gorge, leaving only narrow ledges at the foot of the heights where a tent can stand. Upon one of these ledges, broader than the rest, we managed at length to land. A projecting point of rock sent the water flying out at a tangent into midstream and formed a strong backwater below it. Into this we contrived to twist the canoe’s nose and on a little promontory, covered with yellow ragwort, we pitched our tent. It commanded a view for two miles up the ravine with the sinking sun at the far end. A boy was tending half a dozen cows among the scanty bushes; a queer little imp with wide-open blue eyes, who watched us land and prepare our camp with no signs of fear or surprise. We gave him cherries and chocolate, and he stuffed his mouth with one and his pockets with the other; then he came and stood over our fire and warmed himself without invitation, as if it had been made for his special benefit. A quaint little figure he cut with his pointed, feathered hat and big eyes. He told us that his name was Josef, that he lived two miles further on, went to bed every night at nine o’clock and got up every morning at four. Then he took off his hat, said good night, and vanished into the bushes after his cows.

The sun set in a blaze of golden light that filled the whole gorge with fire; but when the glory faded, the strange grandeur of the place began to make itself felt. The ravine was filled with strange noises, the wooded heights looked forbidding, and the great river rolled in a sullen black flood into the night.

Next morning we passed a big rock in midstream with a shrine perched on its summit; and just beyond it we entered Austria and visited the customs at Engelhartzell, a village on the right bank with an old Cistercian monastery behind it. There was no duty to pay, and we raced on past the mountain village of Obermühl, and out of the gorge into a fertile and undulating country basking in the fierce sunshine.

Neuhaus, with a fine castle on a wooded height, and Ashach, with a view of the Styrian Alps, flashed by. The river from here to Linz is full of history, and its muddy waters have more than once borne crimson foam. There were bloody fights here during the revolt of the peasantry of Upper Austria. Ashach, in 1626, was the insurgents’ headquarters where (as also at Neuhaus) they barricaded the Danube with immense chains to prevent the Bavarians from assisting Count Herberstein, the Austrian governor, who was shut up in Linz. When in flood the Danube escapes from this narrow prison with untold violence. Everywhere the villages bear witness of its path, though most of them lie far away from the banks. High upon the walls lines show the high-water marks of previous years with the dates. “A single night will often send us into the upper storeys,” said a woman who sold us milk and eggs; “but the water falls as quickly as it rises, and then we come down again.” She took it as a matter of course.

The shores became lonely again and our camps were rarely disturbed. One morning, however, about six o’clock we heard someone rummaging among our pans. Then something stumbled heavily against the tent, and there was a sound of many feet and an old familiar smell. We rushed out, to find ourselves in the centre of a herd of about fifty cows. One had its nose in the provision-basket; another was drinking the milk standing in the pail of water; a third was scratching its head against the iron prop of the kettle. Their curiosity was insatiable; every time we drove them off they returned. While my friend was frying the bacon and I was performing ablutions lower down on the river bank, a squadron swept down upon us unexpectedly by a clever flank movement, and one of them whipped up my pyjamas near the tent and ran down the shore with them on her horns. My friend dared not leave the bacon—and I was in nudis! It was exciting for the next few minutes.

In blazing heat that day we came to Linz, the capital of Upper Austria. Below it the Traun and the Enns flowed in, and the Danube became a magnificent river rolling through broad banks alternately wooded and covered with crops and orchards; and now, too, we begin again to see vineyards, of which Bavaria had seemed bare.

For a long time, strange as it may sound, we had been enforced vegetarians and drinkers of condensed milk. We could rarely get fresh milk, though we trudged many a mile to farmhouses and inns for it; either it was all used for butter, or had already been sent to the towns. Of course it would not keep sweet in our canoe under the blazing heat, and we could only trust to the chance of getting it an hour or so before we needed it. But, when we were lucky enough to get it, how delicious were those messes of boiled bread and milk! Meat, too, was hard to come at, except at certain hours. The butchers in the small towns open their shops at certain times only. Not one of them would ever trouble himself to supply us with merely a pound of meat, and more would not, of course, keep fresh.

We were drawing near Vienna now, but first we passed through another fine gorge. It began at Grein (where the Duke of Coburg’s castle, Greinburg, looks down from the heights) and before we emerged breathless at the other end we had come through the famous whirlpools known as the Wirbel and Strudel. The river, narrowed by half its width, plunged with many contortions round sharp corners between high cliffs and past the island-rock of Wörth. Rising in long, heaving undulations the water was alive with whirlpools, twisting and sucking, and throwing us here and there, gushing up underneath us with ugly noises and seething on every side. There was no foam, no crests, no waves or spray; it was like a monstrous snake trying to writhe through a hole too small for it. The shore raced by at top speed, and steering was uncomfortable for a time. In former years these whirlpools were a source of great danger to the navigation; but in 1866 the Emperor had certain rocks blown up and now an inscription on the face of the cliff testifies to the thanks of a grateful people. The traveller in a big steamer might think this description exaggerated. He would not think so in a canoe.

It is impossible to mention, as one would like, all the abbeys, churches, monasteries, ruins, islands, and other points of historic interest that throng the banks. The scenery is enchanting as well as enchanted. There were some interesting castles in these mountains, and grim they still look even in their ruins. Aggstein rose in solitary grandeur on a peak that commanded miles of the Danube in both directions. It was built in the twelfth century by the Kuenings, a robber-race which stretched chains across the river, plundered the traffic, and drowned the owners. We could still see the Blashaus Tower from which the sentinel announced the approach of boats. Its was a plundering, murdering family, and was finally destroyed by the great Ulrich von Grafeneck.

Before Ybbs (the Roman Pons Isidis) we saw the wonderful ruins of Dürrenstein where Richard Cceur de Lion was imprisoned. Here, on the very spot, it was interesting to recall how he was recognised when walking through the fields at Erdberg (since merged in Vienna), captured, and handed over to his enemy, Duke Leopold of Austria, who entrusted him in turn to the keeping of the Kuenings. They kept him for fifteen months (1193) in the great castle of Dürrenstein beneath whose grim walls we passed in our canoe. In Austria the story is implicitly believed, whatever we may think of it in England.

The following day we saw the blue hills of the Wienerwald rising behind Vienna, and before long we were obliged to don our best clothes, and send a porter down from our hotel to fetch the luggage from the bathing-house where the canoe lay below the Reichsbrücke.

We did not stay long in Vienna. Rooms in July seem stuffy after a tent, and a fly-spotted ceiling is a poor substitute for the stars.

The canoe was packed full of provisions ready to start when our first accident occurred. The river had risen a couple of feet and was very swift. My friend had just taken off his shoes and placed them on the top of the other luggage. Several of the crowd, in their misguided fashion, were trying to help us, when I stepped into the little space vacant for me in the stern. How it happened no one knew; someone let go too soon, and she was instantly swept out sideways into the current. The next second I was dropped out neatly into five feet of water, and the canoe, settling till only the tops of the luggage remained in sight, went full tilt down stream. There were fifty yards of clear water, and then came a row of barges tied ten feet from the shore and leaving an inner channel. Into this the canoe luckily was swept; had she careered off into midstream probably we should never have seen her again. With boat-hooks and poles we ran along the banks to catch her before she banged into the barges. My friend ran in his socks. The hotel-porter, the bathhouse man, and a dozen idlers all followed shouting different things at once. But the canoe and the mad current had the start of us. Crash! with a sound of rending, splintering wood she banged into the nearest barge and turned completely over. A few seconds later the various articles appeared on the surface again, and there began a sort of obstacle-race that might have been highly comical had it not been so serious. Our beds with the cork mattresses floated high out of the water. Jumbo (a huge kit-bag holding our wardrobe) came next, up to his neck. A smaller waterproof bag, tied at the neck and holding bread and cameras, followed, spinning merrily. The provision basket (filled with the morning’s careful shopping and some tea just arrived from England) showed only its nose above the surface. Coats, hats, socks, maps, tent-poles and tent followed in motley array at the end of an idiotic looking procession. Every time an article banged into a barge it went under for a few seconds, and meanwhile the canoe was crashing on among ropes and poles in the van. The heavy articles defied our efforts, and Jumbo pulled one man bodily into the water when he tried to drag it ashore.

In the end, however, most of the things were saved. The men caught the canoe as she spun past a barge, and held her till help came. All the articles, too, were fished out except those that would not float. Thus, we lost our lantern, the prop of the kettle, a pair of my friend’s shoes, an odd one of mine, the ridgepole of the tent, and my town hat and coat. It was wonderfully little. The bows of the canoe, however, were completely smashed in; and to make it worse, the rain suddenly came down in torrents and a cold wind blew from the north.

Then a carpenter appeared on the scene and said he could mend the canoe and make a new tent-pole. The people of the bathhouse took our things in to dry, while we jumped into a closed carriage and drove back into Vienna, my friend with no shoes on his feet, and I without a hat on my head. Yet, such was our good luck, that three hours later we were spinning down the river in the mended canoe; the sun was shining brightly, our things were dried, we had a new tent-pole, Vienna was out of sight below the horizon—and when we landed for camp the place was so lonely that, on climbing the bank, I looked straight into the eyes of a great stag with branching antlers.

For two days at racing speed we journeyed through wild and lonely country towards the frontiers of Hungary. The river was like a wide lake—no houses, no boats, no token of man except the daily steamer between Vienna and Budapest. We passed signs of Roman days and Turkish occupancy strangely mingled: Carnuntum, where Marcus Aurelius is said to have written much of his philosophy; Theben on a spur of the little Carpathians, with its rock-perched fortress destroyed by the Turks in 1683 when they swept on to besiege Vienna, and again by the French in 1809. At its very feet the March (the boundary between Austria and Hungary) comes sedately in, and the Danube received a new impetus as we passed below its shadow and into Hungary at last.

The Germans had been kind in a negative fashion, the Bavarians courteous, the Austrians obliging; but the hospitality of the Hungarians was positively aggressive. “Nothing is too much,” they used to declare when we expostulated with them on the overwhelming nature of their attentions, “nothing is too good for Englishmen. Everybody will tell you the same in Hungary.” Kossuth was the magical word, and hatred of the Austrians the keynote of their emotions. We blessed the generation that had welcomed him in exile and went on our way rejoicing. The crowds no longer stood gaping; they helped without being asked. When we landed for provisions they ran down to hold the canoe, while others went into the village to make our purchases more cheaply for us. Even their questions were intelligent. German is of uncertain value here, and we had carefully learned the Magyar words for the articles we most needed. “Now you begin to learn Magyar when it is too late,” laughed the woman in a Pressburg shop where we bought milk and eggs and bacon; “but it’s no matter: you can’t starve in Hungary.” The Hungarian name of the town is Pozsony. It was formerly the capital, where the kings of the Hapsburg race were crowned. Below it the Danube branches into three arms, one of which makes a circuit of fifty miles and comes in again at Komorn. The main river is a couple of miles wide and full of islands, separated by rapids and falls. An officer assured us that we should get lost for days together unless we carefully kept to the main channel. The country is utterly deserted, save for the little black landing-stages of the steamers that appear every twenty miles or so, the villages lying far back and protected by high earthen banks. The loneliness and desolation of these vast reaches of turbulent river and low willow-clad islands were impressive; in flood-time it must be grand.

The water escaped into so many side channels and lagoons that the depth of the river was most variable. Grey shingle-beds appeared often in midstream, and over and over again we were swept into them before we could cross to deeper water. It was difficult to distinguish them in time from the muddy, foam-streaked river, until we learned that the cormorants invariably used them for fishing grounds; and then we took the black bodies in the distance as warning signals that saved us much dangerous wading. The velocity of the stream is so great that one almost expects to see the islands swept bodily away. Big grey hawks circled ever over head and grey crows by the thousand lined the shores. That evening, after crossing and recrossing the river, we found a sheltered camp on a sandy island where pollards and willows roared in the wind. As if to show the loneliness of the spot an otter, rolling over and over among the eddies, swam past us as we landed. About sunset the clouds broke up momentarily and let out a flood of crimson light all over the wild country. Against the gorgeous red sky a stream of dark clouds, in all shapes and kinds, hurried over the Carpathian mountains, and when we went to bed a full moon cast the queerest shadows through the tossing branches. We dined—prosaic detail!—off tongue, onions, potatoes, tea, and dried prunes which we stewed and ate with quantities of beetroot sugar.

Next day the river grew wider, swifter, and even more deserted. At Korteljes we landed to buy provisions, though only the watchman’s hut was in sight. As we stepped on shore my hat blew off and floated down stream. At once the man (who spoke a little German) went into his hut and produced one of his own which he begged me to wear; it was a greasy wide-brimmed felt, but I could not refuse it, and he seemed delighted. He directed us to a farm a mile inland for milk and eggs, and gave us the correct pronounciation of the necessary words. The farm stood on the broad plain in a grove of acacia trees, with snow-white walls and overhanging thatched roofs, forming a square, within which were oxen, buffaloes, pigs, geese, and romping children in brilliant skirts. The older girls had yellow kerchiefs on their heads; one little girl, in flaming colours, was chasing a chicken in and out among the trees and oxen; all stopped to stare as we approached, swinging an empty milk-can. Through the farmhouse door I got a glimpse into a spotless kitchen, and a most courteous woman with brilliant dark eyes sold us what we required very cheaply. I took off my new greasy hat to them when we left, and the children followed us to the river, a motley escort.

On we went down the great rushing stream, ever flanked by a sea of silvery willows swaying and bending in the wind, reed beds, ten feet high, alternating with stretches of grey shingle. Between the wooded islands vistas opened in all directions; narrow glades where the river sent out new arms in patches of sunshine with the faint sound of water tumbling over distant shallows; while down some far blue reach, filled with the afternoon shadows, we could see immense herds of cattle, swine, and flocks of geese, feeding in meadows lined with poplars and birch trees. Horses in vast quantities roamed along the banks, watched by herdsmen who wore cool white skirts instead of trousers. Often, in the backwaters, oxen, horses, buffalo, pigs, and geese were all crowded together trying to keep cool in the great heat.

At Komorn, rising with its fortress just above the dead level of the plain, we laid in provisions. The grocer was inquisitive: “Where have you come from? Where are you going to? How do you cook? Where do you sleep? Are you not afraid of grasshoppers and snakes? What an awful distance you have come—the source of the Danube, where is it? You are both quite young, aren’t you? But you are so enormous,”—and so on, and so on.

From here we saw the blue mountains that encircle Budapest—not more than forty miles away as a crow would fly it, but a splendid loop of sixty-five miles by the river. Budapest draws one like a magnet. There is a suggestion of delicious wildness about it born of I know not what. The very name seems set to some flying fragment of the wild national music—a bar of the csárdás, or of the wailing Hungarian songs that thrill with such intense virility. The West, too, sinks lower on the horizon when Budapest is reached, and the Danube sweeps you on through the Iron Gates to Turkey and the Fekete Tengerig (Black Sea).

Willows, reeds, and islands have all vanished now, and there were no sudden whirlpools in midstream. With majestic dignity that disguised the real speed, the mass of water, a mile to a mile and a half wide, swept steadily down under that fierce heat towards the mountains. We kept to midstream and were never tired of watching the banks slip by with their ever changing pictures: open shore; fields with barley standing in sheaves; vineyards coming down to the water’s edge; cottages with thick thatch and white walls; villages full of wild, overgrown gardens, and groves of acacia trees of brilliant washed green. We landed for milk at a farmhouse on the right bank and found that the proprietor spoke English and had travelled in England and Norway and studied in Vienna. “It’s only twenty-six kilometers to Budapest,” he told us. Later on we overtook some peasants in a boat full of vegetables, and kept pace with them for a little, while we chatted in German. “It’s a little over forty kilometers to Pest,” they said. Boats became frequent after this, broad, flat-bottomed, laden with farm-produce, and rowed by men and women who took their hats off to us and asked many questions in bad German. All agreed on one thing—that the Austrians were a poor lot of people compared with the Hungarians; and all differed on another thing—the distance to Budapest. It varied with every boat, and at length we became so confused with the arguments of the spokesman in German and the mocking chorus of the rest in Hungarian, that we almost expected to hear that we had already passed it, or were perhaps on the wrong river altogether.

To avoid calamities we increased our speed and left the string of boats behind. In the afternoon we came to Gran. The dome of its huge Italian basilica dominates for miles the plain we had just traversed, but looks like a round gleaming pebble beside the mountains that rise behind it. The charms of this quaint little town made us realise that time is after all but a form of thought; in other words, we stayed too long. At half-past six we entered the wide deep valley of these magical mountains hoping to find a camping-place so soon as we were beyond the town. The sun was hidden; the mountains stood outlined in purple against a wonderful sky, with long thin clouds just touching some of the higher peaks; the water glowed as though fires burned beneath the waves. Mile after mile we followed the windings of the valley, the hills folding up behind us, but opening ever in front again into new and darker distances. But no camping-place appeared; one side was too steep, the other treeless. The shadows lengthened and grew deeper; the hills changed from purple to black; the lights of villages twinkled across the river as across a wide lake. They fairly lined the base of the hills, and secluded camping-spots were evidently things of the past; there was not even an island.

Eight, nine o’clock passed; it became too dark to cross or recross with safety. We hugged the left bank, eagerly scanning the shore under the steep hills and waiting for the moon to rise. It was ten o’clock when the moon topped the mountains of the other shore and filled the valley with silver. We found a level yard or two below some vineyards, unpleasantly close to the abode of the proprietor, and there made a small fire and dined late off eggs and cocoa. The scenery was more thrilling than the meal: the dim hills rising through the moonlight; the white river filling the space between as if the whole valley were sliding noiselessly past, the fragrant air, warm and still, shot here and there with fireflies—and Hungary—wild, musical, enchanted Hungary! The fire had died down and we were smoking at the mouth of the tent when sounds of music floated to our ears, and presently a barge of peasants towed by three men along the shore came slowly up the stream. Cymbals and violins were playing a national air and a few low voices were singing. The barge floated past as if no one had seen us, and the music died away in the distance.

And on the mere the wailing died away.

Several hours later the returning voices and violins woke us in the tent as the party went down again too far from shore to be visible to the eye.

A man fishing woke us early and asked if the weinhüter (watchman of vineyards) had not disturbed us. Luckily he had not. “That’s because it’s Sunday and he’s overslept himself.” In spite of this warning we breakfasted leisurely, and then paddling down stream in blazing sunshine landed a mile below at Visegrad on the opposite bank. This little town, with its ruined castle, and fortress destroyed by the Austrians, nestles among the mountains, and here the good folk of Budapest come in summer to their villas among the acacia trees. Everybody spoke to us, helped to pull up the canoe, told us what to see, where to get good coffee or cooling drinks, described (with painful detail) the remaining twenty miles to Budapest, and showed themselves in all ways most courteous and obliging. Gypsy-music sounded everywhere among the trees, and the peasants in bright Sunday costumes lent colour to the scene.

Below Visegrad, which we left with much reluctance, begins an island which stretches the whole twenty miles to Budapest. Taking the inner channel we paddled peacefully all day under blue mountains in a haze of delicious heat, past villages, ferries, churches, castles, private villas, acres of vineyards over the slopes of the hills, and vast herds of horses and oxen standing in the water, till we camped at sunset on a treeless bit of plain at the extreme point of the island, only a mile from Budapest. It was like camping on the Brighton downs. With difficulty we collected scraps of wood enough to make a fire that would boil water. It was a windless night, and our candle stood tied to a stick in the open air with a motionless flame. The moon, rising late, showed rounded curves of bare hills behind us—and then, two figures approached us cautiously from the river. They came to the outside of the firelight circle and stopped; but at our invitation they came within and smoked the last of our noblesse cigars—poor fellows! Night-fishermen they were, short, thickset, dark-faced Huns. They drank our cocoa and explained their strange-looking nets to us while waiting for the moon to rise higher. All night long they fished, and on their way home to bed at five next morning they looked in to give us a hearty good morning and the information that the cows were coming.

The thunder of hoofs confirmed this, and we got up in time to protect the tent from a herd of several hundred cattle. A herder followed them, a dwarf-like creature with a poleaxe as big as himself, and a badge which proclaimed him government keeper of the plain (Crownland) where all men’s cattle might feed on certain conditions. He spoke no German, but he understood the meaning of a plate of veal, and he finished our meat (two pounds) in about ten minutes. Then he drank some cocoa, asking, with a wry face, if it were paprika (Hungarian pepper).

It was piping hot on the treeless plain, and Budapest lay waiting for us. We shaved and donned our town suits. The herder, grateful for his meal, helped to carry our things to the canoe, and, long after we were off, stood shading his eyes with his hand and staring after us. We drifted lazily down another mile of steaming hot river and landed at the wharf of the Hunnia Rowing Club on the right bank—nearly a thousand miles from the sleepy little village in the Black Forest where we had embarked six weeks before.

Dream Trespass

The little feathers of the dusk were drifting through the autumn leaves when we came so unexpectedly upon the inn that was not marked upon our big-scaled map. And most opportunely, for Ducommun, my friend, was clearly overtired. An irritability foreign to his placid temperament had made the last few hours’ trudge a little difficult, and I felt we had reached that narrow frontier which lies between non-success and failure.

“Another five miles to the inn we chose this morning,” I told him “but we’ll soon manage it at a steady pace.”

And he groaned, “I’m done! I simply couldn’t do it.” He sank down upon the bit of broken wall to rest, while the darkness visibly increased, and the wind blew damp and chill across the marshes on our left. But behind the petulance of his tone, due to exhaustion solely, lay something else as well, something that had been accumulating for days. For our walking tour had not turned out quite to measure, distances always under-calculated; the inns, moreover, bad; the people surly and inhospitable; even the weather cross.

And Ducommun’s disappointment had in a sense been double, so that I felt keen sympathy with him. For this was the country where his ancestors once reigned as proprietors, grand seigneurs, and the rest; he had always longed to visit it; and secretly in his imagination had cherished a reconstructed picture in which he himself would somehow play some high, distinguished role his proud blood entitled him to. Clerk to-day in a mere insurance office, but descendant of romantic, ancient stock, he knew the history of the period intimately; the holiday had been carefully, lovingly planned; and—the unpleasantness of the inhabitants had shattered his dream thus fostered and so keenly anticipated. The breaking-point had been reached. Was not this inn we hoped to reach by dark a portion of the very chateau—he had established it from musty records enough—where once his family dwelt in old-time splendour? And had he not indulged all manner of delightful secret dreaming in advance? . . .

It was here, then, returning from a little private reconnoitring on my own account, that I reported my brave discovery of an unexpected half-way house, and found him almost asleep upon the stones, unwilling to believe the short half-mile I promised. “Only another nest of robbery and insolence,” he laughed sourly, “and, anyhow, not the inn we counted on.” He dragged after me in silence, eyeing askance the tumbled, ivy- covered shanty that stood beside the roadway, yet gladly going in ahead of me to rest his weary limbs, and troubling himself no whit with bargaining that he divined might be once more unpleasant.

Yet the inn proved a surprise in another way—it was entirely delightful. There was a glowing fire of peat in a biggish hall, the patron and his wife were all smiles and pleasure, welcoming us with an old-fashioned dignity that made bargaining impossible, and in ten minutes we felt as much at home as if we had arrived at a country house where we had been long expected. “So few care to stop here now,” the old woman told us, with a gracious gesture that was courtly rather than deferential, “we stand no longer upon the old high road,” and showed in a hundred nameless ways that all they had was entirely at our disposal. Till even Ducommun melted and turned soft: “Only in France could this happen,” he whispered with a touch of pride, as though claiming that this fragrance of gentle life, now fast disappearing from the world, still lingered in the land of his descent and in his own blood too. He patted the huge, rough deer-hound that seemed to fill the little room where we awaited supper, and the friendly creature, bounding with a kind of subdued affection, added another touch of welcome. His face and manners were evidence of kind treatment; he was proud of his owners and of his owners’ guests. I thought of well-loved pets in our English country houses. “This beast,” I laughed, “has surely lived with gentlemen.” And Ducommun took the compliment to himself with personal satisfaction.

It is difficult to tell afterwards with accuracy the countless little touches that made the picture all so gentle—they were so delicately suggested, painted in silently with such deft spiritual discretion. It stands out in my memory, set in some strange, high light, as the most enchanting experience of many a walking tour; and yet, about it all, like a veil of wonder that evades description, an atmosphere of something at the same time—I use the best available word—truly singular. This touch of something remote, indefinite, unique, began to steal over me from the very first, bringing with it an incalculable, queer charm. It lulled like a drug all possible suspicions. And in my friend— detail of the picture nearest to my heart, that is—it first betrayed itself, with a degree of surprise, moreover, not entirely removed from shock.

For as he passed before me underneath that low- browed porch, quite undeniably he altered. This indefinable change clothed his entire presentment to my eyes; to tired eyes, I freely grant, as also that it was dusk, and that the transforming magic of the peat fire was behind him. Yet, eschewing paragraphs of vain description, I may put a portion of it crudely thus, perhaps: that his lankiness turned suddenly all grace; the atmosphere of the London office stool, as of the clerk a-holidaying, vanished; and that the way he “bowed his head to enter the dark-beamed lintel of the door was courtly and high bred, instinct with native elegance, and in the real sense aristocratic. It came with an instant and complete conviction. It was wonderful to see; and it gave me a moment’s curious enchantment. All that I divined and loved in the man, usually somewhat buried, came forth upon the surface. A note of explanation followed readily enough, half explanation at any rate—that houses alter people because, like dressing-up with women and children, they furnish a new setting to the general appearance, and the points one is accustomed to undergo a readjustment. Yet with him this subtle alteration did not pass; it not only clung to him during the entire evening, but most curiously increased. He maintained, indeed, his silence the whole time, but it was a happy, dreaming silence holding the charm of real companionship, his disappointment gone as completely as the memory of our former cheerless inns and ill-conditioned people. I cannot pretend, though, that I really watched him carefully, since an attack from another quarter divided my attention equally, and the charm of the daughter of the house, in whose eyes, it seemed to me, lay all the quiet sadness of the country we had walked through—triste, marne, forsaken land—claimed a great part of my observant sympathy. The old people left us entirely to her care, and the way she looked after us, divining our wants before we ventured to express them, was more suggestive of the perfect hostess than merely of someone who would take payment for all that she supplied. The question of money, indeed, did not once intrude, though I cannot say whence came my impression that this hospitality was, in fact, offered without the least idea of remuneration in silver and gold. That it did come, I can swear; also, that behind it lay no suggestion of stiff prices to be demanded at the last moment on the plea that terms had not been settled in advance. We were made welcome like expected guests, and my heart leaped to encounter this spirit of old-fashioned courtesy that the greed of modern life has everywhere destroyed. “To-morrow or the next day, when you are rested,” said the maiden softly, sitting beside us after supper and tending the fire, I will take you through the Allee des tilleuls towards the river, and show you where the fishing is so good.”

For it seemed natural that she should sit and chat with us, and only afterwards I remembered sharply that the river was a good five miles from where we housed, across marshes that could boast no trees at all, tilleuls least of all, and of avenues not a vestige anywhere.

“We’ll start,” Ducommun answered promptly, taking my breath a little, “in the dawn”; and presently then made signs to go to bed. She brought the candles, lit them for us with a spill of paper from the peat, and handed one to each, a little smile of yearning in her deep, soft eyes that I remember to this day.

“You will sleep long and well,” she said half shyly, accompanying us to the foot of the stairs. “I made and aired the beds with my own hands.” And the last I saw of her, as we turned the landing corner overhead, was her graceful figure against the darkness, with the candle-light falling upon the coiled masses of her dark-brown hair. She gazed up after us with those large grey eyes that seemed to me so full of yearning, and yet so sad, so patient, so curiously resigned...

Ducommun pulled me almost roughly by the arm. “Come,” he said with sudden energy, and as though everything was settled. “We have an early start, remember!”

I moved unwillingly; it was all so strange and dreamlike, the beauty of the girl so enchanting, the change in himself so utterly perplexing. “It’s like staying with friends in a country house,” I murmured, lingering in a moment of bewilderment by his door. “Old family retainers almost, proud and delighted to put one up, eh?”

And his answer was so wholly unexpected that I waited, staring blankly into his altered eyes: “I only hope we shall get away all right,” he muttered. “I mean, that is get off.” Evidently his former mood had flashed a moment back. “You feel tired?” I suggested sympathetically, “so do I.”

“Dog-tired, yes,” he answered shortly, then added in a slow, suggestive whisper—“And I feel cold, too— extraordinarily cold.”

The significant, cautious way he said it made me start. But before I could prate of chills and remedies, he quickly shut the door upon me, leaving those last words ringing in my brain “cold, extraordinarily cold.” And an inkling stole over me of what he meant I uninvited and unwelcome it came, then passed at once, leaving a vague uneasiness behind. For the cold he spoke of surely was not bodily cold. About my own heart, too, moved some strange touch of chill. Cold sought an entrance. But it was not common cold. Rather it was in the mind and thoughts, and settled down upon the spirit. In describing his own sensations he had also described my own; for something at the very heart of me seemed turning numb....

I got quickly into bed. The night was still and windless, but, though I was tired, sleep held long away. Uneasiness continued to affect me. I lay, listening to the blood hurrying along the thin walls of my veins, singing and murmuring, and, when at length I dropped off, two vivid pictures haunted me into unconsciousness—his face in the doorway as he made that last remark, and the face of the girl as she had peered up so yearningly at him over the shaded candle. Then—at once, it seemed—I was wide awake again, aware, however, that an interval had passed, but aware also of another thing that was incredible, and somehow dreadful, namely, that while I slept, the house had undergone a change. It caught me, shivering in my bed, utterly unprepared, as though unfair advantage had been taken of me while I lay unconscious. This startling idea of external alteration made me shudder. How I so instantly divined it lies beyond all explanation. I somehow realised that, while the room I woke in was the same as before, the building of which it formed a little member had known in the darkness some transmuting, substituting change that had turned it otherwise. My terror I also cannot explain, nor why, almost immediately, instead of increasing, it subtly shifted into that numbness I have already mentioned—a curious, deep bemusement of the spirit that robbed it of really acute distress. It seemed as if only a part of me—the wakened part— knew what was going on, and that some other part remained in sleep and ignorance.

For the house was now enormous. It had experienced this weird transformation. The roof, I somehow knew, rose soaring through the darkness; the walls ran over acres; it had towers, wings, and battlements, broad balconies, and magnificent windows. It had grown both dignified and ancient and had swallowed up our little inn as comfortably as a palace includes a single bedroom. The blackness about me of course concealed it, but I felt the yawning corridors, the gape of lofty halls, high ceilings, spacious chambers, till I seemed lost in the being of some stately building that extended itself with imposing majesty upon the night.

Then came the instinct—more, perhaps, a driving impulse than a mere suggestion—to go out and see. See what? I asked myself, as I made my way towards the window gropingly, unwilling or afraid to strike a light. And the answer, utterly without explanation, came hard and sharp like this— “To catch them on the lawn.”

And the curious phrase I knew was right, for the surroundings had changed equally with the house. I drew aside the curtain and peered out upon a lawn that a few hours ago had been surely a rather desolate, plain roadway, and beyond it into spacious gardens, bounded by park-like timber, where before had been but dreary, half-cultivated fields. Through a risen mist the light of the moon shone faintly, and everywhere my sight confirmed the singular impression of extension I have mentioned, for away to the left another mass of masonry that was like the wing of some great mansion rose dimly through the air, and beneath my very eyes a projecting balcony obscured pathways and beds of flowers. Next, where a gleam of moonlight caught it, I saw the broad, slow bend of river edging the lawn through clumps of willows. Even the river had come close. And while I stared, striving to force from so much illusion a single fact that might explain, a little tree upon the lawn just underneath moved slightly nearer, and I saw it was a human figure—a figure that I recognised. Wrapped in some long, loose garment, the daughter of the house stood there in an attitude of waiting. And the waiting was at once explained, for another figure—this time the figure of a man that seemed to me both strange and familiar at the same time—emerged from the shadows of the house to join her. She slipped into his arms. Then came a sound of horses neighing in their stalls, and the couple moved away with sudden swiftness silently as ghosts, disappearing in the mist while three minutes later I heard the crunch of hoofs on gravel, dying rapidly away into the distance of the night.

And here a sudden, wild reaction, not easy of analysis, rushed over me, as if that other part of me that had not waked now came sharply to the rescue, set free from the inhibition of some drug. I felt anger, disgust, resentment, and a wave of indignation that somehow I was being tricked. Impulsively—there seemed no time for judgment or reflection—I crossed the landing, now so oddly deep and lofty, and, without knocking, ran headlong into my friend’s room. The bed, I saw at once, was empty, the sheets not even lain in. The furniture was in disorder, garments strewn about the floor, signs of precipitate flight in all directions. And Ducommun, of course, was gone. What happened next confuses me when I try to think of it, for my only recollection is of hurrying distractedly to and fro between his bedroom and my own. There was a rush and scuttling in the darkness, and then I blundered heavily against walls or furniture or both, and the darkness rose up over my mind with a smothering thick curtain that blinded everything . . . and I came to my senses in the open road, my friend standing over me, enormous in the dusk, and the bit of broken wall where he had rested while I reconnoitred, just behind us. The moon was rising, the air was damp and chill, and he was shouting in my ear, “I thought you were never coming back again. I’m rested now. We’d better hurry on and do those beastly five miles to the inn.”

We started, walking so briskly that we reached it in something over seventy minutes, and passing on the way no single vestige of a house nor of any kind of building. I was the silent one, but when Ducommun talked it was only to curse the desolate, sad country, and wonder why his forbears had ever chosen such a wilderness to live in. And when at length we put up at this inn which he made out was a part of his original family estate, he spent the evening poring over maps and papers, by means of which he admitted finally his calculations were all wrong. “The house itself,” he said, “must have stood farther back along the road we came by. The river, you see,” pointing to the dirty old chart, “has changed its course a bit since then. Its older bed lay much nearer to the chateau, flanking the garden lawn below the park.” And he pointed again to the place with a finger that obviously now held office pens.

Egypt

An Impression

A considerable amount of nonsense has been written about the spell of Egypt. Cheapened by exaggeration, vulgarised by familiarity, it has become for many a picture post-card spell, pinned against the mind like the posters at a railway terminus. The moment Alexandria is reached, this huge post-card hangs across the heavens, blazing in an over-coloured sunset, composed theatrically of temple, pyramid, palm trees by the shining Nile, and the inevitable Sphinx. And the monstrosity of it paralyses the mind. Its strident shout deafens the imagination. Memory escapes with difficulty from the insistent, gross advertisement. The post-card and the poster smother sight.

Behind this glare and glitter there hides, however, another delicate yet potent thing that is somehow nameless—not acknowledged by all, perhaps because so curiously elusive, yet surely felt by all because it is so true: intensely vital, certainly, since it thus survives the suffocation of its vile exaggeration. For the ordinary tourist yields to it, and not alone the excavator and archeologist; the latter, indeed, who live long in the country, cease to be aware of it as an outside influence, having changed insensibly in thought and feeling till they have become it: it is in their blood. An effect is wrought subtly upon the mind that does not pass away. Having once “ gone down into Egypt,” you are never quite the same again. Certain values have curiously changed, perspective has altered, emotions have shifted their specific gravity, some attitude to life, in a word, been emphasised, and another, as it were, obliterated. The spell works underground, and, being not properly comprehensible, is nameless. Moreover, it is the casual visitor, unburdened by antiquarian and historical knowledge, who may best estimate its power—the tourist who knows merely what he has gleaned, for instance, from reading over Baedeker’s general synopsis on the voyage. He is aware of this floating power everywhere, yet unable to fix it to a definite cause. It remains at large, evasive, singularly fascinating.

All countries, of course, colour thought and memory, and work a spell upon the imagination of any but the iy inanimate. Greece, India, Japan, Ireland or the Channel Islands leave their mark and imprint—whence the educational value of travel-psychology—but from these the traveller brings back feelings and memories he can evoke at will and label. He returns from Egypt with a marvellous blur. All, in differing terms, report a similar thing. From the first few months in Egypt, saturated maybe with overmuch, the mind recalls with definiteness—nothing. There comes to its summons a colossal medley that half stupefies: vast reaches of yellow sand drenched in a sunlight that stings; dim, solemn aisles of granite silence; stupendous monoliths ‘that ‘stare unblinking at the sun; the shining river, licking softly at the lips of a murderous desert; and an enormous night-sky literally drowned in stars. A score of temples melt down into a single monster; the Nile spreads everywhere; great pyramids float across the sky like clouds; palms rustle in mid-air; and from caverned leagues of subterranean gloom there issues a roar of voices, thunderous yet muffled, that seem to utter the hieroglyphics of a forgotten tongue. The entire mental horizon, oddly lifted, brims with this procession of gigantic things, then empties again without a word of explanation, leaving a litter of big adjectives chasing one another chaotically—chief among them * mysterious ccc agate ”“ formidable,” “ terrific.” But the single, memory that should link all these together intelligibly is Wak ee ie Gncticn on deep for specific recognition, too vast, somehow, for articulate recovery. The Acropolis, the wonders of Japan and India, the mind can grasp—or thinks so; but this composite enormity of Ramesseum, Serapeum, Karnak, Cheops, Sphinx, with a hundred temples and a thousand miles of sand, it knows it cannot. The mind is a blank. Egypt, it seems, has faded. Memory certainly fails, and description wilts. There seems nothing vier ad yon to report, no interesting, clear, intelligible thing. see in’Egypt? What did you like best? What impression “tid Egypt make upon you?” seem questions impossible to answer. Imagination flickers, stammers and goes out. Thought hesitates and stops. A little shudder, probably, makes itself felt. There is an impotent attempt to describe a temple or two, an expedition on donkey-back into the desert; but it sounds unreal, the language wrong, foolish, even affected. That dreadful Post-card rises like a wall. “ Oh, I liked it all immensely. The delightful dry heat, you know—and one can always count upon the weather for picnics arranged ahead, and—” until the conversation can be changed to theatres or the crops at home. Yet, behind the words, behind the Post-card, one is aware all the time of some huge, alluring thing, alive with a pageantry of ages, strangely brilliant, dignified, magnificent, ing almost to tears—something that drifts past like a tly full-rigged vessel with crowded decks and sails painted in an under-world, and yet the whole too close before for proper sight. The ‘spell has become operative! Having been warned to expect this, I, personally, had yet remained tical—until I experienced its truth. … And it was achat disappointing. After time and money spent, one had apparently brought back so little.

I remember asking myself point blank, in solitude, what I had gained, and I remember the fruitless result. Nothing came but that abominable, shouting Post-card, endlessly extended. Its very endlessness, however, was a clue. Egypt is endless and inexhaustible; some hint of eternity lies there, an awareness of immortality almost. To-day, after a = of four or five thousand years, subterranean Egypt peeps u] again at the sun. The vast Memphian cemetery that stretches from Sakkhara to the Mena House has begun to whisper in the daylight. The Theban worship of the sun is being reconstructed. There is a sense of deathlessness about the ancient Nile, about the grim Sphinx and Pyramids, in the very colonnades of Karnak, whose pylons now once more stand upright after a sleep of forty centuries on their backs; above all, in the ing strength of the floating, rustling sand—something that defies time and repudiates change in gers Out of that flat, undifierentiated landscape which is Egypt, still stand the unconquerable finger-posts of stone, pointing, like symbols of ey, to the equally unchanging skies. The spell is laid you once you have looked into the battered visages those Memnon terrors, which reveal, yet hide, far better than the Spin. They have neither eyes nor lips nor nose; their features, as their message, inscrutable. Yet they tell this nameless thing plainly because they have no words. Out of the green fields of millet they stand like portions of the Theban Mountains that have slid down into the plain, then ee eee centuries to stare across the Nile watch the sunrise. From them, as partly from the opened tombs of priest and Pharaoh, comes some ingredient of this singular spell.

But the mind has to escape first from the picture post-card influence before the genuine effect emerges. For the mind has in reality suffered a bludgeoning that is partly stunning. Then, with the passing of the weeks amid surroundings of lesser scale, the glamour asserts its magical accomplishment. Slowly it stirred to life in me; and its grip may be, with some, tremendous. It has attacked unseen, and few escape it altogether, while yet it can neither be told nor painted, nor quite explained. Unguessed at first, because sought for in some crude, tangible form it never, never assumes, it flames up unexpectedly—perhaps in a London street when fog shrouds the chimneys; perhaps at a concert; perhaps in a tearoom perfumed, gossiping women; in church, at the club, even in bed when falling asleep just after a commonplace evening at a commonplace play. A sound recalls the street cries of the Arabs, with its haunting sing-song melody, a breath of air brings back the heated sand, a rustle of the curtain whispers as the palms and acacia whisper—and the truth is realised. Up steals the immense Egyptian glamour. It pours, it rushes up. It is over you in a moment. All this time it has lain coiled in deep recesses of the inner being—recesses where there is silence because they are inaccessible amid the clamour of daily life. There is awe in it, a hint of cold eternity, a glimpse of something unchanging and terrific, yet, at the same time, soft and very tender too. The pictures unroll and spread. You feel again the untold manuole of the Nile. The grandeur of a hundred battered temples beats upon the heart. There is a sense of unutterable beauty. Something in you bows to the procession that includes great figures of non-human lineage. Up sweeps the electric desert air, the alive wind, the wild and delicate perfume of the sand; the luminous grey shadows brush you; you feel the enormous scale of naked desolation which yet brims with strange vitality. An Arab on his donkey flits in colour across the mind, melting off into tiny perspective. A string of camels stands against the sky, swaying forwards the same moment as though it never ceased. A dozen pyramids cleave the air with monstrous wedges, pointing holes in space. In peace and silence, belonging to a loneliness of ages, rise heads and shoulders of towering gods of stone, little jackals silhouetted, perhaps, an instant against thighs half buried in sand. Great winds, great blazing spaces, great days and nights of shining wonder float past from the pavement or the theatre stall, and London, dim-lit England, the whole of modern life indeed, are reduced sharply to a miniature of trifling ugliness that seems the unreality. Egypt rolls through the heart for a second, and is gone. You remember resignedly that you have an appointment ot olf to-morrow with Jones, or you are to lunch with Lady X., and that it may probably rain, and you must go in tubes and taxis, be crowded, jostled, pressed upon by ugly details of time and space. Conventions drive you; our hat has to be blocked before you can wear it. You ave calls to pay. But out there the days swam past in a flood of golden light, and, caught in a procession of ancient splendours, changeless as the leisured Nile, majestic as the tameless desert, and fresh still with the wonder that first created them, you moved with the tide as of some unconditioned world. Egypt steals out and whispers to you in your dreams. Once more float in an atmosphere of passionate mirages. The spell is upon you heavily. And this is not mere spinning of words in an attempt to conjure up an atmosphere. The thing is really there. You feel it always, and it always evades analysis. The mind is aware of something that is unmanageable. The idea suggests itself that, while some countries give, others may take away.

Egypt, with a power of seduction almost uncanny, has robbed the mind of a faculty best described ome as the faculty of measurement. Its scale has stupefied the ability to measure, appraise, estimate; and this balance once destroyed, wonder and awe capture the heart, going what pace they please. Size works half the miracle, for it is size including a quality of terror—monstrous; and, but for the glorious beauty that thunders through it, this sheer size might easily work a very different spell—dismay. The moden mind, no longer terrified by Speed, to which it has grown contemptuous!) accustomed, yet shrinks a little before this display of titani and bewildering size. Egypt makes it realise that it has n handy standard of measurement. It listens to words tha are meaningless. The vast proportions uplift, then stupefy The girth of the Pyramids, the height of the Colossi, the cubi content of the granite columns and the visage of the Sphin« expressed in yards—these convey as little truth as the numbere: leagues of the frightening desert or the length of that weary an interminable Nile. You draw a deep breath of astonishment—then give up the vain attempt to grapple with a thing you canno! readily assimilate. A dizziness of star-distances steals ove! you; there is a breathlessness of astronomical scale in it that exhilarates while it stuns. What mind can gain by the information that our sun, with all its retinue of planets, sweeps annually thirty-five million miles nearer to a certain star in Hercules—yet that Hercules looks no closer than it did thousands of ago? Such distance lies beyond comprehension. Similarly, in Egypt, there is something that continually evades cay in the monstrous details of sheer size, beautiful with majesty, that day and night tower above the shrinking reason. You believe because you see, but though you know you see, you are not sure what you quite believe. Herein lies one letter, at least, of the spell of Egypt. The mind is for ever aware of something that haunts from the further side of experience.

But assuredly it is only one letter in a sentence that no one hears complete, for there seems an other-worldly element in this strange land that is acknowledged by every type, its presence detected in the most ordinary remarks. At a Cairo dance or a Heliopolis gymkhana you may hear a thoughtless woman observe: “But, you know, there is something queer in Egypt, isn’t there? One simply can’t deny it!” while the man, half puzzled and half contemptuous, laughs it off, falling back for explanation upon historical associations, vanished civilisations, mummies, temples, and the rest. The “ queer thing,” however, is not so easily denied, for it is more than any of these. Just as in good conversation there is present among the talkers something that is greater than any one of them separately, so, when your mind meets t and communes with it, there rises up this odd other-worldly presence, equally real, equally undecipherable. A party of us—te quote an instance of its effect upon an ordinary wholesome mind, called usually “ level-headed “—were on our way one night to see the Sphinx by moonlight under the guidance of a distinguished Egyptologist. We were on donkey-back The night was very still, the sky thick with stars, moonlight flooding everything. As we skirted the huge flanks of the Great Pyramid, half in silver, half in black, its soaring edges lit by stars as by stationary lanterns, the business man asked a question of our learned leader. And in daily life he was a man of acute intelligence, guided by logic and reason, successful, rich. ‘Did they build the id from within outwards?”” was his question, as he gazed up at the towering mystery of the colossal outline. The question seemed quite natural, its utter absurdity not at first apparent. A second afterwards one realised the nonsense of it, and longed to hear the grave reply: “No; they hung the apex in mid-air, and then built downwards from it.” But, though the Egyptologist resisted the temptation to be funny at his questioner’s expense, one somehow felt that, had he answered thus, the man would have accepted the explanation without demur. It would have caused him no surprise, for credo quia incredibile does actually represent one’s attitucle to things in this ancient and mysterious country. “Ah, I see,” was all he said, with a sigh, when told that a pyramid was merely a king’s mausoleum, and that a layer of stone was added for each year he lived; “a big job for a contractor, wasn’t it?” He was no whit ashamed of his idiotic question. “A hundred thousand men working for twenty years built this one,” added the other, as we turned its corner and saw the dark head of the monster guarding its approach through all the centuries.

So everywhere—one hears this kind of question, as though the mind grew childish before an incomprehensible thing. Some shadowy magic pervades the faculties; their natural alertness fails; talk is in whispers, almost as if someone were listening; unreality broods over mood and speech and action. The Impossible, dressed in colours of strange, unfading brilliance, stoops down from some tremendous height, steals close past the windows of the mind, halts a moment, peers in—and vanishes. But the mind has seen the outline, has felt the eerie fascination. What it would instantly reject in the Midlands, on a Scotch moor, on a Rhine steamer, or on Brighton Pier, it harbours here with semi-acceptance and belief. The land exhales a steam of enchantment that lulls the senses. You move through this almost visible glamour. All about ee is a high, transrent screen, built by the centuries, and left standing; and on and there are gaps in it; modern life, cast like a cinema picture upon this screen, becomes the unreality; but, behind it, a vast audience gathered by the ages watches and looks on—at us. And occasionally, aware of being watched, the mind sees through a gap—and asks a wild question, as the business man at the pyramid asked one. Anything is possible, and anything may happen.

There are some who claim things do happen. Imagination constructs swiftly in Egypt, with small opposition from the reason. The creative instinct fairly strides. ‘‘I always expect something unusual to happen when I’m out here,” is a sentence repeatedly heard. “ ee I oe there was yey gn ae unexpected will happen this year, too.” As t in thi coaxing heat of climate, in this rich of a past now being unearthed from day to day, and in this brilliant, vivid quality of its present personality, so oddly stimulating, there lies some quality that acts with the effect of a forcing-house upon the character, bringing out latent possibilities, hurrying on events, developing a rush of life too swift for comfort or full understanding. Certainly no one can see Egypt and remain quite what they were before, however much interpretation of its haunting effect may vary for individuals.

For some, a rather dominant impression is undoubtedly “ the monstrous.” A splendour of awful dream, yet never quite of nightmare, stalks everywhere, suggesting an atmosphere of Khubla Khan. There is nothing lyrical. Even the silvery river, the slender palms, the fields of clover and barley and the acres of flashing poppies convey no lyrical sweetness, as elsewhere they might. All moves to a statelier measure. Stern issues of life and death are in the air, and in the grandeur of the tombs and temples there is a solemnity of genuine awe that makes the blood run slow a little. Those Theban Hills where the kings and queens lay buried, are forbidding to the point of discomfort almost. The listening silence in the grim Valley of the Tombs of the Kings, the intolerable glare of sun shine on the stones, the naked absence of any sign of animal or vegetable life, the slow approach to the secret hiding-place where the mummy of a once powerful monarch lies ghastly now beneath the glitter of an electric light, the implacable desert, deadly with heat and distance on every side—this picture, once seen rather colours one’s memory of the rest of Egypt with its sombre and funereal character. And with the great deific monolith the effect is similar. Proportions and sheer size strike bllow after blow upon the mind. Stupendous figures, shrouded to the eyes, shoulder their way slowly through the shifting sands deathless themselves and half-appalling. Their attitudes and gestures express the hieroglyphic drawings come to life. Their towering heads, coiffed with zodiacal signs, or grotesque with animal or bird, bend down to watch you everywhere. There is no hurry in them; they move with the leisure of the moon, with the stateliness of the sun, with the slow silence of the constellations. But they move. There is, between you and them. this effect of a screen, erected by the ages, yet that any moment may turn thin and let them through upon you. A hand of shadow, but with granite grip, may steal forth and draw you away into some region where they dwell among changeless symbols like themselves, a region vast, ancient and undifferentiated as the desert that has produced them. Their effect in the end is weird, difficult to describe, but real. Talk with a mind that has been steeped for years in their atmosphere and presence, and you will appreciate this odd reality. The spell of Egypt is an other-worldly spell. Its vagueness, its elusiveness, its undeniable reality are ingredients, at any rate, in a total result whose detailed analysis lies hidden in mystery and silence—inscrutable.

Egyptian Sorcery

I

Sanfield paused as he was about to leave the Underground station at Victoria, and cursed the weather. When he left the City it was fine; now it was pouring with rain, and he had neither overcoat nor umbrella. Not a taxi was discoverable in the dripping gloom. He would get soaked before he reached his rooms in Sloane Street.

He stood for some minutes, thinking how vile London was in February, and how depressing life was in general. He stood also, in that moment, though he knew it not, upon the edge of a singular adventure. Looking back upon it in later years, he often remembered this particularly wretched moment of a pouring wet February evening, when everything seemed wrong, and Fate had loaded the dice against him, even in the matter of weather and umbrellas.

Fate, however, without betraying her presence, was watching him through the rain and murk; and Fate, that night, had strange, mysterious eyes. Fantastic cards lay up her sleeve. The rain, his weariness and depression, his physical fatigue especially, seemed the conditions she required before she played these curious cards. Something new and wonderful fluttered close. Romance flashed by him across the driving rain and touched his cheek. He was too exasperated to be aware of it.

Things had gone badly that day at the office, where he was junior partner in a small firm of engineers. Threatened trouble at the works had come to a head. A strike seemed imminent. To add to his annoyance, a new client, whose custom was of supreme importance, had just complained bitterly of the delay in the delivery of his machinery. The senior partners had left the matter in Sanfield’s hands; he had not succeeded. The angry customer swore he would hold the firm to its contract. They could deliver or pay up—whichever suited them. The junior partner had made a mess of things.

The final words on the telephone still rang in his ears as he stood sheltering under the arcade, watching the downpour, and wondering whether he should make a dash for it or wait on the chance of its clearing up—when a further blow was dealt him as the rain-soaked poster of an evening paper caught his eye: “Riots in Egypt. Heavy Fall in Egyptian Securities,” he read with blank dismay. Buying a paper he turned feverishly to the City article—to find his worst fears confirmed. Delta Lands, in which nearly all his small capital was invested, had declined a quarter on the news, and would evidently decline further still. The riots were going on in the towns nearest to their property. Banks had been looted, crops destroyed; the trouble was deep-seated.

So grave was the situation that mere weather seemed suddenly of no account at all. He walked home doggedly in the drenching rain, paying less attention to it than if it had been Scotch mist. The water streamed from his hat, dripped down his back and neck, splashed him with mud and grime from head to foot. He was soaked to the skin. He hardly noticed it. His capital had depreciated by half, at least, and possibly was altogether lost; his position at the office was insecure. How could mere weather matter?

Sitting, eventually, before his fire in dry clothes, after an apology for a dinner he had no heart to eat, he reviewed the situation. He faced a possible total loss of his private capital. Next, the position of his firm caused him grave uneasiness, since, apart from his own mishandling of the new customer, the threatened strike might ruin it completely; a long strain on its limited finances was out of the question. George Sanfield certainly saw things at their worst. He was now thirty-five. A fresh start—the mere idea of it made him shudder—occurred as a possibility in the near future. Vitality, indeed, was at a low ebb, it seemed. Mental depression, great physical fatigue, weariness of life in general made his spirits droop alarmingly, so that almost he felt tired of living. His tie with existence, at any rate, just then was dangerously weak.

Thought turned next to the man on whose advice he had staked his all in Delta Lands. Morris had important Egyptian interests in various big companies and enterprises along the Nile. He had first come to the firm with a letter of introduction upon some business matter, which the junior partner had handled so successfully that acquaintance thus formed had ripened into a more personal tie. The two men had much in common; their temperaments were suited; understanding grew between them; they felt at home and comfortable with one another. They became friends; they felt a mutual confidence. When Morris paid his rare visits to England, they spent much time together; and it was on one of these occasions that the matter of the Egyptian shares was mentioned, Morris urgently advising their purchase.

Sanfield explained his own position clearly enough, but his friend was so confident and optimistic that the purchase eventually had been made. There had been, moreover, Sanfield now remembered, the flavour of a peculiarly intimate and personal kind about the deal. He had remarked it, with a touch of surprise, at the moment, though really it seemed natural enough. Morris was very earnest, holding his friend’s interest at heart; he was affectionate almost.

“I’d like to do you this good turn, old man,” he said. “I have the strong feeling, somehow, that I owe you this, though heaven alone knows why!” After a pause he added, half shyly: “It may be one of those old memories we hear about nowadays cropping up out of some previous life together.” Before the other could reply, he went on to explain that only three men were in the parent syndicate, the shares being unobtainable. “I’ll set some of my own aside for you—four thousand or so, if you like.”

They laughed together; Sanfield thanked him warmly; the deal was carried out. But the recipient of the favour had wondered a little at the sudden increase of intimacy even while he liked it and responded.

Had he been a fool, he now asked himself, to swallow the advice, putting all his eggs into a single basket? He knew very little about Morris after all. … Yet, while reflection showed him that the advice was honest, and the present riots no fault of the adviser’s, he found his thoughts turning in a steady stream towards the man. The affairs of the firm took second place. It was Morris, with his deep-set eyes, his curious ways, his dark skin burnt brick-red by a fierce Eastern sun; it was Morris, looking almost like an Egyptian, who stood before him as he sat thinking gloomily over his dying fire.

He longed to talk with him, to ask him questions, to seek advice. He saw him very vividly against the screen of thought; Morris stood beside him now, gazing out across the limitless expanse of tawny sand. He had in his eyes the “distance” that sailors share with men whose life has been spent amid great trackless wastes. Morris, moreover, now he came to think of it, seemed always a little out of place in England. He had few relatives and, apparently, no friends; he was always intensely pleased when the time came to return to his beloved Nile. He had once mentioned casually a sister who kept house for him when duty detained him in Cairo, but, even here, he was something of an Oriental, rarely speaking of his women folk. Egypt, however, plainly drew him like a magnet. Resistance involved disturbance in his being, even ill-health. Egypt was “home” to him, and his friend, though he had never been there, felt himself its potent spell.

Another curious trait Sanfield remembered, too—his friend’s childish superstition; his belief, or half-belief, in magic and the supernatural. Sanfield, amused, had ascribed it to the long sojourn in a land where anything unusual is at once ascribed to spiritual agencies. Morris owed his entire fortune, if his tale could be believed, to the magical apparition of an unearthly kind in some lonely wadi among the Bedouins. A sand-diviner had influenced another successful speculation. … He was a picturesque figure, whichever way one took him: yet a successful business man into the bargain.

These reflections and memories, on the other hand, brought small comfort to the man who had tempted Fate by following his advice. It was only a little strange how Morris now dominated his thoughts, directing them towards himself. Morris was in Egypt at the moment.

He went to bed at length, filled with uneasy misgivings, but for a long time he could not sleep. He tossed restlessly, his mind still running on the subject of his long reflections. He ached with tiredness. He dropped off at last. Then came a nightmare dream, in which the firm’s works were sold for nearly nothing to an old Arab sheikh who wished to pay for them—in goats. He woke up in a cold perspiration. He had uneasy thoughts. His fancy was travelling. He could not rest.

To distract his mind, he turned on the light and tried to read, and, eventually, towards morning, fell into a sleep of sheer exhaustion. And his final thought—he knew not exactly why—was a sentence Morris had made use of long ago: “I feel I owe you a good turn; I’d like to do something for you. …”

This was the memory in his mind as he slipped off into unconsciousness.

But what happens when the mind is unconscious and the tired body lies submerged in deep sleep, no man, they say, can really tell.

II

The next thing he knew he was walking along a sunbaked street in some foreign town that was familiar, although, at first, its name escaped him. Colour, softness, and warmth pervaded it; there was sparkle and lightness in the exhilarating air; it was an Eastern town.

Though early morning, a number of people were already stirring; strings of camels passed him, loaded with clover, bales of merchandise, and firewood. Gracefully-draped women went by silently, carrying water jars of burnt clay upon their heads. Rude wooden shutters were being taken down in the bazaars; the smoke of cooking-fires rose in the blue spirals through the quiet air. He felt strangely at home and happy. The light, the radiance stirred him. He passed a mosque from which the worshippers came pouring in a stream of colour.

Yet, though an Eastern town, it was not wholly Oriental, for he saw that many of the buildings were of semi-European design, and that the natives sometimes wore European dress, except for the fez upon the head. Among them were Europeans, too. Staring into the faces of the passersby he found, to his vexation, that he could not focus sight as usual, and that the nearer he approached, the less clearly he discerned the features. The faces, upon close attention, at once grew shadowy, merged into each other, or, in some odd fashion, melted into the dazzling sunshine that was their background. All his attempts in this direction failed; impatience seized him; of surprise, however, he was not conscious. Yet this mingled vagueness and intensity seemed perfectly natural.

Filled with a stirring curiosity, he made a strong effort to concentrate his attention, only to discover that this vagueness, this difficulty of focus, lay in his own being, too. He wandered on, unaware exactly where he was going, yet not much perturbed, since there was an objective in view, he knew, and this objective must eventually be reached. Its nature, however, for the moment entirely eluded him.

The sense of familiarity, meanwhile, increased; he had been in this town before, although not quite within recoverable memory. It seemed, perhaps, the general atmosphere, rather than the actual streets, he knew; a certain perfume in the air, a tang of indefinable sweetness, a vitality in the radiant sunshine. The dark faces that he could not focus, he yet knew; the flowing garments of blue and red and yellow, the softly-slippered feet, the slouching camels, the burning human eyes that faded ere he fully caught them—the entire picture in this blazing sunlight lay half-hidden, half-revealed. And an extraordinary sense of happiness and well-being flooded him as he walked; he felt at home; comfort and bliss stole over him. Almost he knew his way about. This was a place he loved and knew.

The complete silence, moreover, did not strike him as peculiar until, suddenly, it was broken in a startling fashion. He heard his own name spoken. It sounded close beside his ear.

“George Sanfield!” The voice was familiar. Morris called him. He realized then the truth. He was, of course, in Cairo.

Yet, instead of turning to discover the speaker at his side, he hurried forward, as though he knew that the voice had come through distance. His consciousness cleared and lightened; he felt more alive; his eyes now focused the passersby without difficulty. He was there to find Morris, and Morris was directing him. All was explained and natural again. He hastened. But, even while he hastened, he knew that his personal desire to speak with his friend about Egyptian shares and Delta Lands was not his single object. Behind it, further in among as yet unstirring shadows, lay another deeper purpose. Yet he did not trouble about it, nor make a conscious effort at discovery. Morris was doing him that “good turn I feel I owe you.” This conviction filled him overwhelmingly. The question of how and why did not once occur to him. A strange, great happiness rose in him.

Upon the outskirts of the town now, he found himself approaching a large building in the European style, with wide verandas and a cultivated garden filled with palm trees. A well-kept drive of yellow sand led to its chief entrance, and the man in khaki drill and riding-breeches walking along this drive, not ten yards in front of him, was—Morris. He overtook him, but his cry of welcome recognition was not answered. Morris, walking with bowed head and stooping shoulders, seemed intensely preoccupied; he had not heard the call.

“Here I am, old fellow!” exclaimed his friend, holding out a hand. “I’ve come, you see … !” then paused aghast before the altered face. Morris paid no attention. He walked straight on as though he had not heard. It was the distraught and anguished expression on the drawn and haggard features that impressed the other most. The silence he took without surprise.

It was the pain and suffering in his friend that occupied him. The dark rims beneath heavy eyes, the evidence of sleepless nights, of long anxiety and ceaseless dread, afflicted him with their too-plain story. The man was overwhelmed with some great sorrow. Sanfield forgot his personal trouble; this larger, deeper grief usurped its place entirely.

“Morris! Morris!” he cried yet more eagerly than before. “I’ve come, you see. Tell me what’s the matter. I believe—that I can—help you … !”

The other turned, looking past him through the air. He made no answer. The eyes went through him. He walked straight on, and Sanfield walked at his side in silence. Through the large door they passed together, Morris paying as little attention to him as though he were not there, and in the small chamber they now entered, evidently a waiting-room, an Egyptian servant approached, uttered some inaudible words, and then withdrew, leaving them alone together.

It seemed that time leaped forward, yet stood still; the passage of minutes, that is to say, was irregular, almost fanciful. Whether the interval was long or short, however, Morris spent it pacing up and down the little room, his hands thrust deep into his pockets, his mind oblivious of all else but his absorbing anxiety and grief. To his friend, who watched him by the wall with intense desire to help, he paid no attention. The latter’s spoken words went by him, entirely unnoticed; he gave no sign of seeing him; his eyes, as he paced up and down, muttering inaudibly to himself, were fixed every few seconds on an inner door. Beyond that door, Sanfield now divined, lay someone who hesitated on the narrow frontier between life and death.

It opened suddenly and a man, in overall and rubber gloves, came out, his face grave yet with faint signs of hope about it—a doctor, clearly, straight from the operating table. Morris, standing rigid in his tracks, listened to something spoken, for the lips were in movement, though no words were audible. The operation, Sanfield divined, had been successful, though danger was still present. The two men passed out, then, into the hall and climbed a wide staircase to the floor above, Sanfield following noiselessly, though so close that he could touch them. Entering a large, airy room where French windows, carefully shaded with green blinds opened onto a veranda, they approached a bed. Two nurses bent over it. The occupant was at first invisible.

Events had moved with curious rapidity. All this had happened, it seemed, in a single moment, yet with the irregular effect already mentioned which made Sanfield feel it might, equally, have lasted hours. But, as he stood behind Morris and the surgeon at the bed, the deeps in him opened suddenly, and he trembled under a shock of intense emotion that he could not understand. As with a stroke of lightning some heavenly fire set his heart aflame with yearning. The very soul in him broke loose with passionate longing that must find satisfaction. It came to him in a single instant with the certain knowledge of an unconquerable conviction. Hidden, yet ever waiting, among the broken centuries, there now leaped upon him this flash of memory—the memory of some sweet and ancient love Time might veil yet could not kill.

He ran forward, past the surgeon and the nurses, past Morris who bent above the bed with a face ghastly from anxiety. He gazed down upon the fair girl lying there, her unbound hair streaming over the pillow. He saw, and he remembered. And an uncontrollable cry of recognition left his lips. …

The irregularity of the passing minutes became so marked then, that he might well have passed outside their measure altogether, beyond what men call Time; duration, interval, both escaped. Alone and free with his eternal love, he was safe from all confinement, free, it seemed, either of time or space. His friend, however, was vaguely with him during the amazing instant. He felt acutely aware of the need each had, respectively, for the other, born of a heritage the Past had hidden overlong. Each, it was clear, could do the other a good turn. … Sanfield, though unable to describe or disentangle later, knew, while it lasted, this joy of full, delicious understanding. …

The strange, swift instant of recognition passed and disappeared. The cry, Sanfield realized, on coming back to the Present, had been soundless and inaudible as before. No one observed him; no one stirred. The girl, on that bed beside the opened windows, lay evidently dying. Her breath came in gasps, her chest heaved convulsively, each attempt at recovery was slower and more painful than the one before. She was unconscious. Sometimes her breathing seemed to stop. It grew weaker, as the pulse grew fainter. And Sanfield, transfixed as with paralysis, stood watching, waiting, an intolerable yearning in his heart to help. It seemed to him that he waited with a purpose.

This purpose suddenly became clear. He knew why he waited. There was help to be given. He was the one to give it.

The girl’s vitality and ebbing nerves, her entire physical organism now fading so quickly towards that final extinction which meant death—could these but be stimulated by a new tide of life, the danger-point now fast approaching might be passed, and recovery must follow. This impetus, he knew suddenly, he could supply. How, he could not tell. It flashed upon him from beyond the stars, as from ancient store of long-forgotten, long-neglected knowledge. It was enough that he felt confident and sure. His soul burned within him; the strength of an ancient and unconquerable love rose through his being. He would try.

The doctor, he saw, was in the act of giving his last aid in the form of a hypodermic injection, Morris and the nurses looking on. Sanfield observed the sharp quick rally, only too faint, too slight; he saw the collapse that followed. The doctor, shrugging his shoulders, turned with a look that could not express itself in words, and Morris, burying his face in his hands, knelt by the bed, shaken with convulsive sobbing. It was the end.

In which moment, precisely, the strange paralysis that had bound Sanfield momentarily, was lifted from his being, and an impelling force, obeying his immense desire, invaded him. He knew how to act. His will, taught long ago, yet long-forgotten, was set free.

“You have come back to me at last,” he cried in his anguish and his power, though the voice was, as ever, inaudible and soundless, “I shall not let you go! …”

Drawn forward nearer and nearer to the bed, he leaned down, as if to kiss the pale lips and streaming hair. But his knowledge operated better than he knew. In the tremendous grip of that power which spins the stars and suns, while drawing souls into manifestation upon a dozen planets, he raced, he dived, he plunged, helpless, yet driven by the creative stress of love and sacrifice towards some eternal purpose. Caught in what seemed a vortex of amazing force, he sank away, as a straw is caught and sunk within the suction of a mighty whirlpool. His memory of Morris, of the doctor, of the girl herself, passed utterly. His entire personality became merged, lost, obliterated. He was aware of nothing; not even aware of nothingness. He lost consciousness. …

III

The reappearance was as sudden as the obliteration. He emerged. There had been interval, duration, time. He was not aware of them. A spasm of blinding pain shot through him. He opened his eyes. His whole body was a single devouring pain. He felt cramped, confined, uncomfortable. He must escape. He thrashed about. Someone seized his arm and held it. With a snarl he easily wrenched it free.

He was in bed. How had he come to this? An accident? He saw the faces of nurse and doctor bending over him, eager, amazed, surprised, a trifle frightened. Vague memories floated to him. Who was he? Where had he come from? And where was … where was … someone … who was dearer to him than life itself? He looked about him: the room, the faces, the French windows, the veranda, all seemed only half familiar. He looked, he searched for … someone … but in vain. …

A spasm of violent pain burned through his body like a fire, and he shut his eyes. He groaned. A voice sounded just above him: “Take this, dear. Try and swallow a little. It will relieve you. Your brother will be back in a moment. You are much better already.”

He looked up at the nurse; he drank what she gave him.

“My brother!” he murmured. “I don’t understand. I have no brother.” Thirst came over him; he drained the glass. The nurse, wearing a startled look, moved away. He watched her go. He pointed at her with his hand, meaning to say something that he instantly forgot—as he saw his own bare arm. Its dreadful thinness shocked him. He must have been ill for months. The arm, wasted almost to nothing, showed the bone. He sank back exhausted, the sleeping draught began to take effect. The nurse returned quietly to a chair beside the bed, from which she watched him without ceasing as the long minutes passed. …

He found it difficult to collect his thoughts, to keep them in his mind when caught. There floated before him a series of odd scenes like coloured pictures in an endless flow. He was unable to catch them. Morris was with him always. They were doing quite absurd, impossible things. They rode together across the desert in the dawn, they wandered through old massive temples, they saw the sun set behind mud villages mid wavering palms, they drifted down a river in a sailing boat of quaint design. It had an enormous single sail. Together they visited tombs cut in the solid rock, hot airless corridors, and huge, dim, vaulted chambers underground. There was an icy wind by night, fierce burning sun by day. They watched vast troops of stars pass down a stupendous sky. … They knew delight and tasted wonder. Strange memories touched them. …

“Nurse!” he called aloud, returning to himself again, and remembering that he must speak with his friend about something—he failed to recall exactly what. “Please ask Mr. Morris to come to me.”

“At once, dear. He’s only in the next room waiting for you to wake.” She went out quickly, and he heard her voice in the passage. It sank to a whisper as she came back with Morris, yet every syllable reached him distinctly:

“… and pay no attention if she wanders a little; just ignore it. She’s turned the corner, thank God, and that’s the chief thing.” Each word he heard with wonder and perplexity, with increasing irritability too.

“I’m a hell of a wreck,” he said, as Morris came, beaming, to the bedside. “Have I been ill long? It’s frightfully decent of you to come, old man.”

But Morris, staggered at this greeting, stopped abruptly, half turning to the nurse for guidance. He seemed unable to find words. Sanfield was extremely annoyed; he showed his feeling. “I’m not balmy, you old ass!” he shouted. “I’m all right again, though very weak. But I wanted to ask you—oh, I remember now—I wanted to ask you about my—er—Deltas.”

“My poor dear Maggie,” stammered Morris, fumbling with his voice. “Don’t worry about your few shares, darling. Deltas are all right—it’s you we—”

“Why, the devil, do you call me Maggie?” snapped the other viciously. “And ‘darling’!” He felt furious, exasperated. “Have you gone balmy, or have I? What in the world are you two up to?” His fury tired him. He lay back upon his pillows, fuming. Morris took a chair beside the bed; he put a hand gently on his wasted arm.

“My darling girl,” he said, in what was intended to be a soothing voice, though it stirred the sick man again to fury beyond expression, “you must really keep quiet for a bit. You’ve had a very severe operation”—his voice shook a little—“but, thank God, you’ve pulled through and are now on the way to recovery. You are my sister Maggie. It will all come back to you when you’re rested—”

“Maggie, indeed!” interrupted the other, trying to sit up again, but too weak to compass it. “Your sister! You bally idiot! Don’t you know me? I wish to God the nurse wouldn’t ‘dear’ me in that senseless way. And you, with your atrocious ‘darling,’ I’m not your precious sister Maggie. I’m—I’m George San—”

But even as he said it, there passed over him some dim lost fragment of a wild, delicious memory he could not seize. Intense pleasure lay in it, could he but recover it. He knew a sweet, forgotten joy. His broken, troubled mind lay searching frantically but without success. It dazzled him. It shook him with an indescribable emotion—of joy, of wonder, of deep sweet confusion. A rapt happiness rose in him, yet pain, like a black awful shutter, closed in upon the happiness at once. He remembered a girl. But he remembered, too, that he had seen her die. Who was she? Had he lost her … again … !

“My dear fellow,” he faltered in a weaker voice to Morris, “my brain’s in a whirl. I’m sorry. I suppose I’ve had some blasted concussion—haven’t I?”

But the man beside his bed, he saw, was startled. An extraordinary look came into his face, though he tried to hide it with a smile.

“My shares!” cried Sanfield, with a half scream. “Four thousand of them!”

Whereupon Morris blanched. “George Sanfield!” he muttered, half to himself, half to the nurse who hurried up. “That voice! The very number too!” He looked white and terrified, as if he had seen a ghost. A whispered colloquy ensued between him and the nurse. It was inaudible.

“Now, dearest Maggie,” he said at length, making evidently a tremendous effort, “do try and lie quiet for a bit. Don’t bother about George Sanfield, my London friend. His shares are quite safe. You’ve heard me speak of him. It’s all right, my darling, quite all right. Oh, believe me! I’m your brother.”

“Maggie … !” whispered the man to himself upon the bed, whereupon Morris stooped, and, to his intense horror, kissed him on the cheek. But his horror seemed merged at once in another personality that surged through and over his entire being, drowning memory and recognition hopelessly. “Darling,” he murmured. He realized that he was mad, of course. It seemed he fainted. …

The momentary unconsciousness soon passed, at any rate. He opened his eyes again. He saw a palm tree out of the window. He knew positively he was not mad, whatever else he might be. Dead perhaps? He felt the sheets, the mattress, the skin upon his face. No, he was alive all right. The dull pains where the tight bandages oppressed him were also real. He was among substantial, earthly things. The nurse, he noticed, regarded him anxiously. She was a pleasant-looking young woman. He smiled; and, with an expression of affectionate, even tender pleasure, she smiled back at him.

“You feel better now, a little stronger,” she said softly. “You’ve had a sleep, Miss Margaret.” She said “Miss Margaret” with a conscious effort. It was better, perhaps, than “dear”; but his anger rose at once. He was too tired, however, to express his feelings. There stole over him, besides, the afflicting consciousness of an alien personality that was familiar, and yet not his. It strove to dominate him. Only by a great effort could he continue to think his own thoughts. This other being kept trying to intrude, to oust him, to take full possession. It resented his presence with a kind of violence.

He sighed. So strong was the feeling of another personality trying to foist itself upon his own, upon his mind, his body, even upon his very face, that he turned instinctively to the nurse, though unaware exactly what he meant to ask her for.

“My hand-glass, please,” he heard himself saying—with horror. The phrase was not his own. Glass or mirror were the words he would have used.

A moment later he was staring with acute and ghastly terror at a reflection that was not his own. It was the face of the dead girl he saw within the silver-handled, woman’s hand-glass he held up.

The dream with its amazing, vivid detail haunted him for days, even coming between him and his work. It seemed far more real, more vivid than the commonplace events of life that followed. The occurrences of the day were pale compared to its overpowering intensity. And a cable, received the very next afternoon, increased this sense of actual truth—of something that had really happened.

“Hold shares writing Morris.”

Its brevity added a convincing touch. He was aware of Egypt even in Throgmorton Street. Yet it was the face of the dead, or dying, girl that chiefly haunted him. She remained in his thoughts, alive and sweet and exquisite. Without her he felt incomplete, his life a failure. He thought of nothing else.

The affairs at the office, meanwhile, went well; unexpected success attended them; there was no strike; the angry customer was pacified. And when the promised letter came from Morris, Sanfield’s hands trembled so violently that he could hardly tear it open. Nor could he read it calmly. The assurance about his precious shares scarcely interested him. It was the final paragraph that set his heart beating against his ribs as though a hammer lay inside him:

“… I’ve had great trouble and anxiety, though, thank God, the danger is over now. I forget if I ever mentioned my sister, Margaret, to you. She keeps house for me in Cairo, when I’m there. She is my only tie in life. Well, a severe operation she had to undergo, all but finished her. To tell you the truth, she very nearly died, for the doctor gave her up. You’ll smile when I tell you that odd things happened—at the very last moment. I can’t explain it, nor can the doctor. It rather terrified me. But at the very moment when we thought her gone, something revived in her. She became full of unexpected life and vigor. She was even violent—whereas, a moment before, she had not the strength to speak, much less to move. It was rather wonderful, but it was terrible too.

“You don’t believe in these things, I know, but I must tell you, because, when she recovered consciousness, she began to babble about yourself, using your name, though she has rarely, if ever, heard it, and even speaking—you won’t believe this, of course!—of your shares in Deltas, giving the exact number that you hold. When you write, please tell me if you were very anxious about these? Also, whether your thoughts were directed particularly to me? I thought a good deal about you, knowing you might be uneasy, but my mind was pretty full, as you will understand, of her operation at the time. The climax, when all this happened, was about 11 a.m. on February 13th.

“Don’t fail to tell me this, as I’m particularly interested in what you may have to say.”

“And, now, I want to ask a great favor of you. The doctor forbids Margaret to stay here during the hot weather, so I’m sending her home to some cousins in Yorkshire, as soon as she is fit to travel. It would be most awfully kind—I know how women bore you—if you could manage to meet the boat and help her on her way through London. I’ll let you know dates and particulars later, when I hear that you will do this for me. …”

Sanfield hardly read the remainder of the letter, which dealt with shares and business matters. But a month later he stood on the dock-pier at Tilbury, watching the approach of the tender from the

Egyptian Mail

.

He saw it make fast; he saw the stream of passengers pour down the gangway; and he saw among them the tall, fair woman of his dream. With a beating heart he went to meet her. …

Entrance and Exit

These three—the old physicist, the girl, and the young anglican parson who was engaged to her —stood by the window of the country house. The blinds were not yet drawn. They could see the dark clump of pines in the field, with crests silhouetted against the pale wintry sky of the February afternoon. Snow, freshly fallen lay upon lawn and hill. A big moon was already lighting up.

“Yes, that’s the wood,” the old man said, “and it was this very day fifty years ago—February 13—the man disappeared from its shadows; swept in this extraordinary, incredible fashion into invisibility— into some other place. Can you wonder the grove is haunted?” A strange impressiveness of manner belied the laugh following the words.

“Oh, please tell us,” the girl whispered; “we’re all alone now.” Curiosity triumphed yet a vague alarm betrayed itself in the questioning glance she cast for protection at her younger companion, whose fine face, on the other hand, wore an expression that was grave and singularly “rapt.” He was listening keenly. “As though Nature,” the physicist went on, half to himself, “here and there concealed vacuums, gaps, holes in space (his mind was always speculative; more than speculative, some said), through which a man might drop into invisibility—a new direction, in fact, at right angles to the three known ones—‘higher space,’ as Bolyai, Gauss, and Hinton might call it; and what you, with your mystical turn”—looking toward the young priest—“might consider a spiritual change of condition, into a region where space and time do not exist, and where all dimensions are possible— because they are one.”

“But, please, the story,” the girl begged, not understanding these dark sayings, “although I’m not sure that Arthur ought to hear it. He’s much too interested in such queer things as it is!” Smiling, yet uneasy, she stood closer to his side, as though her body might protect his soul.

“Very briefly, then, you shall hear what I remember of this haunting, for I was barely ten years old at the time. It was evening—clear and cold like this, with snow and moonlight—when someone reported to my father that a peculiar sound, variously described as crying, singing, wailing, was being heard in the grove. He paid no attention until my sister heard it too, and was frightened. Then he sent a groom to investigate. Though the night was brilliant the man took a lantern. We watched from this very window till we lost his figure against the trees, and the lantern stopped swinging suddenly, as if he had put it down. It remained motionless. We waited half an hour, and then my father, curiously excited, I remember, went out quickly, and I, utterly terrified, went after him. We followed his tracks, which came to an end beside the lantern, the last step being a stride almost impossible for a man to have made. All around the snow was unbroken by a single mark but the man himself had vanished. Then we heard him calling for help—above, behind, beyond us; from all directions at once, yet from none, came the sound of his voice; but though we called back he made no answer, and gradually his cries grew fainter and fainter, as if going into tremendous distance, and at last died away altogether.”

“And the man himself? asked both listeners. “Never returned—from that day to this has never bear seen... At intervals for weeks and months afterwards reports came in that he was still heard crying, always crying for help. With time, even these reports ceased—for most of us,” he added under his breath; “and that is all I know. A mere outline, as you see.” The girl did not quite like the story, for the old man’s manner made it too convincing. She was half disappointed, half frightened. “See! there are the others coming home,” she exclaimed, with a note of relief, pointing to a group of figures moving over the snow near the pine trees. “Now we can think of tea!” She crossed the room to busy herself with the friendly tray as the servant approached to fasten the shutters. The young priest, however, deeply interested, talked on with their host, though in a voice almost too low for her to hear. Only the final sentences reached her, making her uneasy— absurdly so, she thought—till afterwards. “—for matter, as we know, interpenetrates matter,” she heard, “and two objects may conceivably occupy the same space. The odd thing really is that one should hear, but not see; that air-waves should bring the voice, yet ether-waves fail to bring the picture.”

And then the older man: “—as if certain places in Nature, yes, invited the change—places where these extraordinary forces stir from the earth as from the surface of a living Being with organs—places like ENTRANCE AND EXIT — 1 of 3 islands, mountaintops, pine-woods, especially pines isolated from their kind. You know the queer results of digging absolutely virgin soil, of course—and that theory of the earth’s being alive—” The voice dropped again.

“States of mind also helping the forces of the place,” she caught the priest’s reply in part “such as conditions induced by music, by intense listening, by certain moments in the Mass even—by ecstasy or—” “I say, what do you think?” cried a girl’s voice, as the others came in with welcome charter and odours of tweeds and open fields. “As we passed your old haunted pine-wood we heard such a queer noise. Like someone wailing or crying. Cæsar howled and ran; and Harry refused to go in and investigate. He positively funked it!” They all laughed. “More like a rabbit in a trap than a person crying,” explained Harry, a blush kindly concealing his startling pallor. “I wanted my tea too much to bother about an old rabbit.” It was some time after tea when the girl became aware that the priest had disappeared, and putting two and two together, ran in alarm to her host’s study. Quite easily, from the hastily opened shutters, they saw his figure moving across the snow. The moon was very bright over the world, yet he carried a lantern that shone pale yellow against the white “Oh, for God’s sake, quick!” she cried, pale with fear. “Quick! or we’re too late! Arthur’s simply wild about such things. Oh, I might have known—I might have guessed. And this is the very night. I’m terrified!”

By the time he had found his overcoat and slipped round the house with her from the back door, the lantern, they saw, was already swinging close to the pine-wood. The night was still as ice, bitterly cold. Breathlessly they ran, following the tracks. Halfway his steps diverged, and were plainly visible in the virgin snow by themselves. They heard the whispering of the branches ahead of them, for pines cry even when no airs stir. “Follow me close,” said the old man sternly. The lantern, he already saw, lay upon the ground unattended; no human figure was anywhere visible.

“See! The steps come to an end here,” he whispered, stooping down as soon as they reached the lantern. The tracks, hitherto so regular, showed an odd wavering—the snow curiously disturbed. Quite suddenly they stopped. The final step was a very long one—a stride, almost immense, “as though he was pushed forward from behind,” muttered the old man, too low to be overheard, “or sucked forward from in front—as in a fall.”

The girl would have dashed forward but for his strong restraining grasp. She clutched him, uttering a sudden dreadful cry. ‘Hark! I hear his voice!” she almost sobbed. They stood still to listen. A mystery that was more than the mystery of night closed about their hearts—a mystery that is beyond life and death, that only great awe and terror can summon from the deeps of the soul. Out of the heart of the trees, fifty feet away, issued a crying voice, half wailing, half singing, very faint. “Help! help!” it sounded through the still night, “for the love of God, pray for me!” The melancholy rustling of the pines followed; and then again the singular crying voice shot past above their heads, now in front of them, now once more behind. It sounded everywhere. It grew fainter and fainter, fading away, it seemed, into distance that somehow was appalling.

The grove, however, was empty of all but the sighing wind; the snow unbroken by any tread. The moon threw inky shadows; the cold bit; it was a terror of ice and death and this awful singing cry... “But why pray?” screamed the girl, distracted, frantic with her bewildered terror. “Why pray? Let us do something to help—do something...!” She swung round in a circle, nearly falling to the ground. Suddenly she perceived that the old man had dropped to his knees in the snow beside her and was—praying. “Because the forces of prayer, of thought, of the will to help, alone can reach and succour him where he now is,” was all the answer she got. And a moment later both figures were kneeling in the snow, praying, so to speak, their very heart’s life out...

The search may be imagined—the steps taken by police, friends, newspapers, by the whole country in fact... But the most curious part of this queer “Higher Space” adventure is the end of it—at least, the “end” so far as at present known. For after three weeks, when the winds of March were a-roar about the land, there crept over the fields towards the house the small dark figure of a man. He was thin pallid as a ghost, worn and fearfully emaciated, but upon his face and in his eyes were traces of an astonishing radiance—a glory unlike anything ever seen... It may, of course, have been deliberate, or it may have been a genuine loss of memory only; none could say—least of all the girl whom his return snatched from the gates of death; but, at any rate, what had come to pass during the interval of his amazing disappearance he has never yet been able to reveal.

“And you must never ask me,” he would say to her—and repeat even after his complete and speedy restoration to bodily health—“for I simply cannot tell. I know no language, you see, that could express it. I was near you all the time. But I was also—elsewhere and otherwise...”

Explorers’ Ghost Stories

Being True Ghost Stories from Labrador, Borneo, New Guinea, the Himalayas, the Alps, and the Pacific Ocean

Genuinely true ghost stories are hard to come by, as anyone who takes the trouble to track them to their origin may know. They have a way of becoming less convincing, less impressive, the nearer one draws to their source. Often enough they evaporate completely. A true ghost story, honestly told, always thrills; and some of the best I have found in books of travel and exploration, where the traveller, bent upon quite other matters and probably not even interested in otherworldly things, has come across a queer happening and set it down honestly and faithfully. Having read several such experiences in books of this kind, I have jotted them down. They may interest others as they did me.

The narrators, as a rule, are hardheaded men, who have warmed both hands at the fires of life. Most of them have looked bright-eyed danger in the face without blinking. They have been “up against it” in a thousand ways. They hold life cheap. Their books, respectively, prove them men of courage and resource. And when men of this stamp tell a queer story and vouch for its veracity, the story is usually impressive. Not all of the tales I shall quote from are, strictly speaking, ghost stories, but all are interesting, suggestive, and, to say the least, mighty queer. They happened both on sea and land. To take a sea experience first:

It is described in A Gypsy of the Horn, where Rex Clements tells of his voyage in a windjammer round the world some twenty years ago. The queer incident may be found on page 129 et seq., and it occurred in the Pacific, soon after leaving Chatham Island. The weather for days had been severe, even terrible, but the ship at last had run into calmer water.

“One dark, moonless night,” says the author, “just before we got clear of the ‘Forties’, with a fresh breeze blowing, and the ship running quietly along under t’gallant’sls, there occurred a most uncanny experience.

“It was about four bells in the middle watch, the ‘churchyard watch,’ as the four hours after midnight is called, that it happened. We, of the mate’s watch, were on deck, the men for’ard, Burton and I under the break, and Mr. Thomas pacing the poop above our heads. Suddenly, apparently close aboard on the port hand, there came howling out of the darkness a most frightful, wailing cry, ghastly in its agony and intensity. Not of overpowering volume—a score of men shouting together could have raised as loud a hail—it was the indescribable calibre and agony of the shriek that almost froze the blood in our veins.”

All rushed to the rail, mate and men too, and stared into the blackness to windward. “The starbowlines, tired men asleep in their bunks below, poured up on deck, If ever men were horror-struck, we were. Even the Old Man was awakened by it, and came up on deck to see. All listened, eyes strained. A moment or two passed—then the appalling scream rang out again, rising to the point of almost unbearable torture and dying crazily away in broken whimperings. … No one said a word. All stood like stones, peering into the gloom. The sound was not repeated. … Slowly, at length, like men emerging from a trance, we moved and spoke. … The men sat up all night, unable to sleep. …”

Many guesses, the author goes on to say, were hazarded as to the explanation of the awful, terrifying cry, but none of them seemed satisfactory to anybody. The cry of a whale was suggested, “but I never heard a whale utter any sounds with its throat,” is the writer’s comment. Some sea-monster that only rarely comes to the surface? “More unlikely still.” The scream of seals, or of sea-lions, on an island beach? Yet the nearest land was Easter Island, 600 miles to the north! The shriek, moreover, as all who heard it agreed, was “so human.” Was it a shipwrecked boat’s crew?

The uncanny sound was never explained. Its effect upon all concerned, from the captain downwards, lasted for days. “In bare words,” adds the author finally, “it doesn’t sound very terrible, but it made that night a night of terror, and even now it sends a shiver through me to think of it.”

A sound that keeps the crew of a windjammer out of their beds all night and put the fear of God into the ship’s officers as well, to say nothing of the Old Man, may well have been of a fairly convincing nature! The incident, taken out of its full context, and apart from the atmosphere of an enthralling book, loses, of course, something of its impressiveness. It has, however, the true ring about it. That cry was heard by a large number of hardheaded men; it scared them badly; and explanation there was none.

While on the subject of queer noises, whether auditory hallucinations or otherwise, two other cases are worth mentioning, both of them in high mountains:

The first is told by the famous rock-climber, George D. Abraham, the author of many thrilling books of mountain adventure, and the hero of more than one escape. He was in a hut on the Dôm, 9,400 feet up, with a couple of porters. “Just at twilight,” he writes, “a curious thing happened. We were all sitting round the cold stove, wrapped in blankets, when a terribly human yell, as of pain, sounded outside quite close to the hut, and just for the moment it caused the bravest of us to shudder. Two of us wrenched open the snowed-up door, fully expecting to revive someone in distress. However, nothing was visible but dense snow clouds, and no human traces could be seen near the hut. … The two porters were in a state of collapse and did little but mutter ‘Geister! Geister!’ with other expressions in patois signifying that the whole party was doomed. Nothing would suffice but that they must descend to the valley at once and leave me (with my guide] to finish the climb, which they felt now would be our last.” The porters were seen down into safety, while the author and his guide spent a cold and sleepless night in the hut, but did not hear the yell again, nor ascertain what caused it. No disaster followed, at any rate, beyond the minor one that the porters’ heavy loads had to be borne by others.

The story has its interest. Mountains guides and porters are not, as a rule, superstitious in the ghostly sense, although certain mountains, certain peaks rather, may enjoy an atmosphere that is malignant in their minds. The Matterhorn, until conquered, most certainly was haunted for the local peasants, this being due partly to its believed inaccessibility and terrifying rockfalls, and partly, no doubt, to its dangerous and menacing aspect. It is no longer haunted now, Whynper having, if at an awful price, laid its evil spirit. In the case just described, it is significant that more than one man heard the strange cry, the same remark applying also to the shriek heard by the windjammers crew. What one man hears may easily be set down as hallucination, but a collective hallucination is more difficult to accept. Mountains, on the other hand, are notorious for strange noises: wind, ice splitting off, rocks falling, snow settling (the dull boom of a snowfield settling is an unpleasant sound), to say nothing of the tricks that echo may play. Experienced climbers, on the other hand, are familiar with these odd sounds and could hardly ascribe them to a human yell.

Captain Gault Macgowan, F.R.G.S. and his wife, climbing in the Western Himalayas, have a similar tale to tell, though in this case it was a mysterious rifle shot that undoubtedly saved their lives. The account must be condensed, although such condensation robs it of much interesting and exciting detail. Macgowan and his wife, for certain reasons, left their main party and undertook a very harebrained (his own word!) climb on their own account. As the day was closing in they found themselves amid a waste of these immense and desolate mountains, in freezing cold, without provisions or shelter, lost at a great height. For hours they had adventured recklessly among gaping crevasses, along knife-edge crests, and across steep couloirs ending in a sheer drop into empty space. Both were exhausted, cold, hungry, when, having descended at grave risk a dangerous gradient, they reached a mighty crevasse impossible to cross. Turning to reclimb the awful slope, the smooth rocks they had slithered down, proved unnegotiable. Unable to get up or down, they found themselves stuck. “Nearby was a hollow in the rocks. We crept into it and gazed at each other helplessly. It looked as if this was the end.”

Their predicament seemed hopeless, and a night at such an elevation, without food or dry clothing, must have ended in death.

“Suddenly across the snowy spaces, came the sharp crack of a rifle-shot! Imagine our relief! We realized at once that the shikari was somewhere near us, and blessed him for his wisdom in firing the gun—our only means of communication. My wife turned the glasses in the direction of the shot, and in two moments we had picked up the main party—four tiny black dots away across the glacier, high up on the opposite side of the valley. She took off her coat and waved it frantically, and we shouted our loudest in chorus. Had they seen us … ?”

Several hours later, after some perilous scrambling in the deepening twilight, the two parties met and danger was over. “We congratulated the shikari on his forethought in firing the gun, for it had undoubtedly been the means of saving our lives. To our amazement, however, the man indignantly denied having fired his rifle. He seemed hurt that we should accuse him of doing so without permission, and declared that he had heard no shot, the porters verifying his statement. Thereupon I counted the ammunition. It was untouched; the rifle was clean! There was no alternative but to believe that Providence had taken a hand on our behalf, and the porters assured us emphatically that God had saved our lives.”

The story invites none but rather obvious comment perhaps. Of the three incidents described, that of the windjammer is the most convincing. A characteristic belonging to them all is noticeable, and perhaps significant: that the strange sounds were heard by men in a state of physical exhaustion. The ship’s crew, after weeks of battling with terrific weather, were worn out, and climbers, at the end of a long day which has started probably before dawn, are in a condition of severe bodily fatigue. Nerves and muscles are both weary.

The other cases of queer or ghostly happenings I have jotted down from my reading are, I think, of a more interesting and significant kind, more convincing, at any rate. Two of them combine visual with audible experiences; the tangible being, however, not included, touch being, perhaps, the rarest of qualities met with in a ghost story, or the sense most difficult to affect. When all three senses are impressed, to say nothing of smell and taste, the result may be considered highly interesting, though not necessarily more evidential.

Commander H. G. Stoker, D.S.O., R.N., gives a curious account of a visible appearance in his book Straws in the Wind, when he describes his escape with two companions from the Turkish Prison Camp at Hissar, in the centre of Asia Minor and 130 miles from the nearest sea. The characteristic of physical exhaustion and intense nervous strain is again noticeable, as will be seen. Captain Stoker, of course, was in charge of the famous submarine AE2 during the war, whose exploits were well known—a man of great daring and resource. Two officer friends of his on the submarine had lost their lives some eighteen months before the uncanny experience to be described: during the escape, as he frankly tells us, he mistook his two companions in flight for these two dead men, addressing them as such even in daylight, “while realizing the absurdity of the obsession and recognizing it was an hallucination.” The overwrought condition of mind and nerves is frankly admitted, yet the visible appearance, the ghost, which was seen by him when in this state, was seen by his two escaping pals as well. Here is the point of interest in this curious account. We hear much about “extended telepathy” nowadays. Did Commander Stoker’s strong personality transfer a visual hallucination of his own to the receptive minds of his two companions? He goes into little detail concerning it, merely giving a straightforward description of what occurred. He mentions, however, that the whole time the ghostly figure was visible—several hours—he kept the fact to himself. It was later that he discovered from a spontaneous remark of his companions that they both had seen the figure too. The appearance, he declares, differed wholly from the obsession of his dead officer friends of the submarine. This latter he recognized as a pure hallucination.

To come, then, to his “queer” tale:

With two companions they escaped from the Prison Camp and got a fair start before their absence could be noticed, and in due course, after breathless experiences and hairbreadth risks, they reached the Taurus Mountains on their way to the sea. Only one Pass was feasible, it was strictly guarded, sentries armed to the teeth prowled over its narrow neck, watch fires gleamed. One of their party would reconnoitre, and then the three of them would crawl past just out of reach of the dangerous fires. It was very dark, a wild night, a gale of wind whistling through the crags. The sense of danger, prolonged over several hours, was intense; another step and they might be challenged, shot at sight; but the storm muffled the noise of their stumbling among the rough stones, and the sentries did not stray further than need be from their fires. Hunger, thirst, physical exhaustion, nervous and mental strain, all were severe. They moved in single file.

“In the middle of the night [p. 271] I felt—not suddenly nor surprisedly—that we were not three men struggling along in line, but four. There was a fourth man at the end of our line, in the correct position for a fourth man to be. When we stopped for a few moments’ rest, he did not join us, but remained in the darkness, out of sight; yet as soon as we rose and resumed our march, he dropped into place forthwith. He never spoke, nor did he go ahead to lead us. His attitude seemed just that of the true and loyal friend who says: ‘I cannot help, but when danger is at hand remember always that I am here, to stand—or fall—with you.’ ”

The face is not seen, it will be noticed; no sound of footsteps stumbling among the rocks is audible; there is no detailed description of the figure, beyond that it is that of a man; nor is any attempt at speech recorded, either between the author and the ghostly appearance, nor between the author, again, and his two companions.

This mysterious fourth man stayed by them, following in line, until the worst was over and the dangerous pass had been successfully negotiated. The escaped prisoners reached the plain and breathed more freely. “I turned and looked behind,” writes the author. “The fourth man had disappeared. I made no mention of him to the other two. … A couple of hours later, drinking hot cocoa in a safe hiding-place, one of my companions made a quiet remark about the fourth man. They had both seen him. We had all three been sensible of his presence throughout the most trying part of the night; we all three agreed that the moment he left us was when we felt we had put the danger behind. … I cannot exaggerate,” he adds, “how real his presence was, how content one felt—despite the mystery of it—that he should be there, what a strength and comfort his presence seemed to be. … From the time he left us luck turned against us.” Not long after, indeed, the whole party were recaptured and imprisoned again.

Having sent an account of the incident to Sir Arthur Conan Doyle, Commander Stoker received the following reply: “It is the same experience as Shackleton’s sledge party, which had an extra man. One of you was probably mediumistic (without knowing it). Many are. Some friend took advantage of the fact.”

In The Lure of the Labrador Wild, one of the most poignantly moving adventure books ever written, a very interesting case of otherworldly intervention in human affairs is given. The volume describes with intense vividness the Leonidas Hubbard Expedition (1905) across Labrador, ending in Hubbard, its leader, being starved to death in the most distressing circumstances. Had the ghostly intervention been obeyed his life would unquestionably have been saved.

The Expedition was on its way back, making as fast as their exhausted, half-starved condition would allow for Grand Lake, where a cache of food lay waiting for them. Winter was setting in with its awful cold. They had been living on soup made out of boots, decayed partridge, anything and everything that would yield the tiniest amount of sustenance in fact, for many days, and travelling over the roughest sort of country at the same time. Exhaustion had reduced them all to skeletons, and death was close. To work the canoe at all was almost beyond their strength, and they had no idea what river they were on, nor where it led. Finally the question was faced: Should they desert the river and cut across country in the last hope of making Grand Lake and the buried food?

There was a long discussion. The chances across country were against them, for Hubbard could hardly walk by this time, and the other two were feeble and emaciated; yet the river was against them too, for a long stretch of dangerous rapids lay ahead, and the men had no strength to deal with difficult water. An upset meant certain death. Besides, where was the river leading them? The discussion, a very keen but very friendly one, led to no decision, but Hubbard himself was in favour of the cross-country venture, desperate though it was. And Hubbard was leader of the expedition. In the end they decided to sleep on it.

The third member of this desperate party was George Elson, a half-breed Cree Indian from James Bay, engaged for the expedition by the Hudson Bay Company Post at Missanambie, Ontario. He was a stalwart in every sense of the term; a fine fellow, calm, cheerful, companionable, faithful, a man of character. He was, in addition, a man of immense experience. It was through this Indian that the “otherworldly intervention” came—a dream.

The morning following the discussion the three men renewed the fateful talk, in the course of which George announced:

“I had a strange dream about it last night, fellus,” he said quietly. He was asked to tell it.

“It was a strange dream,” he repeated, and hesitated. Hubbard urged him to go on.

“Well,” he said, “I dreamed the Lord stood before me, very beautiful and bright, and He had a mighty kind look on His face. And He said to me: ‘George, don’t leave this river. Just stick to it and it will take you out to Grand Lake, where you’ll find the cache with lots of grub, and then you’ll be all right and safe. I can’t spare you any more fish, George, and if you leave this river you won’t get any more. Just stick to this river and I’ll take you out safe. The Lord was all smilin’ and bright, and He looked at me very pleasant. Then He went away, and I dreamed we went right down the river, and came out in Grand Lake, near where we had left it coming up. And we found the cache and all the grub we wanted, and had a fine time.”

Dillon Wallace, member of the expedition and the author of the book describing it, adds: “It was quite evident that George was greatly impressed by his dream. I give it here simply for what it is worth. At the same time, I cannot help characterizing it as remarkable, not to say extraordinary; for none of us had the faintest suspicion that the river we were on emptied into Grand Lake at all, much less that its mouth was near the point where we left the lake on our way up. But I myself attached no importance to the dream at the time, whatever I may think now.”

Hubbard himself, an intensely religious man, also disregarded the dream, which, if obeyed, would have saved his life. He admitted it was “unusual,” but it did not turn him from his strong instinct to leave the river and cut across country. ‘It isn’t possible, you know,” he said to George, “for this river to empty into Grand Lake. We were talking about leaving the river last night, and you had it on your mind.” Thus he explained the dream.

“Maybe,” admitted the Indian, “but it was a mighty strange dream, and we’d better think about it before we leave the river. Stick to the canoe, Hubbard, that’s what I say.”

In the end Hubbard, too weak to move, sent Wallace and George across country, he himself remaining with what food there was in the little tent. The two men, after terrible privations, reached the cache of food, but when, later, they arrived with help at the tent, they found Hubbard dead beside his diary. The river emptied into Grand Lake after all. The few entries the dying Hubbard made in his diary during the last awful solitude are among the most moving and poignant imaginable.

Two other capital true ghost stories carry us from bleak and frozen Labrador to the genial heat of the Tropics—Borneo and New Guinea. Most of the European houses in Borneo, to take that first, are “berhantu” (haunted) according to the natives, and the following ghost story is told by Oscar Cook, late District Officer, North Borneo Civil Service, in his enchanting volume, Borneo: Stealer of Hearts. The Commissioner at a place called Tengilan met his death suddenly by drowning, and Cook was summoned to replace him temporarily as Acting District Officer. It was in 1917. Cook was invited to stay with another official in a comfortable little European house, which had been inhabited formerly by an Englishman named G. This man G., some years before, entangled by drink and a native woman, had died in the room, in the very bed indeed, Cook now occupied. Cook himself knew nothing of this, and his host did not mention it.

After a long talk about the immediate business in hand, the two men separated for bed at 10:30. Cook heard his host moving about in his room; they called good night to each other through the thin wooden walls; then Cook put his lamp out. He heard the clock strike eleven.

“Then I fell asleep,” he writes. “Suddenly, I was wide awake, but not with a start. No sound or presence had aroused me. I was simply wide awake. I was not strung up nor excited. I turned over and looked at my watch—it was after 1 a.m. (I have somewhat condensed the following account of what happened.—A. B.) I closed my eyes and was about to fall asleep again when I heard footsteps coming up the steps that led from the garden to the front door.

“I listened. Slowly the footsteps mounted the stairs. Then I heard the catch of the low wooden gate pulled back, and the creak of the doors being opened. Down the full length of the veranda came the footsteps, and passed into the dining-room. Whoever was walking kept straight on, for I heard the noise of the doors that shut off this room from the passage leading to the kitchen being opened, and the footsteps went along this passage. Then they halted.

“A clear and decisive voice then called out: ‘Boy!’ It was a voice I did not recognize. No answer came. Again the voice rang out, but in a sharper, more impatient tone: ‘Boy!’ Again there was no reply. After a brief silence, the footsteps then descended the stairs that led from the passage to the kitchen. They halted on the bottom step. ‘Boy!’ the voice called out angrily. There was no answer. Another silence followed. Then the footsteps came back up the stairs, passed along the passage again, across the dining-room, and out into the veranda. The creak of the gate reached me and I heard the closing of the latch. Down the steps the footsteps clumped, and out into the garden. Then silence … I fell asleep, wondering who it was …”

At breakfast next morning Cook asked his host what he was doing, walking all over the house during the night. “So you heard it too!” was the rejoinder, with relief. “I never moved all night long.”

Cook stared at his host, an unimaginative man, a long-headed, shrewd planter, a man of facts and figures, and an utter scoffer at ghostly things. “Well,” he asked, “what about it then?”

“It was G.,” his host went on, “calling for a drink. I’ve often been disturbed by him. G. was the man here before my predecessor. He died in your room—on your bed. The Doctor visited him one day, hearing he was ill. He gave him five minutes to live. Old G. just managed to sit up in bed, smiled, and asked for gin. He smoked a moment, chatted a bit, the gasper dropped from his lips—he was dead! He’s buried in the garden, just on the slope of the hill below your window. My predecessor saw him, and one night even shot him. Well, there it is! My predecessor saw and shot him; I, too, have seen him; you’ve heard him. It’s there, and it happens, and it’s always the same. Now, get on with your tea, and we’ll go and look at the grave. I always inspect it twice a month, and put a coolie to clean and tend it.”

Captain A. W. Monckton, F.R.G.S., F.Z.S., tells a first-rate and most circumstantial ghost story in his widely read volume, Some Experiences of a New Guinea Resident Magistrate. It is indexed as “Spooks in Samarai,” and occurs on page 109. It is admirably told and as convincing as anything well can be. “I tell the story for what it is worth,” he writes, sandwiching it in among other adventures of a most enthralling description. “I leave my readers who are interested in psychical research to form what opinion they choose. All I say is that the story, as related, is absolutely true.” And, indeed, it has the ring of sincerity and truth all through it.

The author was staying alone in the house of a man named Moreton, at Samarai, Moreton living elsewhere at the time; he was Resident Magistrate of the Eastern Division.

“One night,” runs the account, “in Moreton’s house, I had a curious and uncanny experience. I was sitting at the table, writing a long dispatch which engaged all my attention; my table was in the middle of the room, and on my right and left hand respectively there were two doors, one opening on to the front and the other on to the back veranda of the house. Both doors were closed and fastened with ordinary wooden latches, which could not possibly open of their own accord as a spring lock might do. The floor of the room was made of heavy teakwood boards, nailed down; the floor of the veranda being constructed of laths of palm, laced together with native string.

“As I wrote, I became conscious that both doors were wide open, and—hardly thinking what I was doing—I got up, closed them both, and went on writing. A few minutes later, I heard footsteps upon the coral path leading up to the house; they came across the squeaky palm veranda, my door opened, and the footsteps went across the room and—as I raised my eyes from my dispatch—the other door opened, and the footsteps passed across the veranda and down again on to the coral. I paid very little attention to this at first, having my mind full of the subject of which I was writing, but half thought that either Poruma or Giorgi (trusted personal servants), both of whom were in the kitchen, had passed through the room. However, I again rose and absentmindedly shut both doors for the second time.

“Some time later, once more the footsteps came, crash crash on the coral, squeak squeak on the veranda; again my door opened and the squeak changed to the tramp of booted feet on the boarded floor. As I looked to see who it was, the tramp passed close behind my chair and across the room to the door, which opened, and then again the tramp changed to the squeak and the squeak to the crash on the coral. I was, by this time, getting very puzzled, but after a little thought I decided my imagination was playing me tricks, and that I had not really closed the doors when I thought I had. I made certain, however, that I did close them this time, and went on with my work again. Once more, the whole thing was repeated, only this time I rose from the table, took my lamp in my hand, and gazed hard at the places on the floor from which the sound came, but could see nothing.”

Captain Monckton then describes how he went on to the veranda and bawled to the two servants in the kitchen, asking who was playing tricks, and, before they could answer, steps again sounded in his room behind him. Poruma, hearing the; steps, was surprised. “I didn’t know you had anyone with you,” he observed, whereupon his master repeated what had happened. “Someone keeps opening my door,” he said, “and walking about. I want him caught.” Anyone who has read the book will know that Captain Monckton’s orders generally were obeyed, without delay too! But Poruma, the old servant, replied: “No one would dare to enter the Government compound and play tricks on the Resident Magistrate.” His master insisted angrily that the fellow, whoever he might be, must be caught. “I mean to get to the bottom of this fooling,” he said, repeating his order. He sent to the Guard House and got the gatekeeper, also the gaoler and all his warders, finally to the ship as well for her men. The gatekeeper, an honest fellow, swore that the gate had been locked as usual at 10 p.m., before which hour none but Government people had passed in.

A search under Captain Monckton’s instructions was at once organized. There were only three rooms, furnished with Spartan simplicity. They were soon examined. Four men with lanterns were placed under the house, which was raised about four feet from the ground on piles. Other men were stationed back and front. Then the Captain searched the house once more himself. “Tt was impossible,” he adds, “for a mouse to have passed unseen.” This done, he shut the doors of his room, and sat inside with Poruma and Giorgi. They waited in silence a few minutes.

“Presently, exactly the same thing occurred once more. Through that line of men came the footsteps; through my room in precisely the same manner came the tread of a heavily-booted man, then went on to the palm veranda, where—in the now brilliant illumination—we could see the depression at the spots from which the sound came, as though a man were stepping there. [The italics are my own.—A. B.]

“Well,” I asked my men, “what do you make of it?”

“No man living could have passed unseen,” was Poruma’s reply. “It’s either the spirit of a dead man, or a devil.”

Whatever Captain Monckton may have thought, and he offers no opinion or explanation, he moved to the ship for the night and slept on board. Nothing of the sort ever happened again, and a year later the house was pulled down. Before this, however, the author had sat up in it on purpose with a man named Armit, Health Officer and Collector of Customs, but the investigation produced no results. Armit, on this occasion, mentioned that Moreton, the former occupant, had once or twice hinted at something queer having happened. Moreton himself was, therefore, interviewed on the subject. His reply was interesting: “One night,” he admitted, “sleeping in the hammock on the veranda, I heard footsteps. They wakened me. I called out angrily, ‘Who’s making the racket?’ There was no reply, but my hammock was banged violently against the wall. I said nothing about it to anyone, for I was alone at the time, and I didn’t want to be laughed at.”

Failure of the Swiss Winter Season

This year we have enjoyed the unusual privilege of seeing bright green fields in mid-January at a height of three thousand five hundred feet above the sea, and people who came to meet the snow and ice have been picking primroses instead—so several newspapers report—upon the slopes about the Lake of Geneva. the winter has got lost somewhere, and the familiar phrase of the hotelier, " We never knew such weather before at this time of year,” has been really justified for once. All over Switzer- ind it has been the same, east and west, north and south— warm winds from the Atlantic, rain, fog, thaw, and only just enough frost at the resorts that lie above five thousand feet to provide a little inferior skating.

The disappointment of many hundreds has been keen, and the loss to hotels and purveyors of winter-sport articles unquestionably very large. For the great holiday rush is over now, and hundreds never put on their ski at all. The sleighs have hardly dared to show their runners; the peasants are donig all their carting still on wheels. They are content, how- over. “Quel bel hiver!” they say, thus adding insult to injury. For the Basses Alpes, usually lying beneath ten feet ot snow at this time, are green and full of hints of spring flowers— a condition unknown in January for very many years. The hares are running over the upper pastures, fat and well fed. They may be puzzled, but they like it as much as the peasants do. And all the summits of the Jura Mountains, usually crested and heavily “ corniced ” with creamy white, lie at this moment bare aud green, as one knows them in the beginning of April. Yesterday I picked a large blue gentian at a height of four thousand five hundred feet above the sea. There are patches of snow, and drifts and occasional little fields of it, but all growing daily smaller. The very torrents are the torrents one knows, swollen and turbid, after the first spring thaws.

With the exception of a fairly heavy fall just before Christmas everything that has since fallen from the sky—below four thousand feet—has been rain, or rainy sleet with a few flakes of snow mixed here and there in mid-air, enough to permit hope though hope as yet unfulfilled. Although a sprinkling of visions come out at the end of November and early in December expecting to find the winter already in full sway, the majority know that the real snow hardly comes before the New Year. Christmas Week usually sees it, and by the time the great tourist army with two weeks at their disposal has arrived, there has been time for it to “ settle,” freeze into powdery crystals and get generally into good condition. Each fresh fall then adds to its perfection. But this year all these secondary falls have been rain or sleet. There was an early “chute ” in November, very heavy, though quickly disappear- ing; and since then there have been, in the Jura at least, a favourite ski-ing ground, as many as nine other falls, each one melting quicker than its predecessor. For the prevailing winds have been west and south-west, and the frost has been barely enough to keep the few available northern slopes (where the sun cannot reach{them during the day) in dry condition, even for the slowest ski-ing. The consequence is that the second instalment of visitors, who come for February, have been frightened away. The Jura hotels, usually crowded at this time, are fast emptying, and the carriages meet empty trains. The season, already half over, has been a very disappointing one—the worst for many years. Moreover, coming on the heels of two other indifferent ones, it has done Switzerland “much harm. Her reputation is in danger. On every side one hears men saying, " Next year I shan’t risk it again. I shall go to Norway.” In Norway there is good ski-ing up to the close of April, and in some places even into May. The journey is longer, the sea portion is a nuisance to most, but the prices en pension compare favourably with Swiss hotel prices, and are even less, and a ski-er gets his money’s worth, at any rate. Now, at this very moment, writing in these last days of January at a height not far from four thousand feet, the sun blazes in a cloudless sky upon green fields and pine woods untouched by white, birds are singing, there are summery fleecy clouds just visible upon the distant Alps, and a mild south-west wind brings thoughts and feelings that belong to April. Spring is in the air. It seems absurd to talk of ski at all. And every morning the hotelier wrings his hands and taps the weather-glass and looks morbidly at the soppy rink. ‘“‘ It will come, yes, it will come,” he says, though with less conviction daily; “ it will come in February. The winter is later than usual, that’s all. We always get it in the end!” Probably, too, he is right.

Like last year, there may be heavy snow—the heaviest of the vear—in March. But no one will be here to see it. After mid-February, besides, the heat of the sun is such that the surface of the snow melts rapidly between eleven and three o'clock, and, freezing again at night, offers a crust of icy hard- ness on which turning is difficult, skidding incessant and tumbling a dangerous and serious matter altogether. It is not ski-able snow. The Ski-ing, Jumping Meeting, held annually at Ste. Croiz in the Jura vaudois, and a meeting of recognised importance, has already been postponed three times. It is usually held the first week in January. This year it may possibly not take place at all.

If Switzerland wishes to win back its character, hotels must be built higher up the mountains—a couple of thousand feet or more. At a certain height, of course, there is bound to be snow and frost. Yet that means higher pension terms at the same time, for provisions have further to come. It also involves questions of inaccessibility. The Christmas rush of people with a limited time at their disposal dislike an extra day added to their journey at each end. It makes a difference when a man has only two weeks to deal with.

Reports from Eastern Switzerland have been slightly better, perhaps. The prevailing westerly winds that come from the Atlantic have passed across the great central glacier systems before they reach the Engadine and the Tyrol. They have been thoroughly cooled, whereas Western Switzerland receives their load of ocean moisture straight from the coast. No mountains lie between. The Jura undoubtedly suffers in t's respect; and many experienced people begin their winter seas east of Lucerne, and end it in the Jura on the way back England. This year, however, they are going home dir Reports have frightened them. And the crowds of foreigners waiting in Lausanne, Geneva, Montreux, Vevey and t'¢ numerous places along the shores of the lake have simply '° come further. The mountain hotels have lost thousands '” this way. The towns offer some attractions, at any rate; that a winter-sport hotel when there is no winter sport is one of the most dismal things one can well imagine. The proprietor has a very severe time of it. All blame him, directly or in- directly, for the bad conditions. “ As if I could help it, or change the weather!’ he apologises every few minutes. " You might have told us,” is the illogical reply; “at least you might have warned us!’’ And he adds, “ It is the same everywhere. All Switzerland is the same. Such a year has never before been known!” For the favourable reports one reads in certain newspapers are a snare and a delusion. It may be noted that they are invariably undated.

But, when the worst is said, it must be remembered that the winter is not yet over. Also—it is thoroughly ashamed of itself. It may make a violent effort to retrieve itself, and probably it will. There are still hundreds of hopeful men and women who are waiting for that effort. " For when it comes,” they say, “it will be terrible, and worth waiting for!"

Faith Cure on the Channel

A letter from my vague friend was always a source of difficulty: it allowed of so many interpretations—contradictory often. But this one was comparatively plain sailing:-

"You said you were going abroad about this time. So am I. Let's go as far as Paris together. Send me a line to above address at once. Thursday or Friday would suit me.-Yours,X. Y. Z.

“P.S.-I enclose P.O. for that 10s. I owe you."

I received this letter on a Wednesday morning. It was written from the Club, but the Club address was carefully scored out and no other given.

The "P.0." was not enclosed.

In spite of these obstacles, however, we somehow met and arranged to start on Saturday; and the night before we dined together in that excellent little Soho restaurant-"there's nothing," my friend always said, "between its cooking and the Ritz, except prices "-and discussed our prospects, he going to finish a book at a Barbizon inn, I to inspect certain machinery in various Continental dairies.

His heart, it was plain, however, was neither in the cooking nor the book, nor in my wonderful machinery. Like a boy with a secret, he was mysterious about something hitherto unshared Happy, too, for he kept smiling at nothing.

" The fact is," he observed at last over coffee, “I'm really a vile, simply a vile sailor."

“I remember," I said, for we had once been companions on the same yacht.

“And you," he added, holding the black eyebrows steady,“you—are another.” When dealing with simple truths he was often brutally frank.

“What's the good of talking about it?”.

“This," he replied, paying the bill and giving me the amount of the “P.O.," P.O.," “I'll show you."

He conducted me into a little box of a place bearing the legend outside" Foreign Chemist,' and proceeded first to buy the most curious assortment of strange medicines I ever heard of. Weird indeed must have been his ailments. I had no time for reflection, however, on the point, for suddenly turning to me by way of introduction, and allowing the eyebrow next the chemist to dance and bristle so as to attract his attention, he mumbled, "This is my seasick friend. We're off to-morrow. If you've got the stuff ready we might take it now.” And, before I had time to ask or argue, he had pocketed a little package and we were in the street again.

Never had I known him so brisk and practical. “It's a new seasick cure,” he explained darkly as we went home; something quite new-just invented, in fact; and that chap's asking a few of his special customers to try it and give their honest opinions. So I told him we were pretty bad-vile, in fact-and I've got this for nothing. He only wants vile sailors, you see, otherwise there's no test-

“Know what's in it?" He shook his head so violently that I was afraid for the eyebrows.

“But I believe in it. It's simply wonderful stuff; no bromide, he assured me, and no harmful drugs. Just a seasick cure; that's all I"

“I'll take it if you will," I laughed. "I could take poison with impunity before going on the Channel!

" He gave me one bottle. " Take a dose tonight," he explained, another after breakfast in the morning, another in the train, and another the moment you go on board."

I gave my promise and we separated on his doorstep. It was a lot to promise, but as I have explained, I could drink tar or prussic acid before going on a steamer, and neither would have the time to work injury. I marvelled greatly, however, at my vague friend's fit of abnormal lucidity, and in the night I dreamed of him surrounded by all the medicine bottles he had bought to take abroad with him, swallowing their contents one by one, and smiling while he did so, with eyebrows grown to the size of hedges.

I took my doses faithfully, with the immediate result that in the train I became aware of symptoms that usually had the decency to wait for the steamer. My friend took his too. He was in excellent spirits, eyes bright, full of confidence. The bottles were wrapped in neat white paper, only the necks visible; and we drank our allotted quantity from the mouths, without glasses.

“Not much taste," I remarked.

“Wonderful stuff," he replied. “I believe in it absolutely. It's good for other things, too; it made me sleep like a top, and I had the appetite of a horse for breakfast. That chemist 'll make his fortune when he brings it out. People will pay a pound a bottle, lots of 'em."

At Newhaven the sea was agitated-hideously so; even in the harbour the steamers rose and fell absurdly. Not all the fresh, salt winds in the world, nor all the jolly sunshine and sparkling waves, nor all that strong beauty that comes with the first glimpse of the sea and long horizons, could lessen the sinking dread that was in my—my heart. Truth to tell, I had no more belief in the elixir than if it had been chopped hay and treacle.

My friend, however, was confidence personified. “The fact is," he said, laughing at the wind and sea," the real fact is I believe in that chemist. He told me this stuff was infallible; and I believe it is. The trouble with you is funk—sheer blue funk."

We stuck to our guns and swallowed the last prescribed dose just before the syren announced our departure—and fifteen minutes later. .

It was a degrading three hours; and the sting of it was that my friend, with a hideous cap tied down about his ears, a smile that was in the worst possible taste, and a jaunty confidence that was even more insulting than he intended it to be, walked up and down that loathsome, sliding, switchback deck the entire way. Not the entire way, though, for half-way across he disappeared into the dining-room, and returned in due course with that brown beard of his charged with bread-crumbs, and between his lips actually—a pipe. And, without so much as speaking to me, he paced to and fro before my chair, when a little of that imagination he put so delightfully into his books would have led him discreetly to pace the other deck where I could not see him. I thought out endless revenges, but the fact was I never had time to think out any single revenge properly to its conclusion. Something—something unspeakably vile—always came to interfere; and the sight of my friend, balancing up and down the rolling deck chatting to sailors, admiring the sea and sky, and puffing hard at his pipe all the time, was, I think, the most abominable thing I have ever seen.

Simply marvellous, I call it,” he told me in the douane at Dieppe. "The stuff is a revolutionary discovery. It's the first time I ever ate a meal on a steamer in my life. Sorry you suffered so. Can't understand it," he added, with a complacency that was insufferable. I was positively delighted to see the Customs officer open all his bags and litter his things about in glorious confusion. .

In Paris that night our little hotel was rather full, and we had to share a big two-bedded room. My friend groaned a good deal between two and three in the morning and kept me awake; and once, somewhere about five a.m., I saw him with a lighted candle fumbling at the table among a lot of little white paper packages which I recognised as his purchases from that criminal London chemist who had concocted the seasick cure.

It was at nine o'clock, however, while he was down at his bath, that I noticed something on the table by his bed that instantly arrested my attention. Regardless of morals, I investigated. It was unmistakable. It was his own bottle of the seasick cure. He had never taken it at all 1

Then, just as his step sounded in the passage, it flashed across me. He had made one of his usual muddles. He had mistaken the bottle He had swallowed the contents of some other phial instead.

Revenge is sweet; but I felt well again, and no longer harboured any spite. There was just time to hide the bottle in my hand when he entered.

“Awful headache I've got,” he said. make out what's wrong with me. Such funny pains, too."

“After-effects of the seasick cure, probably. They'll pass in time," I suggested. But he remained in bed for a day and a night with all the symptoms of mal de mer on land.

It was many weeks later when I told him the truth, and showed the bottle to prove it—just in time to prevent his telling the chemist, “I have tried your seasick cure and found it absolutely efficacious," etc.

“What cured you," I said, was far more wonderful than anything one can buy in bottles. It was faith, sheer faith!”

I believe you're right," he replied meekly. “I believed in that stuff absolutely.” Then he added, But, you know, I should like to find out what it was I did take."

IV

FIRST HATE

They had been shooting all day; the weather had been perfect and the powder straight, so that when they assembled in the smoking-room after dinner they were well pleased with themselves. From discussing the day’s sport and the weather outlook, the conversation drifted to other, though still cognate, fields. Lawson, the crack shot of the party, mentioned the instinctive recognition all animals feel for their natural enemies, and gave several instances in which he had tested it—tame rats with a ferret, birds with a snake, and so forth.

“Even after being domesticated for generations,” he said, “they recognize their natural enemy at once by instinct, an enemy they can never even have seen before. It’s infallible. They know instantly.”

“Undoubtedly,” said a voice from the corner chair; “and so do we.”

The speaker was Ericssen, their host, a great hunter before the Lord, generally uncommunicative but a good listener, leaving the talk to others. For this latter reason, as well as for a certain note of challenge in his voice, his abrupt statement gained attention.

“What do you mean exactly by ‘so do we’?” asked three men together, after waiting some seconds to see whether he meant to elaborate, which he evidently did not.

“We belong to the animal kingdom, of course,” put in a fourth, for behind the challenge there obviously lay a story, though a story that might be difficult to drag out of him. It was.

Ericssen, who had leaned forward a moment so that his strong, humorous face was in clear light, now sank back again into his chair, his expression concealed by the red lampshade at his side. The light played tricks, obliterating the humorous, almost tender lines, while emphasizing the strength of the jaw and nose. The red glare lent to the whole a rather grim expression.

Lawson, man of authority among them, broke the little pause.

“You’re dead right,” he observed, “but how do you know it?”—for John Ericssen never made a positive statement without a good reason for it. That good reason, he felt sure, involved a personal proof, but a story Ericssen would never tell before a general audience. He would tell it later, however, when the others had left. “There’s such a thing as instinctive antipathy, of course,” he added, with a laugh, looking around him. “That’s what you mean probably.”

“I meant exactly what I said,” replied the host bluntly. “There’s first love. There’s first hate, too.”

“Hate’s a strong word,” remarked Lawson.

“So is love,” put in another.

“Hate’s strongest,” said Ericssen grimly. “In the animal kingdom, at least,” he added suggestively, and then kept his lips closed, except to sip his liquor, for the rest of the evening—until the party at length broke up, leaving Lawson and one other man, both old trusted friends of many years’ standing.

“It’s not a tale I’d tell to everybody,” he began, when they were alone. “It’s true, for one thing; for another, you see, some of those good fellows”—he indicated the empty chairs with an expressive nod of his great head—“some of ’em knew him. You both knew him too, probably.”

“The man you hated,” said the understanding Lawson.

“And who hated me,” came the quiet confirmation. “My other reason,” he went on, “for keeping quiet was that the tale involves my wife.”

The two listeners said nothing, but each remembered the curiously long courtship that had been the prelude to his marriage. No engagement had been announced, the pair were devoted to one another, there was no known rival on either side; yet the courtship continued without coming to its expected conclusion. Many stories were afloat in consequence. It was a social mystery that intrigued the gossips.

“I may tell you two,” Ericssen continued, “the reason my wife refused for so long to marry me. It is hard to believe, perhaps, but it is true. Another man wished to make her his wife, and she would not consent to marry me until that other man was dead. Quixotic, absurd, unreasonable? If you like. I’ll tell you what she said.” He looked up with a significant expression in his face which proved that he, at least, did not now judge her reason foolish. “‘Because it would be murder,’ she told me. ‘Another man who wants to marry me would kill you.’”

“She had some proof for the assertion, no doubt?” suggested Lawson.

“None whatever,” was the reply. “Merely her woman’s instinct. Moreover, I did not know who the other man was, nor would she ever tell me.”

“Otherwise you might have murdered him instead?” said Baynes, the second listener.

“I did,” said Ericssen grimly. “But without knowing he was the man.” He sipped his whisky and relit his pipe. The others waited.

“Our marriage took place two months later—just after Hazel’s disappearance.”

“Hazel?” exclaimed Lawson and Baynes in a single breath. “Hazel! Member of the Hunters!” His mysterious disappearance had been a nine days’ wonder some ten years ago. It had never been explained. They had all been members of the Hunters’ Club together.

“That’s the chap,” Ericssen said. “Now I’ll tell you the tale, if you care to hear it.” They settled back in their chairs to listen, and Ericssen, who had evidently never told the affair to another living soul except his own wife, doubtless, seemed glad this time to tell it to two men.

“It began some dozen years ago when my brother Jack and I came home from a shooting trip in China. I’ve often told you about our adventures there, and you see the heads hanging up here in the smoking-room—some of ’em.” He glanced round proudly at the walls. “We were glad to be in town again after two years’ roughing it, and we looked forward to our first good dinner at the club, to make up for the rotten cooking we had endured so long. We had ordered that dinner in anticipatory detail many a time together. Well, we had it and enjoyed it up to a point—the point of the entr�e, to be exact.

“Up to that point it was delicious, and we let ourselves go, I can tell you. We had ordered the very wine we had planned months before when we were snow-bound and half starving in the mountains.” He smacked his lips as he mentioned it. “I was just starting on a beautifully cooked grouse,” he went on, “when a figure went by our table, and Jack looked up and nodded. The two exchanged a brief word of greeting and explanation, and the other man passed on. Evidently they knew each other just enough to make a word or two necessary, but enough.

“‘Who’s that?’ I asked.

“‘A new member, named Hazel,’ Jack told me. ‘A great shot.’ He knew him slightly, he explained; he had once been a client of his—Jack was a barrister, you remember—and had defended him in some financial case or other. Rather an unpleasant case, he added. Jack did not ‘care about’ the fellow, he told me, as he went on with his tender wing of grouse.”

Ericssen paused to relight his pipe a moment.

“Not care about him!” he continued. “It didn’t surprise me, for my own feeling, the instant I set eyes on the fellow, was one of violent, instinctive dislike that amounted to loathing. Loathing! No. I’ll give it the right word—hatred. I simply couldn’t help myself; I hated the man from the very first go off. A wave of repulsion swept over me as I followed him down the room a moment with my eyes, till he took his seat at a distant table and was out of sight. Ugh! He was a big, fat-faced man, with an eyeglass glued into one of his pale-blue cod-like eyes—out of condition, ugly as a toad, with a smug expression of intense self-satisfaction on his jowl that made me long to——

“I leave it to you to guess what I would have liked to do to him. But the instinctive loathing he inspired in me had another aspect, too. Jack had not introduced us during the momentary pause beside our table, but as I looked up I caught the fellow’s eye on mine—he was glaring at me instead of at Jack, to whom he was talking—with an expression of malignant dislike, as keen evidently as my own. That’s the other aspect I meant. He hated me as violently as I hated him. We were instinctive enemies, just as the rat and ferret are instinctive enemies. Each recognized a mortal foe. It was a case—I swear it—of whoever got first chance.”

“Bad as that!” exclaimed Baynes. “I knew him by sight. He wasn’t pretty, I’ll admit.”

“I knew him to nod to,” Lawson mentioned. “I never heard anything particular against him.” He shrugged his shoulders.

Ericssen went on. “It was not his character or qualities I hated,” he said. “I didn’t even know them. That’s the whole point. There’s no reason you fellows should have disliked him. My hatred—our mutual hatred—was instinctive, as instinctive as first love. A man knows his natural mate; also he knows his natural enemy. I did, at any rate, both with him and with my wife. Given the chance, Hazel would have done me in; just as surely, given the chance, I would have done him in. No blame to either of us, what’s more, in my opinion.”

“I’ve felt dislike, but never hatred like that,” Baynes mentioned. “I came across it in a book once, though. The writer did not mention the instinctive fear of the human animal for its natural enemy, or anything of that sort. He thought it was a continuance of a bitter feud begun in an earlier existence. He called it memory.”

“Possibly,” said Ericssen briefly. “My mind is not speculative. But I’m glad you spoke of fear. I left that out. The truth is, I feared the fellow, too, in a way; and had we ever met face to face in some wild country without witnesses I should have felt justified in drawing on him at sight, and he would have felt the same. Murder? If you like. I should call it self-defence. Anyhow, the fellow polluted the room for me. He spoilt the enjoyment of that dinner we had ordered months before in China.”

“But you saw him again, of course, later?”

“Lots of times. Not that night, because we went on to a theatre. But in the club we were always running across one another—in the houses of friends at lunch or dinner; at race meetings; all over the place; in fact, I even had some trouble to avoid being introduced to him. And every time we met our eyes betrayed us. He felt in his heart what I felt in mine. Ugh! He was as loathsome to me as leprosy, and as dangerous. Odd, isn’t it? The most intense feeling, except love, I’ve ever known. I remember”—he laughed gruffly—“I used to feel quite sorry for him. If he felt what I felt, and I’m convinced he did, he must have suffered. His one object—to get me out of the way for good—was so impossible. Then Fate played a hand in the game. I’ll tell you how.

“My brother died a year or two later, and I went abroad to try and forget it. I went salmon fishing in Canada. But, though the sport was good, it was not like the old times with Jack. The camp never felt the same without him. I missed him badly. But I forgot Hazel for the time; hating did not seem worth while, somehow.

“When the best of the fishing was over on the Atlantic side, I took a run back to Vancouver and fished there for a bit. I went up the Campbell River, which was not so crowded then as it is now, and had some rattling sport. Then I grew tired of the rod and decided to go after wapiti for a change. I came back to Victoria and learned what I could about the best places, and decided finally to go up the west coast of the island. By luck I happened to pick up a good guide, who was in the town at the moment on business, and we started off together in one of the little Canadian Pacific Railway boats that ply along that coast.

“Outfitting two days later at a small place the steamer stopped at, the guide said we needed another man to help pack our kit over portages, and so forth, but the only fellow available was a Siwash of whom he disapproved. My guide would not have him at any price; he was lazy, a drunkard, a liar, and even worse, for on one occasion he came back without the sportsman he had taken up country on a shooting trip, and his story was not convincing, to say the least. These disappearances are always awkward, of course, as you both know. We preferred, anyhow, to go without the Siwash, and off we started.

“At first our luck was bad. I saw many wapiti, but no good heads; only after a fortnight’s hunting did I manage to get a decent head, though even that was not so good as I should have liked.

“We were then near the head waters of a little river that ran down into the Inlet; heavy rains had made the river rise; running downstream was a risky job, what with old log-jams shifting and new ones forming; and, after many narrow escapes, we upset one afternoon and had the misfortune to lose a lot of our kit, amongst it most of our cartridges. We could only muster a few between us. The guide had a dozen; I had two—just enough, we considered, to take us out all right. Still, it was an infernal nuisance. We camped at once to dry out our soaked things in front of a big fire, and while this laundry work was going on, the guide suggested my filling in the time by taking a look at the next little valley, which ran parallel to ours. He had seen some good heads over there a few weeks ago. Possibly I might come upon the herd. I started at once, taking my two cartridges with me.

“It was the devil of a job getting over the divide, for it was a badly bushed-up place, and where there were no bushes there were boulders and fallen trees, and the going was slow and tiring. But I got across at last and came out upon another stream at the bottom of the new valley. Signs of wapiti were plentiful, though I never came up with a single beast all the afternoon. Blacktail deer were everywhere, but the wapiti remained invisible. Providence, or whatever you like to call that which there is no escaping in our lives, made me save my two cartridges.”

Ericssen stopped a minute then. It was not to light his pipe or sip his whisky. Nor was it because the remainder of his story failed in the recollection of any vivid detail. He paused a moment to think.

“Tell us the lot,” pleaded Lawson. “Don’t leave out anything.”

Ericssen looked up. His friend’s remark had helped him to make up his mind apparently. He had hesitated about something or other, but the hesitation passed. He glanced at both his listeners.

“Right,” he said. “I’ll tell you everything. I’m not imaginative, as you know, and my amount of superstition, I should judge, is microscopic.” He took a longer breath, then lowered his voice a trifle. “Anyhow,” he went on, “it’s true, so I don’t see why I should feel shy about admitting it—but as I stood there in that lonely valley, where only the noises of wind and water were audible, and no human being, except my guide, some miles away, was within reach, a curious feeling came over me I find difficult to describe. I felt”—obviously he made an effort to get the word out—“I felt creepy.”

“You,” murmured Lawson, with an incredulous smile—“you creepy?” he repeated under his breath.

“I felt creepy and afraid,” continued the other, with conviction. “I had the sensation of being seen by someone—as if someone, I mean, was watching me. It was so unlikely that anyone was near me in that God-forsaken bit of wilderness, that I simply couldn’t believe it at first. But the feeling persisted. I felt absolutely positive somebody was not far away among the red maples, behind a boulder, across the little stream, perhaps, somewhere, at any rate, so near that I was plainly visible to him. It was not an animal. It was human. Also, it was hostile.

“I was in danger.

“You may laugh, both of you, but I assure you the feeling was so positive that I crouched down instinctively to hide myself behind a rock. My first thought, that the guide had followed me for some reason or other, I at once discarded. It was not the guide. It was an enemy.

“No, no, I thought of no one in particular. No name, no face occurred to me. Merely that an enemy was on my trail, that he saw me, and I did not see him, and that he was near enough to me to—well, to take instant action. This deep instinctive feeling of danger, of fear, of anything you like to call it, was simply overwhelming.

“Another curious detail I must also mention. About half an hour before, having given up all hope of seeing wapiti, I had decided to kill a blacktail deer for meat. A good shot offered itself, not thirty yards away. I aimed. But just as I was going to pull the trigger a queer emotion touched me, and I lowered the rifle. It was exactly as though a voice said, ‘Don’t!’ I heard no voice, mind you; it was an emotion only, a feeling, a sudden inexplicable change of mind—a warning, if you like. I didn’t fire, anyhow.

“But now, as I crouched behind that rock, I remembered this curious little incident, and was glad I had not used up my last two cartridges. More than that I cannot tell you. Things of that kind are new to me. They’re difficult enough to tell, let alone to explain. But they were real.

“I crouched there, wondering what on earth was happening to me, and, feeling a bit of a fool, if you want to know, when suddenly, over the top of the boulder, I saw something moving. It was a man’s hat. I peered cautiously. Some sixty yards away the bushes parted, and two men came out on to the river’s bank, and I knew them both. One was the Siwash I had seen at the store. The other was Hazel. Before I had time to think I cocked my rifle.”

“Hazel. Good Lord!” exclaimed the listeners.

“For a moment I was too surprised to do anything but cock that rifle. I waited, for what puzzled me was that, after all, Hazel had not seen me. It was only the feeling of his beastly proximity that had made me feel I was seen and watched by him. There was something else, too, that made me pause before—er—doing anything. Two other things, in fact. One was that I was so intensely interested in watching the fellow’s actions. Obviously he had the same uneasy sensation that I had. He shared with me the nasty feeling that danger was about. His rifle, I saw, was cocked and ready; he kept looking behind him, over his shoulder, peering this way and that, and sometimes addressing a remark to the Siwash at his side. I caught the laughter of the latter. The Siwash evidently did not think there was danger anywhere. It was, of course, unlikely enough——”

“And the other thing that stopped you?” urged Lawson, impatiently interrupting.

Ericssen turned with a look of grim humour on his face.

“Some confounded or perverted sense of chivalry in me, I suppose,” he said, “that made it impossible to shoot him down in cold blood, or, rather, without letting him have a chance. For my blood, as a matter of fact, was far from cold at the moment. Perhaps, too, I wanted the added satisfaction of letting him know who fired the shot that was to end his vile existence.”

He laughed again. “It was rat and ferret in the human kingdom,” he went on, “but I wanted my rat to have a chance, I suppose. Anyhow, though I had a perfect shot in front of me at easy distance, I did not fire. Instead I got up, holding my cocked rifle ready, finger on trigger, and came out of my hiding place. I called to him. ‘Hazel, you beast! So there you are—at last!’

“He turned, but turned away from me, offering his horrid back. The direction of the voice he misjudged. He pointed down stream, and the Siwash turned to look. Neither of them had seen me yet. There was a big log-jam below them. The roar of the water in their ears concealed my footsteps. I was, perhaps, twenty paces from them when Hazel, with a jerk of his whole body, abruptly turned clean round and faced me. We stared into each other’s eyes.

“The amazement on his face changed instantly to hatred and resolve. He acted with incredible rapidity. I think the unexpected suddenness of his turn made me lose a precious second or two. Anyhow he was ahead of me. He flung his rifle to his shoulder. ‘You devil!’ I heard his voice. ‘I’ve got you at last!’ His rifle cracked, for he let drive the same instant. The hair stirred just above my ear.

“He had missed!

“Before he could draw back his bolt for another shot I had acted.

“‘You’re not fit to live!’ I shouted, as my bullet crashed into his temple. I had the satisfaction, too, of knowing that he heard my words. I saw the swift expression of frustrated loathing in his eyes.

“He fell like an ox, his face splashing in the stream. I shoved the body out. I saw it sucked beneath the log-jam instantly. It disappeared. There could be no inquest on him, I reflected comfortably. Hazel was gone—gone from this earth, from my life, our mutual hatred over at last.”

The speaker paused a moment. “Odd,” he continued presently—“very odd indeed.” He turned to the others. “I felt quite sorry for him suddenly. I suppose,” he added, “the philosophers are right when they gas about hate being very close to love.”

His friends contributed no remark.

“Then I came away,” he resumed shortly. “My wife—well, you know the rest, don’t you? I told her the whole thing. She—she said nothing. But she married me, you see.”

There was a moment’s silence. Baynes was the first to break it. “But—the Siwash?” he asked. “The witness?”

Lawson turned upon him with something of contemptuous impatience.

“He told you he had two cartridges.”

Ericssen, smiling grimly, said nothing at all.

From the Swiss Lakes

The suggestiveness of sudden contrast must always be a quickener to the inner life—that sharp little spur forward it gives to the imagination—and to descend from a sojourn of months among the frozen immobilities of the high Alps, and catch a great bit of the world’s surface in dancing motion, gave me a sensation the other day that was keen enough to be properly described as a “shock.” For it seemed lke passing from death into life to drop from the terrors of the silent heights and come abruptly upon the blue waters of Lake Geneva, rippling for miles in sunshine, plashing along the shores as with a sound of children playing, and carrying to and fro the white lateen sails in foretaste already of the summer. And the contrast—the transition, at least—seemed all the more sudden and effective because deep in the bosom of the lake, like giant thoughts maturing in some steady mind, lay the reflections of those very mountains left two short hours before. For the Valais Alps that tower beyond the southern shores, facing the strip from Lausanne to Villeneuve, drop into the lake dark images of themselves that stretch halfway across and readily conjure to an imaginative mind the picture of death waiting inevitably in the depths of all things.

Of all the big puddles that indent the surface of the map of Europe, Lac Leman has been my favourite—and for a somewhat bizarre reason connected with the fancies of childhood. I always thought of its crescent shape as formed by some Blue Moon in her first quarter that had tumbled from the sky and embedded herself here between the Jura and the Alps. What she loses in picturesque variety of shore and bay, she gains in the perfect symmetry of her delicately-curved lips, this crescent-shaped depression brimming with blue water. Just now, of course, she is peculiarly “brimming,” for, in common with the other lakes of Switzerland, after the downpours of the winter months she has about as much water as she can comfortably hold; and the poplars that sentinel the shores here and there like campanile seem from a disance to be standing well over their ankles among the waves. On all sides the slopes discharge their melting snows, and the Rhone, swollen and turbulent, comes tearing in with an almost unprecedented volume of mountain waters. Everywhere along the northern and western shores, as the lake curves from Chillon round to Morges (where Paderewski leads his farmer life), and along la côte past Nyon to Geneva, the vineyard slopes are all running and a-drip, while on the opposite side the streams from Faucigny and Chablais come foaming down, only yielding in torrential value to the flood rushing further east from the Valais snowfields behind St. Gingolphe and Bouveret. At night, leaning out of my hotel window, I heard this sound of many waters faintly in the air, and irresistibly came the picture of the lake as a great receiving station—some patient mother of the fairy tales taking into her untroubled heart all the passion and complaint of these troubled and troublesome children, listening to their babbling, confused tales of journeys and adventures, neither believing nor disbelieving, but accepting it all without interruption or contradiction, and finally smoothing them all down into silence and sleep, their voices hushed behind her own quiet breathing. All night long the murmur of these water-voices went on, rising and falling, telling their endless tales as they have told them since the beginning of the world—the tales of winter’s cruelties and their own release and escape on the wings of the first south wind. And the old lake, it seemed to me, was well content to listen, letting their wild stories murmur through her dreams; for they brought to her another and far more pregnant message that just now is beginning to run secretly all over the world—the message of spring. For spring touches the surface of water by ways incredibly delicate and almost indecipherable; those faint reflections of a sky that knows it first and instantly passes it on.

The life of this lake, I always think, increases as it leaves Geneva and sweeps round towards the mountains and the entrance to the Rhone Valiey. The town itself, scorched in summer, and desolated in winter by the icy bise noire that sucks down through the trough of the long curve from Lausanne, cutting like broken glass, presents itself to my imagination as the point where the Rhone escapes only too gladly. Even the seabirds prefer the Chillon end. The trees themselves grow more vital and independent towards the eastern tip; near the town they are too saturated with the heavy affairs of men to be more than half alive, and the shores where they stand in rather sorry patches to drink seem formal, killed by concrete and stone walls. One of these Geneva trees, however, has tried to escape! Everyone, as the train leaves Villeneuve coming west, must have seen that single unhappy little tree, wasted and alone, that stands upon its island of concrete walls a little east of Chillon, out some distance in the lake. Wizened and half terrified, bereft of all shelter or companionship of its kind, it grows there pluckily among the stress of wind and water, as though one night it had tried to escape, had flown down the whole length of the lake towards the mountain forests, been suddenly discovered and—fixed there for the term of its natural life at hard labour. I should like to raise a fund to transplant that plucky little tree into some big mountain wood where it would be looked after by its kind, and know its last days spent in comfort and companionship.

H. S. H.

In the mountain Club Hut, to which he had escaped after weeks of gaiety in the capital, Delane, young travelling Englishman, sat alone, and listened to the wind that beat the pines with violence. The firelight danced over the bare stone floor and raftered ceiling, giving the room an air of movement, and though the solid walls held steady against the wild spring hurricane, the cannonading of the wind seemed to threaten the foundations. For the mountain shook, the forest roared, and the shadows had a way of running everywhere as though the little building trembled. Delane watched and listened. He piled the logs on. From time to time he glanced nervously over his shoulder, restless, half uneasy, as a burst of spray from the branches dashed against the window, or a gust of unusual vehemence shook the door. Over-wearied with his long day’s climb among impossible conditions, he now realised, in this mountain refuge, his utter loneliness; for his mind gave birth to that unwelcome symptom of true loneliness—that he was not, after all, alone. Continually he heard steps and voices in the storm. Another wanderer, another climber out of season like himself, would presently arrive, and sleep was out of the question until first he heard that knocking on the door. Almost—he expected some one.

He went for the tenth time to the little window. He peered forth into the thick darkness of the dropping night, shading his eyes against the streaming pane to screen the firelight in an attempt to see if another climber—perhaps a climber in distress—were visible. The surroundings were desolate and savage, well named the Devil’s Saddle. Black-faced precipices, streaked with melting snow, rose towering to the north, where the heights were hidden in seas of vapour; waterfalls poured into abysses on two sides; a wall of impenetrable forest pressed up from the south; and the dangerous ridge he had climbed all day slid off wickedly into a sky of surging cloud. But no human figure was, of course, distinguishable, for both the lateness of the hour and the elemental fury of the night rendered it most unlikely. He turned away with a start, as the tempest delivered a blow with massive impact against his very face. Then, clearing the remnants of his frugal supper from the table, he hung his soaking clothes at a new angle before the fire, made sure the door was fastened on the inside, climbed into the bunk where white pillows and thick Austrian blankets looked so inviting, and prepared finally for sleep.

“I must be over-tired,” he sighed, after half an hour’s weary tossing, and went back to make up the sinking fire. Wood is plentiful in these climbers’ huts; he heaped it on. But this time he lit the little oil lamp as well, realising—though unwilling to acknowledge it—that it was not over-fatigue that banished sleep, but this unwelcome sense of expecting some one, of being not quite alone. For the feeling persisted and increased. He drew the wooden bench close up to the fire, turned the lamp as high as it would go, and wished unaccountably for the morning. Light was a very pleasant thing; and darkness now, for the first time since childhood, troubled him. It was outside; but it might so easily come in and swamp, obliterate, extinguish. The darkness seemed a positive thing. Already, somehow, it was established in his mind—this sense of enormous, aggressive darkness that veiled an undesirable hint of personality. Some shadow from the peaks or from the forest, immense and threatening, pervaded all his thought. “This can’t be entirely nerves,” he whispered to himself. “I’m not so tired as all that!” And he made the fire roar. He shivered and drew closer to the blaze. “I’m out of condition; that’s part of it,” he realised, and remembered with loathing the weeks of luxurious indulgence just behind him.

For Delane had rather wasted his year of educational travel. Straight from Oxford, and well supplied with money, he had first saturated his mind in the latest Continental thought—the science of France, the metaphysics and philosophy of Germany—and had then been caught aside by the gaiety of capitals where the lights are not turned out at midnight by a Sunday School police. He had been surfeited, physically, emotionally, and intellectually, till his mind and body longed hungrily for simple living again and simple teaching—above all, the latter. The Road of Excess leads to the Palace of Wisdom—for certain temperaments (as Blake forgot to add), of which Delane was one. For there was stuff in the youth, and the reaction had set in with violent abruptness. His system rebelled. He cut loose energetically from all soft delights, and craved for severity, pure air, solitude and hardship. Clean and simple conditions he must have without delay, and the tonic of physical battling. It was too early in the year to climb seriously, for the snow was still dangerous and the weather wild, but he had chosen this most isolated of all the mountain huts in order to make sure of solitude, and had come, without guide or companion, for a week’s strenuous life in wild surroundings, and to take stock of himself with a view to full recovery.

And all day long as he climbed the desolate, unsafe ridge, his mind—good, wholesome, natural symptom—had reverted to his childhood days, to the solid worldly wisdom of his church-going father, and to the early teaching (oh, how sweet and refreshing in its literal spirit!) at his mother’s knee. Now, as he watched the blazing logs, it came back to him again with redoubled force; the simple, precious, old-world stories of heaven and hell, of a paternal Deity, and of a daring, subtle, personal devil——

The interruption to his thoughts came with startling suddenness, as the roaring night descended against the windows with a thundering violence that shook the walls and sucked the flame half-way up the wide stone chimney. The oil lamp flickered and went out. Darkness invaded the room for a second, and Delane sprang from his bench, thinking the wet snow had loosened far above and was about to sweep the hut into the depths. And he was still standing, trembling and uncertain, in the middle of the room, when a deep and sighing hush followed sharp upon the elemental outburst, and in the hush, like a whisper after thunder, he heard a curious steady sound that, at first, he thought must be a footstep by the door. It was then instantly repeated. But it was not a step. It was some one knocking on the heavy oaken panels—a firm, authoritative sound, as though the new arrival had the right to enter and was already impatient at the delay.

The Englishman recovered himself instantly, realising with keen relief the new arrival—at last.

“Another climber like myself, of course,” he said, “or perhaps the man who comes to prepare the hut for others. The season has begun.” And he went over quickly, without a further qualm, to unbolt the door.

“Forgive!” he exclaimed in German, as he threw it wide, “I was half asleep before the fire. It is a terrible night. Come in to food and shelter, for both are here, and you shall share such supper as I possess.”

And a tall, cloaked figure passed him swiftly with a gust of angry wind from the impenetrable blackness of the world beyond. On the threshold, for a second, his outline stood full in the blaze of firelight with the sheet of darkness behind it, stately, erect, commanding, his cloak torn fiercely by the wind, but the face hidden by a low-brimmed hat; and an instant later the door shut with resounding clamour upon the hurricane, and the two men turned to confront one another in the little room.

Delane then realised two things sharply, both of them fleeting impressions, but acutely vivid: First, that the outside darkness seemed to have entered and established itself between him and the new arrival; and, secondly, that the stranger’s face was difficult to focus for clear sight, although the covering hat was now removed. There was a blur upon it somewhere. And this the Englishman ascribed partly to the flickering effect of firelight, and partly to the lightning glare of the man’s masterful and terrific eyes, which made his own sight waver in some curious fashion as he gazed upon him. These impressions, however, were but momentary and passing, due doubtless to the condition of his nerves and to the semi-shock of the dramatic, even theatrical entrance. Delane’s senses, in this wild setting, were guilty of exaggeration. For now, while helping the man remove his cloak, speaking naturally of shelter, food, and the savage weather, he lost this first distortion and his mind recovered sane proportion. The stranger, after all, though striking, was not of appearance so uncommon as to cause alarm; the light and the low doorway had touched his stature with illusion. He dwindled. And the great eyes, upon calmer subsequent inspection, lost their original fierce lightning. The entering darkness, moreover, was but an effect of the upheaving night behind him as he strode across the threshold. The closed door proved it.

And yet, as Delane continued his quieter examination, there remained, he saw, the startling quality which had caused that first magnifying in his mind. His senses, while reporting accurately, insisted upon this arresting and uncommon touch: there was, about this late wanderer of the night, some evasive, lofty strangeness that set him utterly apart from ordinary men.

The Englishman examined him searchingly, surreptitiously, but with a touch of passionate curiosity he could not in the least account for nor explain. There were contradictions of perplexing character about him. For the first presentment had been of splendid youth, while on the face, though vigorous and gloriously handsome, he now discerned the stamp of tremendous age. It was worn and tired. While radiant with strength and health and power, it wore as well this certain signature of deep exhaustion that great experience rather than physical experience brings. Moreover, he discovered in it, in some way he could not hope to describe, man, woman, and child. There was a big, sad earnestness about it, yet a touch of humour too; patience, tenderness, and sweetness held the mouth; and behind the high pale forehead intellect sat enthroned and watchful. In it were both love and hatred, longing and despair; an expression of being ever on the defensive, yet hugely mutinous; an air both hunted and beseeching; great knowledge and great woe.

Delane gave up the search, aware that something unalterably splendid stood before him. Solemnity and beauty swept him too. His was never the grotesque assumption that man must be the highest being in the universe, nor that a thing is a miracle merely because it has never happened before. He groped, while explanation and analysis both halted. “A great teacher,” thought fluttered through him, “or a mighty rebel! A distinguished personality beyond all question! Who can he be?” There was something regal that put respect upon his imagination instantly. And he remembered the legend of the country-side that Ludwig of Bavaria was said to be about when nights were very wild. He wondered. Into his speech and manner crept unawares an attitude of deference that was almost reverence, and with it—whence came this other quality?—a searching pity.

“You must be wearied out,” he said respectfully, busying himself about the room, “as well as cold and wet. This fire will dry you, sir, and meanwhile I will prepare quickly such food as there is, if you will eat it.” For the other carried no knapsack, nor was he clothed for the severity of mountain travel.

“I have already eaten,” said the stranger courteously, “and, with my thanks to you, I am neither wet nor tired. The afflictions that I bear are of another kind, though ones that you shall more easily, I am sure, relieve.”

He spoke as a man whose words set troops in action, and Delane glanced at him, deeply moved by the surprising phrase, yet hardly marvelling that it should be so. He found no ready answer. But there was evidently question in his look, for the other continued, and this time with a smile that betrayed sheer winning beauty as of a tender woman:

“I saw the light and came to it. It is unusual—at this time.”

His voice was resonant, yet not deep. There was a ringing quality about it that the bare room emphasised. It charmed the young Englishman inexplicably. Also, it woke in him a sense of infinite pathos.

“You are a climber, sir, like myself,” Delane resumed, lifting his eyes a moment uneasily from the coffee he brewed over a corner of the fire. “You know this neighbourhood, perhaps? Better, at any rate, than I can know it?” His German halted rather. He chose his words with difficulty. There was uncommon trouble in his mind.

“I know all wild and desolate places,” replied the other, in perfect English, but with a wintry mournfulness in his voice and eyes, “for I feel at home in them, and their stern companionship my nature craves as solace. But, unlike yourself, I am no climber.”

“The heights have no attraction for you?” asked Delane, as he mingled steaming milk and coffee in the wooden bowl, marvelling what brought him then so high above the valleys. “It is their difficulty and danger that fascinate me always. I find the loneliness of the summits intoxicating in a sense.”

And, regardless of refusal, he set the bread and meat before him, the apple and the tiny packet of salt, then turned away to place the coffee pot beside the fire again. But as he did so a singular gesture of the other caught his eyes. Before touching bowl or plate, the stranger took the fruit and brushed his lips with it. He kissed it, then set it on the ground and crushed it into pulp beneath his heel. And, seeing this, the young Englishman knew something dreadfully arrested in his mind, for, as he looked away, pretending the act was unobserved, a thing of ice and darkness moved past him through the room, so that the pot trembled in his hand, rattling sharply against the hearthstone where he stooped. He could only interpret it as an act of madness, and the myth of the sad, drowned monarch wandering through this enchanted region, pressed into him again unsought and urgent. It was a full minute before he had control of his heart and hand again.

The bowl was half emptied, and the man was smiling—this time the smile of a child who implores the comfort of enveloping and understanding arms.

“I am a wanderer rather than a climber,” he was saying, as though there had been no interval, “for, though the lonely summits suit me well, I now find in them only—terror. My feet lose their sureness, and my head its steady balance. I prefer the hidden gorges of these mountains, and the shadows of the covering forests. My days”—his voice drew the loneliness of uttermost space into its piteous accents—“are passed in darkness. I can never climb again.”

He spoke this time, indeed, as a man whose nerve was gone for ever. It was pitiable almost to tears. And Delane, unable to explain the amazing contradictions, felt recklessly, furiously drawn to this trapped wanderer with the mien of a king yet the air and speech sometimes of a woman and sometimes of an outcast child.

“Ah, then you have known accidents,” Delane replied with outer calmness, as he lit his pipe, trying in vain to keep his hand as steady as his voice. “You have been in one perhaps. The effect, I have been told, is——”

The power and sweetness in that resonant voice took his breath away as he heard it break in upon his own uncertain accents:

“I have—fallen,” the stranger replied impressively, as the rain and wind wailed past the building mournfully, “yet a fall that was no part of any accident. For it was no common fall,” the man added with a magnificent gesture of disdain, “while yet it broke my heart in two.” He stooped a little as he uttered the next words with a crying pathos that an outcast woman might have used. “I am,” he said, “engulfed in intolerable loneliness. I can never climb again.”

With a shiver impossible to control, half of terror, half of pity, Delane moved a step nearer to the marvellous stranger. The spirit of Ludwig, exiled and distraught, had gripped his soul with a weakening terror; but now sheer beauty lifted him above all personal shrinking. There seemed some echo of lost divinity, worn, wild yet grandiose, through which this significant language strained towards a personal message—for himself.

“In loneliness?” he faltered, sympathy rising in a flood.

“For my Kingdom that is lost to me for ever,” met him in deep, throbbing tones that set the air on fire. “For my imperial ancient heights that jealousy took from me——”

The stranger paused, with an indescribable air of broken dignity and pain.

Outside the tempest paused a moment before the awful elemental crash that followed. A bellowing of many winds descended like artillery upon the world. A burst of smoke rushed from the fireplace about them both, shrouding the stranger momentarily in a flying veil. And Delane stood up, uncomfortable in his very bones. “What can it be?” he asked himself sharply. “Who is this being that he should use such language?” He watched alarm chase pity, aware that the conversation held something beyond experience. But the pity returned in greater and ever greater flood. And love surged through him too. It was significant, he remembered afterwards, that he felt it incumbent upon himself to stand. Curious, too, how the thought of that mad, drowned monarch haunted memory with such persistence. Some vast emotion that he could not name drove out his subsequent words. The smoke had cleared, and a strange, high stillness held the world. The rain streamed down in torrents, isolating these two somehow from the haunts of men. And the Englishman stared then into a countenance grown mighty with woe and loneliness. There stood darkly in it this incommunicable magnificence of pain that mingled awe with the pity he had felt. The kingly eyes looked clear into his own, completing his subjugation out of time. “I would follow you,” ran his thought upon its knees, “follow you with obedience for ever and ever, even into a last damnation. For you are sublime. You shall come again into your Kingdom, if my own small worship——”

Then blackness sponged the reckless thought away. He spoke in its place a more guarded, careful thing:

“I am aware,” he faltered, yet conscious that he bowed, “of standing before a Great One of some world unknown to me. Who he may be I have but the privilege of wondering. He has spoken darkly of a Kingdom that is lost. Yet he is still, I see, a Monarch.” And he lowered his head and shoulders involuntarily.

For an instant, then, as he said it, the eyes before him flashed their original terrific lightnings. The darkness of the common world faded before the entrance of an Outer Darkness. From gulfs of terror at his feet rose shadows out of the night of time, and a passionate anguish as of sudden madness seized his heart and shook it.

He listened breathlessly for the words that followed. It seemed some wind of unutterable despair passed in the breath from those non-human lips:

“I am still a Monarch, yes; but my Kingdom is taken from me, for I have no single subject. Lost in a loneliness that lies out of space and time, I am become a throneless Ruler, and my hopelessness is more than I can bear.” The beseeching pathos of the voice tore him in two. The Deity himself, it seemed, stood there accused of jealousy, of sin and cruelty. The stranger rose. The power about him brought the picture of a planet, throned in mid-heaven and poised beyond assault. “Not otherwise,” boomed the startling words as though an avalanche found syllables, “could I now show myself to—you.”

Delane was trembling horribly. He felt the next words slip off his tongue unconsciously. The shattering truth had dawned upon his soul at last.

“Then the light you saw, and came to——?” he whispered.

“Was the light in your heart that guided me,” came the answer, sweet, beguiling as the music in a woman’s tones, “the light of your instant, brief desire that held love in it.” He made an opening movement with his arms as he continued, smiling like stars in summer. “For you summoned me; summoned me by your dear and precious belief: how dear, how precious, none can know but I who stand before you.”

His figure drew up with an imperial air of proud dominion. His feet were set among the constellations. The opening movement of his arms continued slowly. And the music in his tones seemed merged in distant thunder.

“For your single, brief belief,” he smiled with the grandeur of a condescending Emperor, “shall give my vanished Kingdom back to me.”

And with an air of native majesty he held his hand out—to be kissed.

The black hurricane of night, the terror of frozen peaks, the yawning horror of the great abyss outside—all three crowded into the Englishman’s mind with a slashing impact that blocked delivery of any word or action. It was not that he refused, it was not that he withdrew, but that Life stood paralysed and rigid. The flow stopped dead for the first time since he had left his mother’s womb. The God in him was turned to stone and rendered ineffective. For an appalling instant God was not.

He realised the stupendous moment. Before him, drinking his little soul out merely by his Presence, stood one whose habit of mind, not alone his external accidents, was imperial with black prerogative before the first man drew the breath of life. August procedure was native to his inner process of existence. The stars and confines of the universe owned his sway before he fell, to trifle away the dreary little centuries by haunting the minds of feeble men and women, by hiding himself in nursery cupboards, and by grinning with stained gargoyles from the roofs of city churches. ...

And the lad’s life stammered, flickered, threatened to go out before the enveloping terror of the revelation.

“I called to you ... but called to you in play,” thought whispered somewhere deep below the level of any speech, yet not so low that the audacious sound of it did not crash above the elements outside; “for ... till now ... you have been to me but a ... coated bogy ... that my brain disowned with laughter ... and my heart thought picturesque. If you are here ... alive! May God forgive me for my ...”

It seemed as though tears—the tears of love and profound commiseration—drowned the very seed of thought itself.

A sound stopped him that was like a collapse in heaven. Some crashing, as of a ruined world, passed splintering through his little timid heart. He did not yield, but he understood—with an understanding which seemed the delicate first sign of yielding—the seductiveness of evil, the sweet delight of surrendering the Will with utter recklessness to those swelling forces which disintegrate the heroic soul in man. He remembered. It was true. In the reaction from excess he had definitely called upon his childhood’s teaching with a passing moment of genuine belief. And now that yearning of a fraction of a second bore its awful fruit. The luscious Capitals where he had rioted passed in a coloured stream before his eyes; the Wine, the Woman, and the Song stood there before him, clothed in that Power which lies insinuatingly disguised behind their little passing show of innocence. Their glamour donned this domino of regal and virile grandeur. He felt entangled beyond recovery. The idea of God seemed sterile and without reality. The one real thing, the one desirable thing, the one possible, strong and beautiful thing—was to bend his head and kiss those imperial fingers. He moved noiselessly towards the Hand. He raised his own to take it and lift it towards his mouth——

When there rose in his mind with startling vividness a small, soft picture of a child’s nursery, a picture of a little boy, kneeling in scanty night-gown with pink upturned soles, and asking ridiculous, audacious things of a shining Figure seated on a summer cloud above the kitchen-garden walnut tree.

The tiny symbol flashed and went its way, yet not before it had lit the entire world with glory. For there came an absolutely routing power with it. In that half-forgotten instant’s craving for the simple teaching of his childhood days, Belief had conjured with two immense traditions. This was the second of them. The appearance of the one had inevitably produced the passage of its opposite. ...

And the Hand that floated in the air before him to be kissed sank slowly down below the possible level of his lips. He shrank away. Though laughter tempted something in his brain, there still clung about his heart the first aching, pitying terror. But size retreated, dwindling somehow as it went. The wind and rain obliterated every other sound; yet in that bare, unfurnished room of a climber’s mountain hut, there was a silence, above the roar, that drank in everything and broke the back of speech. In opposition to this masquerading splendour Delane had set up a personal, paternal Deity.

“I thought of you, perhaps,” cried the voice of self-defence, “but I did not call to you with real belief. And, by the name of God, I did not summon you. For your sweetness, as your power, sickens me; and your hand is black with the curses of all the mothers in the world, whose prayers and tears——”

He stopped dead, overwhelmed by the cruelty of his reckless utterance.

And the Other moved towards him slowly. It was like the summit of some peaked and terrible height that moved. He spoke. He changed appallingly.

“But I claim,” he roared, “your heart. I claim you by that instant of belief you felt. For by that alone you shall restore to me my vanished Kingdom. You shall worship me.”

In the countenance was a sudden awful power; but behind the stupefying roar there was weakness in the voice as of an imploring and beseeching child. Again, deep love and searching pity seared the Englishman’s heart as he replied in the gentlest accents he could find to master:

“And I claim you,” he said, “by my understanding sympathy, and by my sorrow for your God-forsaken loneliness, and by my love. For no Kingdom built on hate can stand against the love you would deny——”

Words failed him then, as he saw the majesty fade slowly from the face, grown small and shadowy. One last expression of desperate energy in the eyes struck lightnings from the smoky air, as with an abandoned movement of the entire figure, he drew back, it seemed, towards the door behind him.

Delane moved slowly after him, opening his arms. Tenderness and big compassion flung wide the gates of love within him. He found strange language, too, although actual, spoken words did not produce them further than his entrails where they had their birth.

“Toys in the world are plentiful, Sire, and you may have them for your masterpiece of play. But you must seek them where they still survive; in the churches, and in isolated lands where thought lies unawakened. For they are the children’s blocks of make-believe whose palaces, like your once tremendous kingdom, have no true existence for the thinking mind.”

And he stretched his hands towards him with the gesture of one who sought to help and save, then paused as he realised that his arms enclosed sheer blackness, with the emptiness of wind and driving rain.

For the door of the hut stood open, and Delane balanced on the threshold, facing the sheet of night above the abyss. He heard the waterfalls in the valley far below. The forest flapped and tossed its myriad branches. Cold draughts swept down from spectral fields of melting snow above; and the blackness turned momentarily into the semblance of towers and bastions of thick beaten gloom. Above one soaring turret, then, a space of sky appeared, swept naked by a violent, lost wind—an opening of purple into limitless distance. For one second, amid the vapours, it was visible, empty and untenanted. The next, there sailed across its small diameter a falling Star. With an air of slow and endless leisure, yet at the same time with terrific speed, it dived behind the ragged curtain of the clouds, and the space closed up again. Blackness returned upon the heavens.

And through this blackness, plunging into that abyss of woe whence he had momentarily risen, the figure of the marvellous stranger melted utterly away. Delane, for a fleeting second, was aware of the earnestness in the sad, imploring countenance; of its sweetness and its power so strangely mingled; of it mysterious grandeur; and of its pathetic childishness. But, already, it was sunk into interminable distance. A star that would be baleful, yet was merely glorious, passed on its endless wandering among the teeming systems of the universe. Behind the fixed and steady stars, secure in their appointed places, it set. It vanished into the pit of unknown emptiness. It was gone.

“God help you!” sighed across the sea of wailing branches, echoing down the dark abyss below. “God give you rest at last!”

For he saw a princely, nay, an imperial Being, homeless for ever, and for ever wandering, hunted as by keen remorseless winds about a universe that held no corner for his feet, his majesty unworshipped, his reign a mockery, his Court unfurnished, and his courtiers mere shadows of deep space. ...

And a thin, grey dawn, stealing up behind clearing summits in the east, crept then against the windows of the mountain hut. It brought with it a treacherous, sharp air that made the sleeper draw another blanket near to shelter him from the sudden cold. For the fire had died out, and an icy draught sucked steadily beneath the doorway.

Her Birthday

It was her birthday on the morrow, and I set forth to find a suitable and worthy present. My means, judged by the standards of the big merchants, seemed trivial; yet, could I but discover the right gift, no matter how insignificant, I felt sure that it would please her, and so make me doubly happy. And the kind of gift I already knew, for I had a specimen of it in my humble lodgings; only of so poor a type that I was ashamed to offer it. I must find somewhere a much, much better one, if possible, perfect and without a single flaw. I went, therefore, into the great shops and saw a thousand wonderful and lovely things.

So particular was I, however, and so difficult to suit, that I wearied the salesfolk, and began to feel despondent. All that they showed me was so wrong-so cheap. In the matter of actual expense there was no disagreement, for I mentioned plainly beforehand the price that I would pay, or, rather, that I was prepared to pay. But in the nature and quality of the goods there was no satisfying me at all. Everything that they spread before my eyes seemed ordinary, trifling, even spurious. Marvellously fashioned, and of the most costly description, they yet seemed somewhere counterfeit. The goods were sham. Already she possessed far better. There was nowhere and I went to the very best emporiums where the rich and favoured of the world bought their offeringsthere was nowhere the little genuine thing I sought. The finest that was set before me seemed unworthy. I compared one and all with the specimen, broken yet authentic, that I had at home. And even the cleverest of the salesfolk was unable to deceive me, because I knew.

“And this, for instance?” I asked at length, far from content, yet thinking it might just do perhaps in place of anything better I could find. “How much is this magnificent, jewelled thing, with its ingenious little surprise for each day in the entire year? You mentioned—?”

“Ten million pounds, sir,” said the man obsequiously, while he eyed me with a close and questioning glance.

“Ten million only !” And I laughed in his face.

That was the price you named, sir,” he murmured.

I drew myself up, looking disdainfully, pityingly at him. And, though he met my eye, he hesitated. Over his tired features there stole a soft and marvellous expression. Something more tender than starlight shone in his little eyes. And, as he answered in a gentle voice that was almost a whisper, I saw him smile as a man may smile when he understands a divine, unutterable thing. Glory touched him for an instant with high radiance, and a hint of delicious awe hid shyly in his voice. I barely caught the words, so low he murmured them :

I fear, sir, that what you want is not to be had at all-in our establishment. You will hardly find it. It is not in the market.” He seemed to bow his head in reverence a moment. ” It is not-for sale.”

And so I went back to my dingy lodgings, having made no single purchase. I looked I fondly at my own little specimen, trying to imagine it had somehow gained in value, in beauty, almost in splendour. At least, I said to myself, it is not spurious. It is real …

And, sitting down to my table, I dipped my broken pen into a penny bottle of inferior ink, and began my birthday letter :—

“This is your birthday, dear, and I send you all my love” Being young, I underlined the words describing my little present, thinking to increase its value thus.

But I did not complete the sentence, for there was another thing that I must find to send her, or she would be disappointed. And a birthday comes but once a year. But, again, though I already possessed a tiny specimen of this other thing I sought, it did not seem to me nearly good enough to offer. Though genuine, it was worn by frequent use. Its lustre had dimmed a little, for I touched it daily. It seemed too ordinary and common for a special present. I was ashamed to send it.

So I set out again and searched … and searched … in every likely and unlikely place, even groping in the dark about the altars of the churches where I found by chance the doors ajar, and penetrating to those secret shrines where those who seek truth, it is said, go in to pray. For I knew that there was this other little present from me that she would look for because she had need of it. …

And my search was wonderful and full of high adventure, yet so long that the moon had drawn the hood over the door of her silver tent, and the stars were fading in the east behind the towers of the night, before I returned home, footsore, aching, empty-handed, and very humble in my heart. For nowhere had I been able to find this other little thing she would be pleased to have from me. To my amazement, yet to my secret joy, I found nothing better than what I had at home-nothing, that is, indubitably genuine. In quantity it was not anywhere for sale. It was more rare than I had guessed-and I felt delicious triumph in me.

I sat down, humble, reverent, but incommunicably proud and happy, to my unfinished letter. Unless I posted it immediately she would not get it when she woke upon her birthday morning. I finished it. I posted it just as it was—brief, the writing a little shaky, the paper cheap, blot, smudge, and all :

” … and my worship.”

And then, like a scrap of paper that enclosed the other gifts, yet need not be noticed unless she wished it, I added (above the little foolish name she knew me by) another tiny presentall that I had brought into the world or could take out with me again when I left it :

I wrote: “Yours ever faith-fully.”

How Garnier Broke the Log-Jam

A Camp-Fire Story

A log-jam is a mighty serious thing, an ‘don’t you forgit it,” said Hank Davis, as he carefully selected a burning ember n the camp fire with his naked fingers and held it to the ash of a half-smoked cigar.

We others, sitting cleaning our guns by the fitful light, said nothing, for we knew this was Hank’s preface to a yarn. All day long we had tramped the woods and marshes on the trail of the elusive moose, and after a big supper of venison, trout, and coffee, we were just in the mood for a story. We felt, too, that Hank-this picturesque, dirty, hard-faced son of the woods - was just the fellow to tell it.

There he sat opposite to us, leaning against a fallen tree, his face smeared, his slouch hat over one eye, and his big fingers toying with the gleaming barrel that always carried true when it rested against his shoulder and had his fierce eye looking down it.

“An’ I never hunt through these pairts and see the runnin’ water,” he went on as though to himself, ” without calling to mind that thar frog-eatin’ Canuck, Jean Garnier, an’ how ‘ ’twas he broke the jam way back in the sixties.”

Behind us the tents shone white and ghostly in the firelight, and the stars peeped down through a tangle of pine- branches that just stirred in the night breeze. On our left the big lake stretched for many miles, and there was not a habitable bit of land in any direction under a two days’ journey.

So we learned (in language that will not bear faithful reproduction) that Jean Garnier hailed originally from a little village near Montreal, named Ste. Rose. He had lived there all his life, more or less, and ” a mighty wet life it was too.” For Garnier was very fond of the white whisky of French Canada - that powerful fiery liquid made from corn and found all through Upper Canada- and was more often under its influence than otherwise. But, in spite of his bad habits, he had won the love of a very charming girl in the village, and he loved her too, he told himself, better than any thing else in the world.

“With a single exception,” she said to him one day. That horrid whisky -you love that better than you love me. Other wise you’d give it up for me.”

“But you wouldn’t cast away a man just because a drop of whisky.”

“Jean,of Jean! It’s because I love you so much, that’s why I say I won’t marry you till you give over swallowing that vile white fire.” The girl looked up with a loving appeal in her brown eyes, but she saw the deepening frown on his face, and her heart misgave her.

Jean, dear, you were a strong- built man a while ago, and I was mighty proud when you came that day and put your arm round my waist and said you loved me- me, a weakly bit of a thing, and you standing up six feet of beautiful strength. The girls were all wild you chose me. Now they laugh instead. And it’s all that dreadful drink—”

The man drew closer, interrupting her with a fierce gesture. “Marry me straight away, Lucie, and I’ll swear never to touch another drop. I’ll give it up altogether.”

He bent his dark head down to the level of her face and stretched out his arms to catch her to his heart. But she slipped past him, white to the lips, and her heart thump ing. She knew this was a last struggle, and her mind was made up. Her courage must not fail her now after all those hours of prayer and sleeplessness. He had broken a hundred promises for the drink ; but she believed in his love, and was determined not to spare herself if she could only save him.

Jean was dimly conscious of the nobility of her love, and her great force of character worked subtly upon him and overcame him. His arms dropped to his side, and he fell back a pace or two. The longing rose in him eagerly, triumphantly, as it had risen many a time before, to become the true man again, to fight with his whole being and win at last. A stray gleam of sunshine fell from the clouds just then, and threw into vivid contrast the strength of his face and the signs of weakness born of long indulgence. The double revelation smote the girl anew. She drew to his side again.

“Oh, Jean, I cannot argue, but voice broke—” but tell me again that you do love me, more than anything else in the whole world. Give me your promise once again. I’ll believe it—”

There was a deep silence between them. The sun was hidden by a passing cloud. The wind stirred mournfully in the clustering Golden Rod behind them, as if the sighs their hearts would not hold had passed out together and mingled in the air of heaven before them.

The man’s eyes were fixed upon the ground. The moments passed, and he showed no sign that he had even heard her appeal. Then a low sob from the girl broke the silence. Jean suddenly straightened and shook himself. He squared his splendid shoulders, and his great chest heaved with the breathing of strong emotion.

“Lucie, child,” he said simply—but his voice was very low and tense—” I love you better than anything else in heaven or earth, and I cannot lose you. I give you my promise, and this time le lon Dieu will help me to keep it.”

She looked up gratefully, with swimming eyes.

“But first,” he went on, ” I shall go away. You will wait for me ; it will not be long- a few months at most ; but when I come back I shall be your old Jean again- a man- and worthy of your splendid love. And, remember always, I love you.”

It was late autumn when this conversation took place, and a large lumber camp was then in process of formation. Garnier saw the chance to get away from his old companions into a vigorous open- air life that would give his system strength for the great battle. He joined the camp and went away into the far lonely region of forest near the head- waters of the Ottawa River (where we were moose -hunting when Hank told us the story), and for six months the snow and ice cut them off from civilisation as completely as if they had gone to the moon.

The little world of a lumber camp, shut in by the snows and the frozen lakes, surrounded by bleak hills and leagues of path less forest, has a peculiar interest all its own. A winter that brings a snowfall of ten feet, with thirty-foot drifts and a temperature of forty degrees below zero, is a very serious winter indeed. The life in the camp is almost martial, and necessarily so. In an average sized camp there are some fifty men, rough, vigorous, often desperate fellows, and they are ruled with a rod of iron by the Shanty Boss -i.e. he who rules over the shanty. For there is one huge pine- log shanty in which they eat, and another in which they sleep. The latter has several large stoves burning night and day, and hardly any ventilation. Wooden bunks, three deep, with blankets, and moss or cedar-branches for mattresses, line the walls all the way round. A cook and a cookee” (assistant cook) rule over the eating shanty, and pro vide the men with four tremendous meals a day-salt pork, crushed apples, coffee, brown sugar, and a rough kind of bread. The camp rises long before it is light, and at once, after breakfast, the men go out to chop down the trees. At ten o’clock a meal is brought out to them. At two o’clock it is repeated. At six o’clock they come home, dog tired, for the fourth meal, and by eight o’clock they are in bed and asleep. No ” shooting- irons “” are allowed to be brought into camp, and another rule (which seems to an outsider who has seen the sleepy, tired crew trudge home, almost unnecessary), very strictly enforced, forbids a single spoken word in the sleeping shanty.

The work is extremely hard, and there is little energy left over for fighting or quarrel. ling, although some Shanty Bosses rule their commandoes with more success than others.

The “axeing” of the big trees is all done while there is snow on the ground, for with out its slippery assistance it would be impossible to draw the huge logs to the water’s edge. One set of men make a roadway to the nearest lake or stream, consisting of a main artery with smaller trails running into it and taking in all the big trees on the way. Saplings and undergrowth are cut away from the surface of the snow so that the horses may have a clear skidway along which to draw the great logs. In the summer these skidways are recognisable as faint vistas through the forest, always leading to water.

Once the logs reach the lake or stream they are piled up in stacks twenty feet high along the shore, and, when the ice melts in the spring, are tumbled over into the water and floated in immense ” booms ” acres in extent, for many weeks, across lakes and down streams till they reach the swift waters of the Ottawa River, and thence are guided to the saw-mills many miles farther to the southwards.

In the spring these booms choke up many a good fishing stream. Perhaps some unwieldy log gets caught by a projection in the bank at a sharp corner. Instantly the others, ever crowding on behind, pile up upon its back, and in a short time a towering heap of logs dams the river from bank to bank, forms an ever-changing waterfall, floods the surrounding ” bush,” and, in short, forms a log- jam. To start the logs on their journey again is to “break a jam,” and it may easily be imagined that the task of disentangling these massive tree-trunks one from another and setting loose the heap of ill- balanced monsters is one fraught with the greatest personal danger. In fact, to break a jam is to lead a forlorn hope, and the honour is pressed upon no one. The Gangman of the boom asks for volunteers from among the single men ; and more than one fine fellow whose sweetheart is waiting in some far village of the St. Lawrence to marry him when the camp breaks up in the early summer has lost her prospective husband in this manner.

Guiding the booms, even in clear water, is a dangerous matter. With spiked boots and a balancing-pole that is also a thrusting-pole, the men run along the logs, jumping from one to the other and keeping their balance with amazing agility. Here and there, however, it may be a man slips in and the logs close over him and make it impossible for him to rise to the surface again.

Hank gave us all this information, much adorned with unnecessary expletives, by way of explaining what happened subsequently to Garnier, for Hank and Garnier were members of the same camp, and when it broke up to follow the logs in the spring, they chanced also to be assigned to the same boom.

The men were half-way down a little rushing stream, called, if I remember rightly, the Sabbatis River, when the jam came upon them.

The water was unusually high, full of melted snow and lumps of ice. The journey across the open lakes had been cold and dangerous, and the moment the boom headed into the narrow stream it started off in a wild rush, with a clumsy galloping motion of its great logs that filled the woods round with deep echoes. This headlong career down stream of an army of tree trunks has something uncanny, even horrible, about it. They seem almost alive, like some antediluvian monsters escaping from the lake in preconcerted onslaught, their ribs black and shining, snorting as they go, irresistible, terrific. As they crash together in the foaming water, leaping away from the impact, half-climbing upon one another’s shoulders, and slipping back with a roar into the waves, to thrust their blunt noses again skywards the next moment, it is difficult to believe that they are merely so a much dead wood racing on as fast as ever they can go to the whizzing saws of the mills.

The men knew the dangers that lay ahead, increasing every moment ; but none of them flinched. Personal courage in a lumber camp is at a discount, or, as Hank put it more picturesquely, ” You kin bet your sweet life there ain’t no white-livered skulkers in a lumber camp outfit.” So that, when the inevitable jam came and the logs began piling up upon each other, with that dreadful thunderous sound which must be heard to be appreciated, it was certainly through no fault of theirs ; and, having done all they could to prevent it, they sprang, dived, swam, or wriggled for the shore, each as best he could, and fortunately with no accidents and no lives lost.

There, in mid-stream, the logs banged and crashed together. The massive wall grew more and more solid. The water hissed through it in places, gurgling up underneath it, and pouring in little torrents over it, wherever it could find a way. A black 1 barrier had suddenly barred the river’s course. Logs stuck out at all possible angles, like huge pencils in a heap of children’s toys. Some stood upright, others lurched sideways, and the whole mass heaved and swayed and groaned as the weight increased and the water pressed up against it.

And, meanwhile, the burden of the water grew steadily behind, and the river began to rise perceptibly.

The time had come to call for volunteers. Some one must break the jam.

Standing behind a clump of hemlock trees, out of sight of the rest of the men, Jean Garnier was wrestling with his thoughts. Here was the chance he had been looking for-the chance of proving beyond a doubt to the girl he loved that he was a man once more, that his courage had returned, his nerves grown steady, and that he was master of himself. No man of intemperate habits and shaken nerve could hope to break a log-jam successfully. Everybody knew that. The girls should no longer laugh at her, or the men sneer at him. He could hold up his head again in the village, for she would be proud of him, and he would have proved that he had once for all, and finally, turned over a new leaf. This was only a single act, true, but it was the culmination of many, many weeks of self- restraint, and 1 she would know and realise this, and her respect would come back for him.

He weighed swiftly the awful risk of losing her, and perhaps of breaking her heart, if he failed and was killed. But he cast them aside in the balance. Somehow he felt sure he would get through all right. His old confidence in himself had returned. There were many offers even in the first five minutes, but no one could stand against Jean Garnier. His experience, his strength, his length of limb and arm, and his undoubted skill, all combined to favour him.

He shook hands with a few pals and laughed when the Shanty Boss, a man of proved courage himself, gave him a word of final advice, and added to it-a strange phrase in such company-” may God bring you safe through it.”

Only one man can break a jam. Others can help from the shore, or from whatever vantage-points there may be ; but one mind, and above all one man’s weight, must decide the awful course of the loosening mass.

Before starting, he crossed over to speak to his friend Hank Davis. ” You know why I’m doing this, Hank,” he said in his Canuck French. “It’s simply to show her that I’ve got back my nerve and courage, and that I’m not the loafer I used to be. If anything happens, give her my wages, and tell her why I did it. See? “

Hank gave him a characteristic blessing, and Garnier looked over his shoulder and laughed as he said, ” I’ll get through all right ; don’t you worry yourself.”

The next moment he was gone. A crowd of silent men stood in the shadow of the great trees and watched. Garnier carried his pole easily and approached the jam from the rear, springing from log to log where they lay tightly packed and ever rising on the swollen river. A strange silence descended upon the crowd in the wood. The roar of the water became a thing apart. Every eye was fixed on Garnier-a tall, sinewy figure, passing lightly through the spray from log to log ; springing with unerring judgment across foaming gaps ; leaving one log just before it turned ; landing on another, and leaping from it again to a third a second before it was sucked endways, first rising like a pillar, into a vortex of whirling waves.

He soon reached the summit of the barrier and began to use his spiked pole with a will. He thrust here and there ; dislodged a log on his left, helped forward one on his right, and toppled over another in front of him. The judgment of the man never failed. It became an awful fight between the river and the logs, seeking to destroy him, and the skilful courageous woodsman a fight in which the slightest miscalculation, or false distribution of a few pounds’ weight, meant a terrible death.

“If anyone can do it, he can,” murmured the boss, cold- blooded, and without excitement, leaning against a tree on the shore and smoking his pipe. It was not the first time he had seen jams broken by a long way.

“Oh, I guess he’ll fix it all right,” said another, a personal pal of Garnier’s, and whose eyes never left the leaping, shifting figure out in mid-stream.

Just then there rose on the air a terrifying sound. It seemed to come from under the ground, and the very earth shook. The next minute the whole solid barrier of logs melted away like summer mist before the men’s eyes. The jam was broken. It collapsed with an appalling shout of sound. Water spurted up in a hundred fountains to the sky. Whole groups of logs rose on end, wet and shaking, and fell crashing against one another. Then a mighty wave rolled down the river from the wall of water accumulated behind the jam, and the entire mass slid in a broad seething of water past the watching crowd of men and into a bank of enveloping spray beyond.

On the crest of this great wave, erect and calm amid the leaping logs, stood the figure of Garnier. He still held his pole as he swept past them and vanished into the fierce confusion of mist and foam below.

A second later, at the bottom of the fall, the logs could be heard crashing and smash ing together with a fiendish uproar in the swirling waters. The men turned to look at one another, and the Shanty Boss looked up the river instead of down. A second later, and the men were flying down the banks to gather the logs into a new boom, and, if possible, to find the body of Jean Garnier. It would, of course, be in pieces, perhaps even unrecognisable ; but still they could put him in a decent grave, with a wooden cross and the date, and the Shanty Boss could mumble a prayer over it while they stood round and bared their heads beneath ” the murmuring pines and the hemlocks.”

But, as they were searching the shore a quarter of a mile or so lower down, a faint voice was heard calling across the river—

I’m all right, boys ; but get a hustle on and come over to me.”

It seemed incredible, but, following the direction of the sound with their eyes, they saw a man’s figure crouching on the shore just beyond the reach of the still swollen river. It was indeed Garnier. His face was scarcely recognisable as a human countenance, and both his arms turned out to be broken, but apparently he had escaped serious internal injury in the most marvellous manner.

No one ever knew how he escaped, least of all the man himself.

“I saw you all standing under the trees like a streak of black,” he said, “as I was carried past, and the next minute a tree jumped up an’ caught me such a smack in the face that I thought the whole of my skull had gone off with it. That’s all I remember.”

But the chance wave that swept him into safety on the shore had also brought him back a helpless, disfigured man for life. No girl would care to marry him now, and the courage of this rough woodsman was again shown -even if it was mistaken courage-in his decision to live for the rest of his broken life in the woods, and to show himself no more in the village of Ste. Rose, a burden to his parents and a perpetual source of horror and regret to the girl he loved.

“Take her my wages, Hank, old pard, and tell her- tell her I broke the jam. You know-she’ll understand. There’s lots of buried up in these woods,” he added, “fellers that’s broke jams before me.”

“It’ll break her heart as well,” Hank observed. ” Lucie’s almighty fond of you.” But Garnier held to his decision, and those among the men who were returning to Ste. Rose agreed to conceal the fact that he was alive.

The arms were set in due course by the camp doctor, the wounds in the face healed gradually ; and two months later the man entered intoa partnership with a fishing Indian of those parts, and prepared to spend the rest of his life in the woods.

When Hank returned to Ste. Rose he went at once to fulfil the promise he had given to his comrade. It was an odious and difficult task. Moreover, it was not the whole truth. His long face betrayed the nature of his message.

“What is your news of him? ” she asked quickly. ” Tell me at once. Oh! is it bad? You look so dreadful—? “

“He broke the jam,” Hank said huskily, for he did not understand roundabout methods of breaking bad news. Quickest was best, he thought. And, there- I never seen any man do a grander thing. He was the bravest chap of the lot, and that cool over it all—”

“I he-gone then? ” she asked in a breathless whisper and with so awful a face that Hank cut short the description he had imagined she would like, and hurried on to his message and the money.

“Here’s his wages I was to give you,” he said, with the feeling that he was doing a most shameful thing, ” and I was particular to tell you that he did it so you might know he was a man again, and—” But Hank’s sentence remained unfinished, for the girl had fallen in a faint at his feet. He picked her up and laid her on the sofa and in the time he had to collect himself before she came round again he made up his mind, after his own method, that his promise to Jean was a bad one, and that he was blessed if he’d keep it.

“He ain’t gone at all, only you don’t give a feller time to answer,” he said as soon as she opened her eyes. ” He’s only a bit mussed up, that’s all. He’s waiting for you, if you’ll only listen instead of faintin’.”

“But I made him do it,” she murmured despairingly. ” I sent him away. He did it for me. Oh! take me to him at once, or bring him to me. I must see him. I can’t live without him.”

Bit by bit the girl learned the exact truth, and the story so set her heart aflame that there was nothing for it but to go after her lover into the woods and seek till she found him. He had originally gone up with the camp in November. He broke the jam in April, and the news was brought to her in the end of July. It was thus nine months since she had seen him, and her heart ached unspeakably.

A week or so after Hank’s revelation he started up into the woods again to search for Garnier and the Indian. Lucie and her brother went with him. But the Indian kept a moving camp, and it was some time before they got upon his tracks.

“It was well on in September,” said Hank, as he finished the story, ” when we found the trail of the fishing Indian and p up with his old squaw. Garnier and the Indian were out on a fishing bout, and wouldn’t be back for a week or more. One evening at sunset, as we were sitting on the shore parin’ cedar ribs for the canoes, we heard some one singing far out on the lake, and there, sure’nough, was the big fishing - canoe with Pete, the Indian, in the bows, and Garnier, in the stern seat, steering. His arms were as good as ever, and his voice well it kinder made the tears rise in yer throat somehow to hear it.

“And Lucie, she jumped up and couldn’t settle herself to doin’ anything except runnin’ along the shore and calling to him across the water. I think old Pete had an idea his wigwam was being attacked, because he stopped paddling one time, and made as if he was sheerin’ round to land somewhar else. But at last they come close enough to see who it was, and then-well, I never seen a canoe nearer upsettin’ in the whole of my life. For Garnier, he stood up an’ stared, and then sot down again, and then got up again, just as if he was on shore instead of in a bark canoe loaded with fish.

“Then, when they landed, Lucie’s brother an’ I, we took old Pete, the Indian, aside to show him something in the bush. He wasn’t exactly lookin’ for it, that’s true, but then we wanted him out of the way whar he couldn’t stare in that foolish Indian way. An’ they two -well, Pete’s old squaw followed us out also - and they two had the dirty old wigwam all to themselves to do their fist-shakin’ in.

“Yes, an’ it all happened not over a mile away from this here very spot whar we’re now settin’.” he observed, looking round into the woods where the silence and the shadows were growing every minute deeper, ” an’ I do b’lieve the old Indian’s still lamenting his luck at losing such a good, honest fishing partner to this very day.”

If the Cap Fits—

Field-Martin, the naturalist, sat in his corner armchair at the Club and watched them—this group of men that had drifted together round the table just opposite and begun to talk. He did not wish to listen, but was too near to help himself. The newspaper over which he had dozed lay at his feet, and he bent forward to pick it up and make it crackle with a pretence of reading.

“Then what is psychometry?” was the question that first caught his attention. It was Slopkins who asked it, the man with the runaway chin and over-weighted, hooked nose, that seemed to bring forward all the top of his face and made him resemble a large codfish for ever in the act of rising to some invisible bait. “Something to do with soul measuring, I suppose, unless my Greek has gone utterly to pot,” said the jovial man beside him, pouring out his tea from a height, as a waiter pours out flat beer when he wants to force it to froth in the glass.

“Like those Yankee doctors, don’t you remember,” put in someone else, with the irrelevance of casual conversation, “who weighed a human body just before it died and just after, and made an affidavit that the difference in ounces represented the weight of the soul.”

Several laughed. Field-Martin wheeled up his chair with vigorous strokes of his heels and joined the group, accepting the offer of an extra cup out of that soaring teapot. The particular subject under discussion bored him, but he liked to sit and watch men talking, just as he liked to sit and watch birds or animals in the open air, studying their movements, learning their little habits, and the rest. The conversation flowed on in desultory fashion in the way conversations usually do flow on, one or two talkers putting in occasional real thoughts, the majority merely repeating what they have heard others say.

“Yes, but what is psychometry really?” repeated the codfish man, after an interval during which the talk had drifted into an American story that grew apparently out of the reference to American doctors. For that particular invisible bait still hovered above the surface of his slow mental stream, and he was making a second shot at it, after the manner of his ilk. The question was so obviously intended to be answered seriously that this time no one guffawed or exercised his wit. For a moment, indeed, no one answered at all. Then a man at the back of the group, a man with a deep voice and a rather theatrical and enthusiastic manner, spoke.

“Psychometry, I take it,” he said with conviction, “is the quality possessed by everything, even by inanimate objects, of sending out vibrations which—which can put certain sensitive persons en rapport, pictorially as it were, with all the events that have ever happened within the ken of such objects—” “Persons known as psychometrists, I suppose?” from the codfish man, who seemed to like things labelled carefully.

The other nodded. “Psychometrist, I believe,” he continued, “is the name of that very psychical and imaginative type that can ‘sense’ such infinitely delicate vibrations. In reality, I suppose, they are receptive folk who correspond to the sensitive photographic plate that records vibrations of light in a similar way and results in a visible picture.”

A man dropped his teaspoon with a clatter; another splashed noisily in his cup, stirring it a third plunged at the buttered toast of his neighbour; and Field-Martin, the naturalist, gave an impatient kick with his leg against the arm-chair opposite. He loathed this kind of talk. The speaker evidently was one of those who knew by heart the “patter” of psychical research, or what passes for it among credulous and untrained minds—master of that peculiar jargon, quasi-scientific, about vibrations and the rest, that such persons affect. But he was too lazy to interrupt or disagree. Wondering vaguely who the speaker might be, he drank his tea, and listened with laughter and disgust about equally mingled in his mind. Others, besides the codfish, were asking questions. Answers were not behindhand.

“You remember Denton’s experiments—Professor Denton, of Cambridge, Mass.,” the enthusiastic man was saying, “who found that his wife was a psychometrist, and how she had only to hold a thing in her hand, with eyes blindfolded, to get pictures of scenes that had passed before it. A bit of stone he gave her brought vivid and gorgeous pictures of processions and pageants before her inner eye, I remember, and at the end of the experiment her husband told her what the stone was.”

“By Jove! And what was it?” asked codfish. “A fragment from an old temple at Thebes,” was the reply.

“Quite possible,” was the reply. “But, another time, when he gave her something wrapped up in a bit of paper, taken from a tray covered with objects similarly wrapped up so that he could not know what particular one he held at the moment, she took it for a second, then screamed out that she was rushing, tearing, falling through space, and let it drop with a gasp of breathless excitement—”

“And—?” asked one or two.

“It was a piece of meteorite,” was the answer. “You see, she had psychometrised the sensations of the falling star. I know, for instance, another woman who is so sensitive to the atmospheres of things and people, that she can tell you every blessed thing about a stranger whose just-vacated chair she sits down in. I’ve known her leave a bus, too, when certain people have got in and sat next to her, because—” Field-Martin paid for his neighbour’s tea by mistake and moved away, hoping his contempt was not too clearly marked for politeness.

“—everything, you see, has an atmosphere charged with its own individual associations. An object can communicate an emotion it has borrowed by contact with someone living—” was a fragment of the last sentence he heard as he left the room and went downstairs, spitting fire internally against the speaker and all his kidney. He seized his hat and hurried away. He walked home to his Chelsea flat, fuming inwardly, wondering vaguely if there was any other club he could join where he could have his tea without being obliged to listen to such stuff … He walked through the Park, meaning to cut through via Queensgate, and as he went he followed his usual custom of thinking out details of his work: the next day, for instance, he was to lecture upon “English Birds of Prey,” and in his mind he reviewed carefully the form and substance of what he would say. He skirted the Serpentine, watching the sea-gulls wheeling through the graceful figures of their evening dance against the saffron sky. The exquisite tilt and balance of their bodies fascinated him as usual. He stopped a moment to watch it. To a mind like his it was full of suggestion, and instinctively he began comparing the method of flight with that of the hawks; one or two points occurred to him that he could make good use of in his lecture … when he became aware that something drew his attention down from the sky to the water, and that the interest he felt in the birds was being usurped by thoughts of another kind. Without apparent reason, reflections of a very different order passed into the stream of his consciousness—somewhat urgently. Sea-gulls, hawks, birds of prey, and the rest faded from his mental vision; wings and details of flight departed; his eye, and with it his thought, dropped from the sky to the surface of the water, shimmering there beneath the last tints of the sunset. The emotion of the naturalist,” stirred into activity by the least symbol of his lifelong study—a bird, an animal, an insect—had been curiously replaced; and the transition was abrupt enough to touch him with a sense of surprise—almost, perhaps, of shock.

Now, vigorous imagination, the kind that creates out of next to nothing, was not an ingredient of his logical and “scientific” cast of mind, and Field-Martin, slightly puzzled, was at a loss to explain this irregular behaviour of his usually methodical system. He stepped back farther from the brink where the little waves splashed … yet, even as he did so, he realised that the force dictating the impulse was of a protective character, guiding, directing, almost warning. In words, had he been a writer, he might have transposed it thus: “Be careful of that water!” For the truth was it had suddenly made him shrink.

He continued his way, puzzled and disturbed. Of the mutinous forces that lie so thinly screened behind life, dropping from time to time their faint, wireless messages upon the soul, Field-Martin hardly discerned the existence. And this passing menace of the water was disquieting—all the more so because his temperament furnished him with no possible instrument of measurement. A sense of deep water, cold, airless, still, invaded his mind; he thought of its suffocating mass lying over mouth and ears he realised something of the struggle for breath, and the frantic efforts to reach the surface and keep afloat that a drowning man—

“But what nonsense is this? Where do these thoughts suddenly come from?” he exclaimed, hurrying along. He had crossed the road now. So as to put a greater distance, and a stretch of wholesome human traffic, between him and that sheet of water lying like painted glass beneath the fading sky. Yet it pulled and drew him back again to the shore, inviting him with a curious, soft insistence that rendered necessary a distinct effort of will to resist it successfully. Birds were utterly forgotten. His very being was steeped in water—to the neck, to the eyes, his lungs filled, his ears charged with the rushing noises of singing and drumming that come to complete the dread bewilderment of the drowning man. Field-Martin shook and trembled as he crossed the bridge by Kensington Gardens. … That impulse to throw himself over the parapet was the most outrageous and unaccountable thing that had ever come upon him … and as he hurried down Queensgate he tried to calculate whether there was time for him to see his doctor that very night before dinner, or whether he must postpone it to the first thing in the morning. For, assuredly, this passing disorder of his brain must have immediate attention; such results of overwork could not be seen to quickly enough. If necessary, he would take a holiday at once. …

He decided to say nothing to his wife … and yet the odd thing was that before dinner was half over the whole mood had vanished so completely, and his normal wholesome balance of mind recovered such perfect control, that he could afford to laugh at the whole thing, and did laugh at it—what was more, even made his wife laugh at it too. The fact remained to puzzle and perplex, but the reality of it was gone. But that night, when he went to the Club, the hallporter stopped him: “Beg pardon, sir, but Mr. Finsen thought you might have taken his hat by mistake last night?” “His hat?” The name “Finsen” was unknown to him.

“He wears a green felt hat like yours, sir, and they were on adjoining pegs.” Field-Martin took off his head-covering and discovered his mistake. Finsen’s name was inside in small gold letters. He explained matters with the porter, and left the necessary directions for the exchange to be effected. Upstairs he ran into Slopkins. “That chap Finsen was asking for you,” he remarked; “it seems you exchanged hats last night by mistake, and the porter thought possibly—” “Who is Finsen?”

“You remember, he was talking so wonderfully last night about psychometry—”

“Oh, is that Finsen?”

“Yes,” replied the other. “Interesting man, but a bit queer, you know. Gets melancholia and that sort of thing, I believe. It was only a week or two ago, don’t you remember, that he tried to drown himself?” “Indeed,” said Field-Martin dryly, and went upstairs to look at the evening papers.

Imagination

Having dined upon a beefsteak and a pint of bitter, Jones went home to work. The trouble with Jones—his first name William—was that he possessed creative imagination: that luggage upon which excess charges have to be paid all through life—to the critic, the stupid, the orthodox, the slower minds without the “flash.” He was alone in his brother’s flat. It was after nine o’clock. He was halfway into a story, and had stuck! Sad to relate, the machinery that carries on the details of an original inspiration had blocked. And to invent he knew not how. Unless the imagination “produced” he would not allow his brain to devise mere episodes—dull and lifeless substitutes. Jones, poor fool, was also artist.

And the reason he had “stuck” was not surprising, for his story was of a kind that might well tax the imagination of any sane man. He was writing at the moment about a being who had survived his age—a study of one of those rare and primitive souls who walk the earth today in a man’s twentieth-century body, while yet the spirit belongs to the Golden Age of the world’s history. You may come across them sometimes, rare, ingenuous, delightful beings, the primal dews still upon their eyelids, the rush and glow of earth’s pristine fires pulsing in their veins, careless of gain, indifferent to success, lost, homeless, exiled—dépaysés. The idea had seized him. He had met such folk. He burned to describe their exile, the pathos of their loneliness, their yearnings and their wanderings—rejected by a world they had outlived. And for his type, thus representing some power of unexpended mythological values strayed back into modern life to find itself denied and ridiculed—he had chosen a Centaur! For he wished it to symbolise what he believed was to be the next stage in human evolution: Intuition no longer neglected, but developed equally with Reason. His Centaur was to stand for instinct (the animal body close to Nature) combined with, yet not dominated by, the upright stature moving towards deity. The conception was true and pregnant.

And—he had stuck. The detail that blocked him was the man’s appearance. How would such a being look? In what details would he betray that, though outwardly a man, he was inwardly this survival of the Golden Age, escaped from some fair Eden, splendid, immense, simple, and beneficent, yet—a Centaur?

Perhaps it was just as well he had “stuck,” for his brother would shortly be in, and his brother was a successful business man with the money-sense and commercial instincts strongly developed. He dealt in rice and sugar. With his brother in the flat no Centaur could possibly survive for a single moment. “It’ll come to me when I’m not thinking about it,” he sighed, knowing well the waywardness of his particular genius. He threw the reins upon the subconscious self and moved into an armchair to read in the evening paper the things the public loved—that public who refused to buy his books, pleading they were “queer.” He waded down the list of immoralities, murders and assaults with a dreamy eye, and had just reached the witness’s description of finding the bloody head in the faithless wife’s bedroom, when there came a hurried, pelting knock at the door, and William Jones, glad of the relief, went to open it. There, facing him, stood the bore from the flat below. Horrors!

It was not, however, a visit after all. “Jones,” he faltered, “there’s an odd sort of chap here asking for you or your brother. Rang my bell by mistake.”

Jones murmured some reply or other, and as the bore vanished with a hurry unusual to him, there passed into the flat a queer shape, born surely of the night and stars and desolate places. He seemed in some undefinable way bent, humpbacked, very large. With him came a touch of open spaces, winds, forests, long clean hills and dew-drenched fields.

“Come in, please:” said Jones, instantly aware that the man was not for his brother. “You have something to—er—” he was going to use the word “ask,” then changed it instinctively—“say to me, haven’t you?”

The man was ragged, poor, outcast. Clearly it was a begging episode; and yet he trembled violently, while in his veins ran fire. The caller refused a seat, but moved over to the curtains by the window, drawing them slightly aside so that he could see out. And the window was high above old smoky London—open. It felt cold. Jones bent down, always keeping his caller in view, and lit the gas-stove. “You wish to see me,” he said, rising again to an upright position. Then he added more hurriedly, stepping back a little towards the rack where the walking-sticks were, “Please let me know what I can do for you!”

Bearded, unkempt, with massive shoulders and huge neck, the caller stood a moment and stared. “Your name and address,” he said at length, “were given to me”—he hesitated a moment, then added—“you know by whom.” His voice was deep and windy and echoing. It made the stretched cords of the upright piano ring against the wall. “He told me to call,” the man concluded.

“Ah yes; of course,” Jones stammered, forgetting for the moment who or where he was. “Let me see—where are you”—the word did not want to come out—“staying?” The caller made an awful and curious movement; it seemed so much bigger than his body. “In what way—er—can I be of assistance?” Jones hardly knew what he said. The other volunteered so little. He was frightened. Then, before the man could answer, he caught a dreadful glimpse, as of something behind the outline. It moved. Was it shadow that thus extended his form? Was it the glare of that ugly gas-stove that played tricks with the folds of the curtain, driving bodily outline forth into mere vacancy? For the figure of his strange caller seemed to carry with it the idea of projections, extensions, growths, in themselves not monstrous, fine and comely, rather—yet awful.

The man left the window and moved towards him. It was a movement both swift and enormous. It was instantaneous.

“Who are you—really?” asked Jones, his breath catching, while he went pluckily out to meet him, irresistibly drawn. “And what is it you really want of me?” He went very close to the shrouded form, caught the keen air from the open window behind, sniffed a wind that was not London’s stale and weary wind, then stopped abruptly, frozen with terror and delight. The man facing him was splendid and terrific, exhaling something that overwhelmed.

What can I … do … for whispered Jones, shaking like a leaf. A delight of racing clouds was in him.

The answer came in a singular roaring voice that yet sounded far away, as though among mountains. Wind might have brought it down.

“There is nothing you can do for me! But, by Chiron, there is something I can do for you!”

“And that is?” asked Jones faintly, feeling something sweep against his feet and legs like the current of a river in flood.

The man eyed him appallingly a moment.

“Let you see me!” he roared, while his voice set the piano singing again, and his outline seemed to swim over the chairs and tables like a fluid mass. “Show myself to you!”

The figure stretched out what looked like arms, reared gigantically aloft towards the ceiling, and swept towards him. Jones saw the great visage close to his own. He smelt the odour of caves, riverbeds, hillsides—space. In another second he would have been lost—

His brother made a great rattling as he opened the door. The atmosphere of rice and sugar and office desks came in with him.

“Why, Billy, old man, you look as if you’d seen a ghost. You’re white!”

William Jones mopped his forehead. “I’ve been working rather hard,” he answered. “Feel tired. Fact is—I got stuck in a story for a bit.”

“Too bad. Got it straightened out at last, I hope?”

“Yes, thanks. It came to me—in the end.”

The other looked at him. “Good,” he said shortly. “Rum thing, imagination, isn’t it?” And then he began talking about his day’s business—in tons and tons of food.

In a Strange Land

A Caucasus Train

The best way to the heart of the Caucasus is via Tiflis, capital of Georgia, and the train from Batoum takes thirteen hours, though the distance is only a fraction over 300 versts. But one is grateful for the slowness of the journey, and thanks the driver of the two naphtha-burning engines for lingering at every one of the numerous stations along the old Colchian shore. Behind one the mountains of Armenia dip their blue sides in the yet bluer sea, and in front the soft outlines of the wooded Abkhasian shore, flanked by Mingrelia on the east, carry the eye with vast leaps up to that snowy, foam-like mass of white, where Eibruz is just visible in the sky, gigantic and remote.

And if one makes the journey on a Sunday, as I did, there is the additional attraction that the natives crowd to every station in the full glory of their wonderful costumes, and you survey some of the most ancient tribes of the world (according to the German authorities the Georgians are older than the Egyptians) while you sit at your carriage-window smoking the long, thin Russian cigarette. Not even Cook could arrange a better or more thorough review of the population than this.

The luxuriance of the vegetation along the fifty miles of shore leaves one rather bewildered, for in this moist and heated brilliance it is almost tropical, and of a rich prodigality almost oppressive. The wild confusion of box, azalea, rhododendron, fig, eucalyptus, almond, jasmine, aloes, huge chestnuts, and acacia, choked with vines and flowering creepers, rising out of a sea of giant bracken and utterly smothered in wild roses, leaves upon the mind a vague sense of a world suffocated under too many leaves, and not even the vile stench of the oil from the engine can prevent a hundred strangely mingled perfumes from flooding the air of the carriage.

Across the plain, too, as the train turns away from the sea and runs eastwards alongside the river Phasis (now Rion), the rich nature of this amazingly fertile soil is everywhere obvious—as also the inherent laziness of those Georgians who loathe work and scarcely trouble to pick the fruit or help the earth produce it, “Lazy as a Grusian” is the word here—Grusian being a collective term for the Georgian, Mingrelian, Iberian, and Gourian tribes in general. Being lazy, too fond of this good Kakhetian wine, and easily provided for by the soil, they are at the same time very, very poor.

The memory of the journey remains in one’s mind as a rather violently brilliant kaleidoscope, haunted persistently by the shades of Medea and Jason; of the Fleece glimmering there among the densely festooned woods of beech, more yellow than those flags that the hot wind sets a-shiver in thousands along every stream, or by yet dimmer visions than Shelley saw winging their way to the realm of Demogorgon in that “Caucasian Vale” where Asia, Panthea, and Ione talked such sweet music when the world was young. The proper way to view the land, one feels, would be as Phryxus did from the back of that flying ram—or its modern equivalent, the aeroplane. The mind and imagination become sorely overcharged and weighted; yet before these first suggestions can be arranged and shifted come others pushing urgently behind—that the Georgians are the “Lost Tribes,” and these “Mountain Jews” who throng the modern stations with their splendid, inscrutable visages had a King who traced his genealogy back to David; that this engine burning Baku oil is puffing its way somewhat in the direction of the fairest of all Gardens of the Imagination, that garden of great rivers, where Eve and Adam played; and that not very far south of Tiflis towers the 12,000 feet of snowy Ararat out of the Armenian plain!

Moreover, before we reached Tiflis under the stars we had passed Mtzkhet, ancient capital of Georgia, the treasure of whose cathedral is the robe of Jesus Christ (Argenteuil and Treves have the tunics only) and the bones of St. Joseph! The scholar or student, doubtless, with facts all neatly labelled and docketed, might have had no trouble with the surging suggestions that swamped an untutored mind, but I know, at any rate, it was a relief to focus the brain on some simple common object—such, for instance, as the charming little Georgian children, in rags and barefooted, who crowded the platforms like bright eyed, nimble-footed elves, and offered mountain strawberries, cherries thickly stuck on waving reds a yard long, and handfuls of wild asparagus at something less than a farthing for more than one could eat.

How they ran in and out among the flowing black and brown bourkas and the tcherkeskas of all colors of the big bearded mountaineers, huge daggers stuck in their belts, mitre-like bashliks at the back of their heads, high soft-leather boots, often charmingly “patterned,” and cartridge-cases of ivory, bone, ebony, or silver, strung at an angle across their big chests!

Very practical some of the arrangements of this Caucasian train—some, not all, for in a first-class carriage the only light was a fag-end of a candle that barely enabled one to tell the time when standing up! At the larger (!) stations the buffets are excellent, and time is ample to prove it. Hot bortsch, omelettes, various steaming meats, and delicious tea, cheese, and cakes, prices plainly marked, stood all ready on a counter. You helped yourself, carried your plate to a table, and were happy. A bell rings three times by way of warning—one stroke first, a few minutes late two strokes, about five minutes afterwards three strokes, and then the train moves out.

Moreover, the guard, in whose Mingrelian breast my Russian phrase book and my struggles with the names of the stations stirred pity and amusement, lent me his timetable, giving time of arrival and departure at every little station, with the exact number of minutes the train stopped there, Nor shall I ever forget the kindness of another Georgian, whom I discovered in the third-class as I walked through, who suddenly addressed me in French. Six feet high, bearded, his tcherkeska a perfect armory of weapons, his long nose suggesting something more than Semitic sympathy, he strode up and informed me that he had once been guide, interpreter, and friend for an Englishman (Lord Somebody, whose name I never discovered, for he pronounced it like a sneeze) in Daghestan, but who knew no French. (“And why was that?” he asked, “when France is at the door of London?”)

This warrior, without molesting me in any way, insisted on steering me through the bewilderment of Tiflis station, finding cab and luggage, telling me exactly what to pay porter and coachman, and then strode off and disappeared in the darkness with the bow of an ambassador and a gentle haughtiness that made a tip an impossible offence.

Towards midday the train passes the watershed between the Rion and the Koura rivers, and at Sowram enters Georgia proper, leaves behind the wooded mountains of Imerethia, aud follows the latter river through a treeless but beautiful valley, down to Tifils. At one of the last little stations, before the forests were gone, however, there entered the train one of the tribe of Georgian mountain Jews, his hands full of handkerchiefs and little shawls of the most delicate colored silk imaginable. It was like foam—light as the cigarette smoke he puffed incessantly. He was a born and most persistent salesman, and had ever new arrangements and groupings of his various articles to tempt one, all handmade in his native village.

He gave the guard half a rouble to be left in peace, and my travelling companion, a German of Baku, just back from the “hugely exaggerated Malkop oilfields,” acted as interpreter as well as victim. For 1½ roubles (3s.) I became owner of an assortment of “silk goods” I could have got nowhere else under four times the amount, and for which he had first suggested 10 roubles, or £1 1s. And this splendid-faced old man, a figure from little pictures of one’s childhood days, was presumably a member of the Lost tribes, and, according to Lehmann, Belk, and others, of a people older than the Egyptians.

By the time the train reaches Tiflis most of these bashlik’d and be-daggered fellows have got out, en route for their mountain villages, and only the few European travellers, mostly en route for Bakon (another seventeen hours) remain, with a handful of Armenians and Persians bound for their respective quarters in the town. The Koura, still little more than a torrent, races through the town that lies in its cup-like depression among arid hills. It looks its best arriving by night from the train, for it is difficult to tell where its twinkling lights end and the stars begin. In the glare of day one sees with dismay that it has its modern quarter (ugly as any other Russian town of straight streets), its tramcars, its funiculaire, and—six miles for roller-skating!

In Hungary with Tent and Canoe

It was a steaming hot day in August when our Canadian canoe slid up alongside the wharf of a Danube Rowing Club in Budapest, and we got out to stretch our legs and look about for a hotel. This was not easy, because of our savage and unkempt appearance, and our microscopic amount of luggage.

Six weeks before, we had launched the canoe at the source of the Danube, in the Black Forest, nearly a thousand miles away, and had been travelling in her ever since, sleeping at night in a gipsy tent on the shore or on the islands in the river, wherever we happened to be towards sunset; cooking our own meals, fishing, bathing, upsetting, shooting rapids, taking photographs, exploring quaint villages, and wandering inland wherever attraction offered.

In a word, we had been thoroughly enjoying the ever-changing scenery of the countries we had passed through—as the Danube rolled on, growing every day wider, swifter, and deeper—Baden, Würtemberg, and Bavaria, Austria and Hungary.

As may be imagined, therefore, our connection with the proverbial bandbox was not discernible at first sight by the time we reached Budapest, for the sun had tanned us a deep red-brown, and the Danube mud had not failed to add the finishing touches of its more delicate tints.

We had a suit of flannel for work, and a suit of cloth, plus a celluloid collar each, for the towns, the size of the canoe—after tent, blankets, and cooking apparatus were in—making further wardrobe impossible. So that, when we tied up at the first little wharf we came to on the right bank and searched the heights of Pest on one side and the streets of Buda on the other, for a hotel, we did so with no exuberant confidence in the nature of our reception.

Then, as we stood trespassing on the floating wharf, a man came lazily out of the boathouse into the fierce sunshine and prepared to lower an outrigger into the current. He was dressed in rowing things, and, after a momentary inspection (its brevity, we thought, did him infinite credit), raised his cap to us, and made a polite little bow. We at once hastened to explain our position to him in German and, to our delight, the gentleman replied with the greatest courtesy in excellent English.

“If you will allow us to take care of your canoe for you during your stay in our city, we shall be very pleased; and if you will come tonight to our club dinner and meet the directors, I have no doubt they will invite you to make the Club your hotel.” And here was sounded the note of that delightful Hungarian hospitality which never ceased to ring in our ears, from morning till night, so long as we were sojourners in the land of the Magyars.

It was the Hunnia Rowing Club to which our good angel had directed us, and we were at once made to feel as specially privileged Hunnia members. They housed, mended, and varnished our battered canoe; they dined us and lunched us; they showed us the town in all its aspects, the views from the heights and from the bridges, the things worth seeing in the galleries and churches and other places too picturesque to mention; they introduced us to the national dishes in queer little out-of-the-way restaurants, undiscoverable by strangers, and led us in the cool of the evening to the pleasant groves of St. Margaret’s Isle, where gipsy bands discoursed Hungarian music, with ravishing effect, into the sma’ wee hours. And the night before we left, a crew of eight took us in a racing shell at midnight, with the swirling current, under the four bridges, and then carried us more slowly up stream again, while the moon rose behind the hundred towers of the Parliament buildings, and shed a silver mist over the hurrying river and the sleeping city on the heights above. It was a memorable occasion, as the historians say.

But even Budapest became wearisome after a time. Our tent had been patched up and our cooking pots secured, and one day we left the friendly rowing club behind us and took the train inland to the Platten See, whither the mended canoe had preceded us by freight.

The Hungarian name for this lake is Balatontó (tó meaning lake), and many of the villages along its shores have Balaton for a prefix. It is a curious body of water, fifty miles long, from two to five miles wide, with warm yellowish waves, and nowhere over thirty feet deep. It has no islands. The south shore is flat, hot, and sandy, but the line on the northern side is diversified with deep bays and bold promontories, and the mountains rise picturesquely to a considerable height. Their volcanic origin is plainly seen in the truncated coves which rise here and there in a series of vigorous landmarks. Vineyards cover their lower slopes, and dotted about everywhere are the little country estates and summer villas of the rich folk from Budapest and Agram.

The natives told us the lake was “extremely dangerous,” but the natives were imaginative and musical and altogether charming—though poor boatmen. They had never set eyes on a canoe, and small rowboats were unknown on the lake. Some of the well-to-do visitors had sailing craft of various sorts, and at the wharves of the hotels there were usually moored a few canoes of the Rob Roy description (called Sandolin), in which, on perfectly calm days, the braver spirits paddled delicately about behind piers and breakwaters. But the latter had a bad name, and the sudden winds were proverbial—as, indeed, they seem to be on every lake in the world—and the majority of visitors and natives were completely hypnotised into staying on shore.

At Balaton Földvar, where we left the train, we found our canoe lying on the platform in the blazing sunshine surrounded by a curious crowd, and the moment we came up to carry her down to the shore the warnings broke out afresh, in three or four languages at once, and with as little warning as the alleged windstorms.

We had intended to start across the lake at once, but as a matter of fact it took us exactly six hours to get away. We had dressed in “camping kit” in the hope that the good people would be afraid to have anything to do with us. But no; apparently it only added to the bait. The Rowing Club had written to their friends. There had been articles about us in the papers; and the canoe, lying on the platform for two days, had roused infinite curiosity. So, with the best intentions in the world, our escape was delayed.

A sort of deputation escorted us to the village store and helped us purchase eggs, matches, oil, bread and vegetables, adding up the little bill in kreuzers and gulden lest we should be cheated; taking our names and addresses at the Post-Office in case letters came; and finally inviting us to lunch in the club and tea in the hotel. And in our threadbare and dirty camping clothes we trudged about all day in the heat, mildly expostulating but completely hypnotised into submission by the violence of the language and the energy and number of the deputation.

An hour before sunset, however, our patience became exhausted. A strong wind was blowing from the west, and the lake was rough, but even the risk of drowning seemed nothing to this endless smiling and bowing and saving “Thank you” in several languages with the thermometer at 100° in the shade.

“But now it is impossible,” they declared. “You cannot go tonight. No boat can live in that sea! Sleep here and go on tomorrow.” But this time we looked our friends straight in the eye, and said “No,” “Nein,” “Non,” “Nem,” “Nines,” and every other negative we could invent, and began to load the canoe.

“You will beyond all doubt presently come into the water like corpses,” said one of the prettiest girls, who had decided linguistic talent. But even that failed to move us and fifteen minutes later we were dancing over the waves half a mile from shore, and the kind and anxious crowd on the shore, with telescopes at their eyes, were doubtless discussing the best means of recovering our bodies and the cheapest way in hot weather of sending them home to England!

We reached the other side at length in safety, and put up our tent at the foot of the hills in the shade of some acacia-trees. A great herd of buffalo came down at sunset to drink, standing in the water up to their muzzles with a forest of branching horns rising oddly above the waves. We found the water took a lot of filtering, but when supper was ready it was a peaceful camp, and as we sat chatting round the fire later we saw the lights of Földvar shining across the lake at us out of the blue and purple shadows—all the more friendly for being at the other end of four or five miles.

The whole region is of volcanic origin, and it is said that sometimes on the calmest days the still waters of the lake suddenly become troubled, and great rolling waves appear, and the water boils and foams in a way that can only be explained by volcanic eruptions in the bed of the lake; but during our stay of several weeks we could find no corroboration of these stories. The volcanic energy which raised up the craters and mountains on the northern shore has retreated into the interior of the earth, From the odd-looking truncated cones behind Badascony the fires have long since ceased to leap forth. Volcanically the region is dead, and the only symptoms of ancient fires and eruptions that now remain are the warm sulphurous springs to be found everywhere in the neighbourhood, and which probably are also scattered over the bed of the lake itself.

Above our camp loomed the great promontory of Tihany, an extinct crater. Bare rocky hills rose up behind the narrow fringe of trees beneath which we pitched our tent, and from their summit the old monastery of Tihany overlooks the greater part of the lake. There was no farmhouse where we could get milk or eggs. Wood was scarce, for the belt of trees held only small acacias with vicious thorns, and very little “dead stuff” on the ground. The heat was intense, and the water was so warm that bathing afforded little relief. Storks and cranes had this part of the shore mostly to themselves, except just about sunset time, when a herd of buffalo and oxen came down over the steep hills to stand up to their necks in the water. We got some good photographs of these creatures, often in herds of several hundred, with only their noses and eyes and humps showing above water, and a sea of sharp curved horns all round. Buffalo milk, when we could get it, was excellent.

The lake runs east and west. The northern shore, as said, is mountainous and very pretty—villages every few miles, and between them vineyards coming down to the water’s edge. In some places, for many miles at a time, immense beds of reeds, ten feet and twelve feet high, line the shore to a depth of several hundred yards. Landing is quite impossible. Even if landing can be effected, and hard dry ground found for the tent, there is still no decent water to drink and no clear space to bathe in. More than once we were obliged to continue paddling for hours longer than we wished owing to these endless and impenetrable reed-beds.

After leaving Tihany we went eastwards down the lake and, just a little distance before the village of Réfülop, came to a camping-place, where we stayed for about a week. It is quite the best spot for a permanent camp on the whole lake. There is wood galore—small oak, pollard, and thorn trees. We found a shady place for the tent und a sandy bay for the canoe. Not a quarter of a mile behind our camp, through the pleasant shady woods, was a farm, where we got milk and eggs and bread as often as we required them. Moreover, the farm had a well of cold clear water, and the pail into which our cooking-pots fitted (one inside the other) just held enough to last us through the day. In the end this proved to be less trouble than filtering the insipid and warm lake water three times a day. In the village itself was a capital little inn where we could get a meal when weary of cooking for ourselves. Food was cheap and good; and, to add to the attractions, a Hungarian band of genuine gipsies played the wild national music all the evening beneath the acacia trees.

Réfülop, however, proved to have one serious drawback, if the daily invasion of our privacy, owing to an article about us in the Budapest papers, can properly be laid to its charge. This article, and the fact that we stayed in this particular camp long enough to attract attention and get ourselves known, unfortunately combined to advertise us, and we had the pleasure (?) of receiving visitors at all hours. They were mostly women. They came in parties of three and upwards. Some spoke German and some English, but they all said the same thing: “We have read about you in the paper, and we are immensely interested to see how you live, and how you cook, and how you sleep, and how you manage that wonderful little boat. Also we want to welcome you to our beautiful country, and to ask if there is anything in the world we can do for you. But most of all we want to know why you take the trouble to come such a long, long way to see our lake, and why you sleep in a tent when there are hotels in all the villages?”

In the end this sort of thing became very wearisome. We were never safe for an hour at a time. The good people all invited us to their villas, and gave us to eat of their delicious national dishes and to drink of their famous wines, but they could not for the life of them understand what we wanted there and what pleasure we found travelling in our rickety canoe and camping out when there were beds everywhere waiting to receive us.

Evidently our explanations were not wholly satisfactory, for the stories that soon circulated concerning us were very far removed from the simple truth. One was that we were both in love with the same Hungarian girl, and neither of us would consent to leave; another was that we intended to purchase a large vineyard, and were come to spy out the land; while a third had it that we meant to buy land and build a house on the shore of the lake, and had already “telegraphed to England for a steam yacht.”

A card of invitation from a friend in Budapest to a musical bachelor who lived all the summer among his vineyards proved a great pleasure. We trudged up the hot dusty roads and at length found his cottage buried among the vines. But sounds of music and dancing came from within, and he was evidently not the solitary hermit we had been led to expect. Covered with dust and with a strong flavour of camp about us, we were not prepared to face a party. Moreover, one of us carried a huge paper parcel from which carrots and onions (for the pot!) projected out all angles, and the other dangled a milk-can to be filled on the way home for supper.

So we hesitated—and were lost. For while we stood listening to the music and wondering what to do, a girl came out onto the verandah and saw us. After a moment’s amazed inspection she burst into a merry laugh and ran in again. The milk-can and the vegetable parcel seemed just then as big as the cottage itself; it was impossible to hide them. A moment later all the others came out flushed with merriment, and in a moment the white-haired old bachelor introduced himself in English and said he had been expecting us.

We were taken in and dusted first! Then a little déjeuner was prepared for us and we had to taste our host’s excellent wines. Our milk-can was filled, our vegetables packed up neatly; and then we were shown some Hungarian dancing that I shall never forget. For our host had been a pupil of Liszt’s, and to his impassioned playing the young people danced and danced till they could not dance anymore. It was real czardas dancing, full of barbaric grace and wild swift movement. And when it was over and the dancers were resting, the musician seemed to forget everything round him as he passed on to play the folk-songs of his country. One after another they stole forth from beneath his fingers, till the very spirit of Hungary seemed to rise up from the earth and air, from the mountains behind the cottage and the blue lake far below, and to stand before us. All the faces grew mournful and earnest as he played, and sometimes a voice joined in to emphasise the penetrating sadness of a phrase, or to mark some change in the weird rhythm.

From the musical bachelor we passed on down the lake to Badascony, where another charming family named Latskovitz entertained us royally. The hospitality of these Hungarians passes belief. Nothing seems too good for one of the nation that welcomed Kossuth. It is impossible to spend a single krenzer, and the want of proper apparel was never once felt. We looked like brigands, yet felt like princes, and the tact and kindness that can accomplish this are to be found only in communities where the spirit of snobbery is unknown—not, alas! in our own beloved England.

These people understood that we preferred a tent to hot bedrooms, and provided us with a private camping-place near their house and vineyards. Their coachman guarded our tent when we were out. They hung their garden trees with lanterns, and gave us of the Hungarian dishes on a round table under a spreading sycamore. We always shook hands immediately on rising from the table, and the conversation was an odd mixture of Hungarian, German, English, and French. But the singing was always in the Magyar tongue, musical, full of life and fire and perfectly adapted to express the subtle spirit of these wonderful songs.

After leaving Badascony we cruised about for a few days and then met our friends again at Kezthély, which lies at the extreme northwest end of the lake. And here an amusing adventure befell us.

It was difficult to leave our friends in proper time, and the sun was rather near the horizon when we paddled away, intending to camp at the first place that might present itself in the next few miles.

Pitching the tent and cooking after dark is a sorry game, but the sun went down and no openings in the great reed-beds appeared. The shore was everywhere treeless and swampy—no dry square yard on which a tent could stand or a decent bed be made. The darkness settled down over the lake and the lights of Kezthély were far, far away, but still the reeds presented an impenetrable wall. The stars came out and were mirrored all round us, but no opening came out in the reeds. Dozens of bays, that looked in the gloom as if they might lead to shore, proved vain, took us in and out, frightening ducks by the dozen and all sorts of other waterfowl as well. Luckily, the lake was like glass and the night clear and fine, but it was a long and tiresome piece of work.

At last, about ten o’clock, we came to a little village on the shore, and just beyond it the reeds came to an end. We pitched our tent by starlight upon a strip of hard sand, separated from the mainland by a space of swamp, marsh, and puddles. There was not a bit of wood to be seen, and the mosquitoes were thick and venomous. But we were so glad of a resting-place at all, and a dry bed into the bargain, that our dinner of milk and bread seemed delicious.

About eleven o’clock, as we were lying on the sand beside the tent, not even the lantern lit, we heard footsteps approaching through the swamp. Presently two figures, apparently boys, came to within a few yards, inspected us curiously, and made off again at a run. “Gipsies,” we heard them say in Hungarian, Our tent being a gipsy tent had misled them evidently, but it was not a pleasant reflection, because gipsies are forbidden by law to live in tents or to travel at all in Hungary. They are compelled to live in houses and have a trade.

Sure enough we had been betrayed. Twenty minutes later we heard more splashing to the accompaniment of excited voices. We lay perfectly still beside the tent, and in another moment a gendarme emerged out of the darkness and outlined his picturesque figure against the stars. His bayonet he held before him as if ready to charge, and his trousers were rolled up over his knees. He wore neither shoes nor stockings. Instantly he began in excited Hungarian; but we could not comprehend a single word he said. German was equally useless, for he knew not a syllable. With the light of many matches he examined the interior of our tent, poking the things about with his bayonet and jabbering all the time as hard as ever he could.

Probably, when he saw that we were not gipsies in spite of the shape of our tent, he came to the conclusion that we meant to fish by night, and made his search on that account. Fishing is strictly forbidden. At last, however, the examination of our small craft satisfied him that we did not intend much damage, for with the aid of the sneaky boy who betrayed us (and whom we felt much inclined to kick into the lake for his pains), he said in appalling German, “Only sleep here tonight, do no harm, and go on again tomorrow,” and took his leave, splashing back again through the swamp.

Our sleep was undisturbed, and a blazing sun in the morning turned the tent into a veritable furnace. We saw that we had camped too close to the village. Another couple of hundred yards and we should never have been seen. Immediately behind us on the mainland we made out the towers of a gentleman’s country house standing in a lovely garden and surrounded by acres of well-kept vineyards. In the bay a little steam yacht floated at anchor. Someone of greater importance than the small local vignerons lived here, and perhaps the zeal of the gendarme was to be explained on this account. And this proved later to be the case.

About eight o’clock two men came splashing through the swamp towards us. With smiles and many apologies they explained that we had camped directly in front of Graf Hanyadi’s house, and that in the darkness the policeman—who was also fish warden had mistaken us for vagabonds. We kept to ourselves the reflection, that in the light the policeman might have formed a yet worse opinion of us, and received the apologies with all the dignity at our command. We made it clear that this bad been the first disagreeable incident that had befallen us since we entered Hungary, The men, who said they were the engineers of the count’s yacht, expressed great contrition, and by way of making up for the annoyance offered to get us fresh milk from the village, and went away for that purpose with our milk-can.

While they were gone Graf Hanyadi himself came down to see us, splashing through the swamp just like the others, and, when we ran out to meet him to save his clothes, held up his hand to prevent us with, “No, no, gentlemen; I come to you.” He was a charming and courtly old gentleman, and was most anxious to do what he could to help us. “You must tell me anything you need and I will send it down from my house. I read about you in the paper yesterday, and my family have been looking out for you all day. Only this morning we saw your tent.”

We took him for a turn in the canoe, a craft he had never seen before, and at last his curiosity got the better of his desire to be of assistance rather than to bother us with questions, and he exclaimed, “But, gentlemen, the paper says that you always kneel in your boat! How is this possible? Your knees must be worn out. Do let me see your knees?”

At length he left us, with many kind wishes. “I shall write to my sons, who are at the farther end of the lake, and tell them to look out for your arrival, and to meet you and supply your wants,” he cried out. And this incident is typical of all our dealings with the Hungarians, from the fisherman and peasant up to the farmers, vignerons, and country gentlefolk. The name of the village where this occurred is Balaton Barény.

The fishing in the Platten See is a snare and a delusion. In the first place it is forbidden, and in the second there is nothing to catch except fogas—a fish peculiar to these waters. A company has the fishing rights over the whole lake, and with immense nets (covering a sweep of a mile and more) catch the fogas, and send them to Budapest, Vienna, Fiume, Agram, and all the other towns. The fishermen are not allowed to sell or give any fish away, but we managed once or twice to get a few excellent and savoury specimens for our pot, nevertheless.

In the Jura-Neuchatel

Many rapid tourist visitors to the continent of Europe make a common mistake. They imagine that a place or city can be known, understood and really appreciated in the very short time which they can devote to what is termed “doing it.” For the tourist with limited time this is very difficult to avoid, if, indeed, it is not inevitable.

While it is very true that the hurried traveller sees and retains in his memory much that is beautiful and grand; it is also true that there are moods of the arch-goddess Nature, which utterly refuse to reveal themselves to the superficial observer; those deeper and more subtle effects that only show themselves to him who forces their revelation by lengthy stay and continual intercourse.

This is especially true of the mountainous region of the Jura. The majority of people see the Jura, either on their way to Switzerland, when they are too eager for the first glimpse of the snowy Alps beyond; or, returning from the glories of the higher Alps, when the Jura seems tame and uninteresting. Thus they catch little more than a most superficial glimpse of this region of romantic, wooded hills. The general impression from the train is a range of hills with lovely pine forests, much the same as any other pine woods, with here and there a few dashes of cliff or a rocky ravine to relieve the monotony.

This may, in a sense, be true; but it is not all. Make a prolonged stay in the Jura of several months, with headquarters, say, at Neuchâtel. Make this quaint old city the starting point for numberless walks, climbs, explorations and excursions; visit alone the wild ravines and hidden streamlets that do not lavish their beauty on every hurrying traveller; stand on some of those proud peaks that rise out of their pine forests and look on the snowy giants in the far distance; follow the little paths, that with such delicious vagueness wind in and out among the fragrant slopes. You will discover the most exquiste little valleys, hidden away from the noisy world, each with its rocky gorge and streamlet, each with its cliff and waterfall. You will see long vistas of forest scenery, where the wild flowers mingle with the moss and pine needles, in a combination of the most lovely colours. Visit these spots, and by dint of many walks and peregrinations, surprise these quiet beauties for yourself, and after a month or two, perhaps, you will begin to appreciate that powerful charm which the Jura region must exercise over every true lover of nature, and which steals over the spirit as insensibly as the dusk that creeps over the fields on a summer’s evening.

The Jura is, indeed, a most romantic district, and one that fully repays a protracted stay. To those return ing from a sojourn among the sky-scaling Alps it will certainly look dwarfed; but what is lost in size is more than made up for and gained in expression. The whole region in the summer time is one of Nature’s fairest smiles, under which lie hidden secret meanings and charms that only reveal them selves to the one who coaxes their revelation and knows the smallest variation of her hills and valleys.

The geological conformation of the Jura gives to the mountain that characteristic appearance shared by all of a similar structure. The mountain limestone, of which they are composed, runs horizontally across the range in winding and well-defined strata. Here and there it may be seen, tilted up on end, and boldly starting out from the softer surroundings, forming a light-hued jagged peak with serrated edges. From time to time the traveller will come across spaces of wild beauty, where the bare white rock rises suddenly out of the moss-strewn ground, looking as if some giant hand had rudely torn from its surface the warm covering of pines, mosses and lichens, which on all sides renders the contrast the more marked.

Very often, too, in the neighbourhood of such spots the diligent observer may discover dark openings in the rock through which he may with difficulty squeeze himself. These are entrances to long and winding passages between the twisting strata which pierce far into the interior of the mountain. We ourself have explored many hundred yards of these winding and tortuous caverns, and provided one keeps a clear remembrance of the different turns and twists of the passages, the journey, with a good lantern, is both interesting and instructive. The air is damp and cool pools of water, deep and dark, into which the water drips continuously from the roof a bove, are scattered throughout these caves. There is on all sides a perfect silence but for the peculiar drip, drip, drip of the water. Only a dull echo responds to the noise of the feet. These interesting caves form a perfect network all along the sides of the Jura, and the intricate windings that thread the hills round Neuchâtel we have often explored and wandered, not infrequently giving ourselves up for lost.

In the neighbourhood of Neuchâtel there is a famous stream that will well repay us to follow its windings for some distance into the mountain home and source. The Areuse is a wild mountain torrent, that varies from a quiet, though never a clear, stream, to a rushing, foaming river. We suddenly plunge into the jaws of a defile so dark and gloomy that we almost imagine it to be the entrance to an enormous cavern. The little path we follow is fixed to the side of the weathered walls like windowsills to the wall of a house. The defile deepens and darkens at every step; the roar of the foaming torrent grows louder and louder, till we have to shout to make our voices heard. At one point in the gorge a man could with ease, though not with safety, span with his legs the width between the cliffs, so close do the edges of the ravine approach each other. But immediately beneath him the walls widen out enormously, eaten away by the violent undercurrents.

Passing out of this miniature via mala, a space of lovely green fields is reached, hemmed in on all sides by towering pine-clad mountains. Here it is that, for the first time, we obtain a view into the interior of the Jura, which repays almost any amount of trouble and time to see. Far ahead a wider horizon opens out, and bounding it between the sky and earth, looms up an amphitheatre of cliff so perfect, so enormous, and with a circle of such wide, sweeping, and majestic proportions that it fairly takes our breath away. It comes as a complete surprise; for we had not thought the Jura contained anything half so grand. This is the famous Cruex du Vent, the caverns of the wind. In a perfect semicircle, the broad strata of the limestone sweeps round its sides with the most beautiful regularity.

The winds here roar with an inimitable grandeur of sound from one end to the other, as if trying to escape from their rocky prison. Six hundred feet into the air these walls rear themselves up, bare and unadorned, and from the summit the impression is, if possible, grander even. Within this giant’s cauldron, the air currents seem to be extremely involved.

The railway from Paris to Berne pierces its way by means of tunnel and embankment through a portion of this great valley. In approaching Salins we cannot help being struck by the striking situation of the place; the forts crowning the lofty rocks are visible at a great distance; on the left rises Mont Poupet, an outpost of the Jura, while the torrent of La Furieuse pursues its turbulent course at the bottom of the valley. The town occupies the background of the narrow gorge, and rises amphitheatre like for a length of nearly two miles.

The salt works of Salins produce three thousand tons of salt annually. The springs are worked by hydraulic pumps. Three wells supply five hundred hectolitres daily.

With a farewell glance at the above illustration of the pretty source of the Furieuse, we turn to the more immediate neighbourhood of the historic city of Neuchâtel. Around its antique houses, its castle and cathedral cluster many memories of bygone days which make it a centre of very great interest to all who love to ponder over the past and read the lessons that history has to teach.

On all sides, in graceful slopes, lie the vine-covered hills that touch the very shores of the blue lake. Here in autumn when But the oranges are in full swing the sight is picturesque. before we explore a few of the beauties of the city itself, let us climb the rounded hill, that runs from immediately behind the castle hill in our illustration, and from its summit discloses a view unparalleled in the whole Jura region. At our feet lie the blue waters of the lakes of Neuchâtel, Bienne and Morat, while in the far distance the sunlight is reflected from a blue fragment of the lake of Geneva. Across the lakes, in indistinct haze, lie rounded hills and fertile valleys, studded with villages and pretty church towers, and behind these, in ever ascending gradations, rise step upon step the steep shoulders of the higher Alps. Behind these, again, stand out in a magnificent background the white peaks of the Alps in a glorious panorama that stretches from Sentis to Mount Blanc and the Matterhorn.

The history of the old city at our feet is a peculiarly interesting and eventful one, from the time when the Novum Castrum was a Roman fort to the time when it at length regained the freedom of its canton in 1857. Its surroundings, its streets, and its institutions are full of recollections of such men as Marat, the Revolutionist, Jean Jacques Rousseau, Farel, the Reformer, and the great scientist and learned Professor Agassiz, who for some years filled a professorial chair in the college. The ancient castle, which stands so picturesquely on the heights, has been turned into public offices. It adorns the city, however, none the less that it combines usefulness with ornament. The old cathedral dates from the twelfth century. Marat was born in a little village called Budry, that lies nearer the Areuse.

In the woods behind the city are some enormous specimens of those erratic blocks, which, lying on rocks of a totally different nature, point to some far distant home, and, as well, to some tremendous carrying power that has borne them so far and dropped them like hailstones all through these woods. Some of them—notably the Pierre de Boudry and Pierre a Bot—are as large as a good-sized cottage, and rise to an equal height with the surrounding trees.

Jimbo's Longest Day

The Longest Day has in it for children a strange, incommunicable thrill. It begins so early in the morning, for one thing, that half of it-the first half-belongs to the mystery of night. It steals upon the world as though from Fairyland, a thing apart from the rush and scurry of ordinary days; it is so long that nothing happens quickly in it; there is a delicious leisure throughout its shining hours that makes it possible to carry out a hundred schemes unhurried. No voice can call "Time's up!"; no one can urge Be quick!"; it passes, true, yet passes like a dream that flows in a circle, having neither proper beginning nor definite end. Christmas Day and Easter Day seem short and sharp by comparison. They are measurable. The Longest Day brims with a happy, endless wonder from dawn to sunset. Exceptional happenings are its prerogative.

All this, and something more no elder can quite grasp, lay stealthily in Jimbo's question: Uncle, to-morrow's the Longest Day. What shall we do?" He glanced across the room at his mother, prepared for a prohibitive remark of some sort. But mother, deep in a stolen book, paid no attention. He looked back at "It's all right; she's not listening ; but we can go outside to discuss it, if you prefer," his expression said. I beckoned him over to me, however, for safety's sake. My position was fairly strong, I knew, because the stolen book was mine, and had been taken from my work-table. Jimbo's mother has this way with books, her passion almost unmoral. If a book comes to me for review, if a friend makes me a present of a book, if I buy or borrow one--the instant it comes into the house she knows it. "I just looked in to see if your room had been dusted," she says; "I'm sorry to disturb you," and is gone again. But she has seen the new book. Her instinct is curious. I used to think she bribed the postman. She smells a new arrival, and goes straight for it. "Were you looking for this?" she will ask innocently an hour later when I catch her with it, household account-books neglected by her side, I'm so sorry. I was just peeping into it." And she is incorrigible, as unashamed. No book is ever lost, at any rate. "Mother's got it," indicates its hiding-place infallibly.

So I felt safe enough discussing plans for the Longest Day with Jimbo, and talked openly with him, while I watched her turn the pages.

"It's the very beginning I like," he said. "I want to see it start. The sun rises at 3:44, you see. That's a quarter to four-three hours and a quarter before I usually get up. How shall we manage it, d'you think?" He had worked it all out.

There's hardly any night either," I said, "for the sun sets at 8:18, and that leaves very little time for darkness. It's light at two, remember."

He stared into my face. "Maria has an alarum clock. She wakes with that. It's by her bed in the attic room, you know."

Mother turned a page noisily, but did not look up. There was no cause for alarm, though we instinctively lowered our voices at once. I cannot say how it was so swiftly, so deftly arranged between us that I was to steal the clock, set it accurately for two in the morning, rise, dress, and come to fetch Jimbo. But the result was clear beyond equivocation, and I had accepted the duty as a man should. Generously he left this exciting thing to me. pose it doesn't go off and wake you," he inquired anxiously," will you be sure to get up and make it go off? Because we might miss the beginning of the day unless you do." I explained something about the mechanism of the mind and the mechanism of an alarum clock that seemed to satisfy him, and then he asked another vital question: "What is exactly the "Longest Day, uncle? I thought all days were about the same-like that," and he stretched an imaginary line in the air with one hand, so that Mac, the terrier, thought he wanted to play a moment. I explained that too, to his satisfaction, whereupon he nestled much closer to me, glancing first over his shoulder at his mother, and inquired whether "everything knew it was the Longest Day-birds, cows, and out-of-door things all over the world-rabbits, I mean like that? They know, I suppose?"

They certainly must find it longer than other days, ordinary days, just common days," I said. "I'm sure of that." And then I cleared my throat so loudly that mother looked up from her book with an unmistakable start. Oh, I'm so sorry," she exclaimed, with unblushing mendacity," but d'you want your book? Were you looking for it? I just took a peep And when I turned to leave the room with it beneath my arm Jimbo had vanished, leaving no trace behind him.

That night he went to bed without a murmur at half-past eight. He trusted me implicitly. There were no questions: "Have you got the clock?" or "How did you get it?" or anything of the kind—just his absolute confidence that I had got it and that I would wake him. At the stairs, however, he turned and made a sign. Leading me through the back door of the Sussex cottage, we found ourselves a moment in the orchard together. And then, saying no word, he pointed. He pointed everywhere ; he stared about him, listening ; he looked up into my face, and then at the orchard, and then back into my face again. His whole little person stood on tiptoe, observing, watching, listening. And at first I was disappointed, for I noticed nothing unusual anywhere. "Well, what is it?" my manner probably expressed. But neither of us said a word. The saffron sky shone between the a trunks of the apple trees; swallows darted to and fro ; a blackbird whistled out of sight ; and over the hedge a big cow thrust her head towards us, her body concealed. In the foreground were beehives. The air was very still and scented. My pipe smoke hung almost motionless. I moved from one foot to the other.

"Aha!" I said mysteriously below my breath, "aha!"

And that was sufficient for him. He knew I had seen and understood. He came a step nearer to me, his face solemn and expectant.

"It's begun already, you see. Isn't it wonderful? Everything knows."

"And is getting ready," I added, "for its coming."

"The Longest Day," he whispered, looking about him with suppressed excitement and ready, if necessary, to believe the earth would presently stop turning. He gave one curious look at the sky, shuddered an instant with intense delight, gave my hand a secret squeeze, and disappeared like a goblin into the cottage. But behind him lingered something his little presence had evoked. Wonder and expectation are true words of power, and anticipation constructs the mould along which Imagination later shall lead her fairy band. I realised what he had seen. The orchard, the cow, the beehives did look different. They were inviting, as, though something was on the way. The very sky, as the summer dusk spread down it, wore colouring no ordinary June evening knew. Midsummer Eve set free the fairies, and Jimbo knew it. The roses seemed to flutter everywhere on wings. The very lilac blooms had eyes. ... I heard a rustle as of skirts high up among the peeping stars....

How it came about is more than I can say, for I went to bed with a whirr of wings and flowers in my head. The stillness of the night was magical, four short hours of transparent darkness that seemed to gleam and glimmer without hiding anything. Maria's alarum clock was not beside my bed, for the simple reason that I had not asked for it. Jimbo and the Longest Day between them had cast a glamour over me that had nothing to do with hours, minutes, seconds. It was delicious and inexplicable. Yet at other times I am an ordinary person, who knows that time is money and money is difficult to come by without uncommon effort. All this came for nothing. Jimbo did it.

And what did I do for Jimbo? I cannot say. His is the grand old magical secret. He believed and wondered; he waited and asked no futile questions ; time and space obeyed his imperious little will; waking or sleeping he dreamed, creating the world anew. I shut no eye that night. I watched the wheeling constellations rise and pass. The whole, clear summer night was rich with the silence of the gods. I dreamed, perhaps, beside my open window, where the roses and the clematis climbed, shining like lamps of starry beauty above the tiny lawn. . And at half-past one, when the east began to whisper stealthily that Someone was on the way, I left my chair and stole quietly down the narrow passage-way to Jimbo's room. . I was clever in my wickedness. I knew that if I waked him, whispering that the Longest Day was about to break, he would open half an eye, turn over in his thick childhood sleep, and murmur, as in dream, "Then let it come." And so, a little weary, if the truth be told, I did all this, and—to my intense surprise-discovered Jimbo perched, wide awake and staring, at the casement window. He had never closed an eye, nor half an eye. He was watchful and alert, but undeniably tired out, as I was.

"Jimbo," I whispered, stealing in upon him, the Longest Day is very near. It's so close you can hear it coming down the sky. It's softer than any dream you ever dreamed in your life. Come out-if you will-we'll see it from the orchard."

He turned towards me in his little nightshirt like a goblin. His eyes were very big, but the eyelids held open with an effort.

"Uncle," he said in a tiny voice, "do you think it's really come at last? It's been terribly slow, but I suppose that's because it's such an awful length. Wasn't it wonderful?"

And I tucked him up. Before the sheet was round his shoulder he was asleep,.... and next morning when we met at breakfast, he just asked me slyly, "Do you think mother guessed or saw anything of what we saw?" We glanced across the table, full of secret signs, together. Mother's letters were piled beside her plate, a book beneath them. It was my stolen book. She had clearly sat up half the night devouring it.

"No," I whispered, "I don't think mother I guesses anything at all. Besides," I added, to-day is the Longest Day, so in any case she'd be a very long time finding out." And, as he seemed satisfied, I felt my conscience clear, and said no more about it.

KEEPING HIS PROMISE

It was eleven o'clock at night, and young Marriott was locked into his room, cramming as hard as he could cram. He was a "Fourth Year Man" at Edinburgh University and he had been ploughed for this particular examination so often that his parents had positively declared they could no longer supply the funds to keep him there.

His rooms were cheap and dingy, but it was the lecture fees that took the money. So Marriott pulled himself together at last and definitely made up his mind that he would pass or die in the attempt, and for some weeks now he had been reading as hard as mortal man can read. He was trying to make up for lost time and money in a way that showed conclusively he did not understand the value of either. For no ordinary man—and Marriott was in every sense an ordinary man—can afford to drive the mind as he had lately been driving his, without sooner or later paying the cost.

Among the students he had few friends or acquaintances, and these few had promised not to disturb him at night, knowing he was at last reading in earnest. It was, therefore, with feelings a good deal stronger than mere surprise that he heard his door-bell ring on this particular night and realised that he was to have a visitor. Some men would simply have muffled the bell and gone on quietly with their work. But Marriott was not this sort. He was nervous. It would have bothered and pecked at his mind all night long not to know who the visitor was and what he wanted. The only thing to do, therefore, was to let him in—and out again—as quickly as possible.

The landlady went to bed at ten o'clock punctually, after which hour nothing would induce her to pretend she heard the bell, so Marriott jumped up from his books with an exclamation that augured ill for the reception of his caller, and prepared to let him in with his own hand.

The streets of Edinburgh town were very still at this late hour—it was late for Edinburgh—and in the quiet neighbourhood of F—— Street, where Marriott lived on the third floor, scarcely a sound broke the silence. As he crossed the floor, the bell rang a second time, with unnecessary clamour, and he unlocked the door and passed into the little hallway with considerable wrath and annoyance in his heart at the insolence of the double interruption.

"The fellows all know I'm reading for this exam. Why in the world do they come to bother me at such an unearthly hour?"

The inhabitants of the building, with himself, were medical students, general students, poor Writers to the Signet, and some others whose vocations were perhaps not so obvious. The stone staircase, dimly lighted at each floor by a gas-jet that would not turn above a certain height, wound down to the level of the street with no pretence at carpet or railing. At some levels it was cleaner than at others. It depended on the landlady of the particular level.

The acoustic properties of a spiral staircase seem to be peculiar. Marriott, standing by the open door, book in hand, thought every moment the owner of the footsteps would come into view. The sound of the boots was so close and so loud that they seemed to travel disproportionately in advance of their cause. Wondering who it could be, he stood ready with all manner of sharp greetings for the man who dared thus to disturb his work. But the man did not appear. The steps sounded almost under his nose, yet no one was visible.

A sudden queer sensation of fear passed over him—a faintness and a shiver down the back. It went, however, almost as soon as it came, and he was just debating whether he would call aloud to his invisible visitor, or slam the door and return to his books, when the cause of the disturbance turned the corner very slowly and came into view.

It was a stranger. He saw a youngish man short of figure and very broad. His face was the colour of a piece of chalk and the eyes, which were very bright, had heavy lines underneath them. Though the cheeks and chin were unshaven and the general appearance unkempt, the man was evidently a gentleman, for he was well dressed and bore himself with a certain air. But, strangest of all, he wore no hat, and carried none in his hand; and although rain had been falling steadily all the evening, he appeared to have neither overcoat nor umbrella.

A hundred questions sprang up in Marriott's mind and rushed to his lips, chief among which was something like "Who in the world are you?" and "What in the name of heaven do you come to me for?" But none of these questions found time to express themselves in words, for almost at once the caller turned his head a little so that the gas light in the hall fell upon his features from a new angle. Then in a flash Marriott recognised him.

"Field! Man alive! Is it you?" he gasped.

The Fourth Year Man was not lacking in intuition, and he perceived at once that here was a case for delicate treatment. He divined, without any actual process of thought, that the catastrophe often predicted had come at last, and that this man's father had turned him out of the house. They had been at a private school together years before, and though they had hardly met once since, the news had not failed to reach him from time to time with considerable detail, for the family lived near his own and between certain of the sisters there was great intimacy. Young Field had gone wild later, he remembered hearing about it all—drink, a woman, opium, or something of the sort—he could not exactly call to mind.

"Come in," he said at once, his anger vanishing. "There's been something wrong, I can see. Come in, and tell me all about it and perhaps I can help—" He hardly knew what to say, and stammered a lot more besides. The dark side of life, and the horror of it, belonged to a world that lay remote from his own select little atmosphere of books and dreamings. But he had a man's heart for all that.

He led the way across the hall, shutting the front door carefully behind him, and noticed as he did so that the other, though certainly sober, was unsteady on his legs, and evidently much exhausted. Marriott might not be able to pass his examinations, but he at least knew the symptoms of starvation—acute starvation, unless he was much mistaken—when they stared him in the face.

"Come along," he said cheerfully, and with genuine sympathy in his voice. "I'm glad to see you. I was going to have a bite of something to eat, and you're just in time to join me."

The other made no audible reply, and shuffled so feebly with his feet that Marriott took his arm by way of support. He noticed for the first time that the clothes hung on him with pitiful looseness. The broad frame was literally hardly more than a frame. He was as thin as a skeleton. But, as he touched him, the sensation of faintness and dread returned. It only lasted a moment, and then passed off, and he ascribed it not unnaturally to the distress and shock of seeing a former friend in such a pitiful plight.

"Better let me guide you. It's shamefully dark—this hall. I'm always complaining," he said lightly, recognising by the weight upon his arm that the guidance was sorely needed, "but the old cat never does anything except promise." He led him to the sofa, wondering all the time where he had come from and how he had found out the address. It must be at least seven years since those days at the private school when they used to be such close friends.

"Now, if you'll forgive me for a minute," he said, "I'll get supper ready—such as it is. And don't bother to talk. Just take it easy on the sofa. I see you're dead tired. You can tell me about it afterwards, and we'll make plans."

The other sat down on the edge of the sofa and stared in silence, while Marriott got out the brown loaf, scones, and huge pot of marmalade that Edinburgh students always keep in their cupboards. His eyes shone with a brightness that suggested drugs, Marriott thought, stealing a glance at him from behind the cupboard door. He did not like yet to take a full square look. The fellow was in a bad way, and it would have been so like an examination to stare and wait for explanations. Besides, he was evidently almost too exhausted to speak. So, for reasons of delicacy—and for another reason as well which he could not exactly formulate to himself—he let his visitor rest apparently unnoticed, while he busied himself with the supper. He lit the spirit lamp to make cocoa, and when the water was boiling he drew up the table with the good things to the sofa, so that Field need not have even the trouble of moving to a chair.

"Now, let's tuck in," he said, "and afterwards we'll have a pipe and a chat. I'm reading for an exam, you know, and I always have something about this time. It's jolly to have a companion."

He looked up and caught his guest's eyes directed straight upon his own. An involuntary shudder ran through him from head to foot. The face opposite him was deadly white and wore a dreadful expression of pain and mental suffering.

"By Gad!" he said, jumping up, "I quite forgot. I've got some whisky somewhere. What an ass I am. I never touch it myself when I'm working like this."

He went to the cupboard and poured out a stiff glass which the other swallowed at a single gulp and without any water. Marriott watched him while he drank it, and at the same time noticed something else as well—Field's coat was all over dust, and on one shoulder was a bit of cobweb. It was perfectly dry; Field arrived on a soaking wet night without hat, umbrella, or overcoat, and yet perfectly dry, even dusty. Therefore he had been under cover. What did it all mean? Had he been hiding in the building? . . .

It was very strange. Yet he volunteered nothing; and Marriott had pretty well made up his mind by this time that he would not ask any questions until he had eaten and slept. Food and sleep were obviously what the poor devil needed most and first—he was pleased with his powers of ready diagnosis—and it would not be fair to press him till he had recovered a bit.

They ate their supper together while the host carried on a running one-sided conversation, chiefly about himself and his exams and his "old cat" of a landlady, so that the guest need not utter a single word unless he really wished to—which he evidently did not! But, while he toyed with his food, feeling no desire to eat, the other ate voraciously. To see a hungry man devour cold scones, stale oatcake, and brown bread laden with marmalade was a revelation to this inexperienced student who had never known what it was to be without at least three meals a day. He watched in spite of himself, wondering why the fellow did not choke in the process.

But Field seemed to be as sleepy as he was hungry. More than once his head dropped and he ceased to masticate the food in his mouth. Marriott had positively to shake him before he would go on with his meal. A stronger emotion will overcome a weaker, but this struggle between the sting of real hunger and the magical opiate of overpowering sleep was a curious sight to the student, who watched it with mingled astonishment and alarm. He had heard of the pleasure it was to feed hungry men, and watch them eat, but he had never actually witnessed it, and he had no idea it was like this. Field ate like an animal—gobbled, stuffed, gorged. Marriott forgot his reading, and began to feel something very much like a lump in his throat.

"Afraid there's been awfully little to offer you, old man," he managed to blurt out when at length the last scone had disappeared, and the rapid, one-sided meal was at an end. Field still made no reply, for he was almost asleep in his seat. He merely looked up wearily and gratefully.

"Now you must have some sleep, you know," he continued, "or you'll go to pieces. I shall be up all night reading for this blessed exam. You're more than welcome to my bed. To-morrow we'll have a late breakfast and—and see what can be done—and make plans—I'm awfully good at making plans, you know," he added with an attempt at lightness.

Field maintained his "dead sleepy" silence, but appeared to acquiesce, and the other led the way into the bedroom, apologising as he did so to this half-starved son of a baronet—whose own home was almost a palace—for the size of the room. The weary guest, however, made no pretence of thanks or politeness. He merely steadied himself on his friend's arm as he staggered across the room, and then, with all his clothes on, dropped his exhausted body on the bed. In less than a minute he was to all appearances sound asleep.

For several minutes Marriott stood in the open door and watched him; praying devoutly that he might never find himself in a like predicament, and then fell to wondering what he would do with his unbidden guest on the morrow. But he did not stop long to think, for the call of his books was imperative, and happen what might, he must see to it that he passed that examination.

Having again locked the door into the hall, he sat down to his books and resumed his notes on materia medica where he had left off when the bell rang. But it was difficult for some time to concentrate his mind on the subject. His thoughts kept wandering to the picture of that white-faced, strange-eyed fellow, starved and dirty, lying in his clothes and boots on the bed. He recalled their schooldays together before they had drifted apart, and how they had vowed eternal friendship—and all the rest of it. And now! What horrible straits to be in. How could any man let the love of dissipation take such hold upon him?

But one of their vows together Marriott, it seemed, had completely forgotten. Just now, at any rate, it lay too far in the background of his memory to be recalled.

Through the half-open door—the bedroom led out of the sitting-room and had no other door—came the sound of deep, long-drawn breathing, the regular, steady breathing of a tired man, so tired that, even to listen to it made Marriott almost want to go to sleep himself.

"He needed it," reflected the student, "and perhaps it came only just in time!"

Perhaps so; for outside the bitter wind from across the Forth howled cruelly and drove the rain in cold streams against the window-panes, and down the deserted streets. Long before Marriott settled down again properly to his reading, he heard distantly, as it were, through the sentences of the book, the heavy, deep breathing of the sleeper in the next room.

A couple of hours later, when he yawned and changed his books, he still heard the breathing, and went cautiously up to the door to look round.

At first the darkness of the room must have deceived him, or else his eyes were confused and dazzled by the recent glare of the reading lamp. For a minute or two he could make out nothing at all but dark lumps of furniture, the mass of the chest of drawers by the wall, and the white patch where his bath stood in the centre of the floor.

Then the bed came slowly into view. And on it he saw the outline of the sleeping body gradually take shape before his eyes, growing up strangely into the darkness, till it stood out in marked relief—the long black form against the white counterpane.

He could hardly help smiling. Field had not moved an inch. He watched him a moment or two and then returned to his books. The night was full of the singing voices of the wind and rain. There was no sound of traffic; no hansoms clattered over the cobbles, and it was still too early for the milk carts. He worked on steadily and conscientiously, only stopping now and again to change a book, or to sip some of the poisonous stuff that kept him awake and made his brain so active, and on these occasions Field's breathing was always distinctly audible in the room. Outside, the storm continued to howl, but inside the house all was stillness. The shade of the reading lamp threw all the light upon the littered table, leaving the other end of the room in comparative darkness. The bedroom door was exactly opposite him where he sat. There was nothing to disturb the worker, nothing but an occasional rush of wind against the windows, and a slight pain in his arm.

This pain, however, which he was unable to account for, grew once or twice very acute. It bothered him; and he tried to remember how, and when, he could have bruised himself so severely, but without success.

At length the page before him turned from yellow to grey, and there were sounds of wheels in the street below. It was four o'clock. Marriott leaned back and yawned prodigiously. Then he drew back the curtains. The storm had subsided and the Castle Rock was shrouded in mist. With another yawn he turned away from the dreary outlook and prepared to sleep the remaining four hours till breakfast on the sofa. Field was still breathing heavily in the next room, and he first tip-toed across the floor to take another look at him.

Peering cautiously round the half-opened door his first glance fell upon the bed now plainly discernible in the grey light of morning. He stared hard. Then he rubbed his eyes. Then he rubbed his eyes again and thrust his head farther round the edge of the door. With fixed eyes he stared harder still, and harder.

But it made no difference at all. He was staring into an empty room.

The sensation of fear he had felt when Field first appeared upon the scene returned suddenly, but with much greater force. He became conscious, too, that his left arm was throbbing violently and causing him great pain. He stood wondering, and staring, and trying to collect his thoughts. He was trembling from head to foot.

By a great effort of the will he left the support of the door and walked forward boldly into the room.

There, upon the bed, was the impress of a body, where Field had lain and slept. There was the mark of the head on the pillow, and the slight indentation at the foot of the bed where the boots had rested on the counterpane. And there, plainer than ever—for he was closer to it—was the breathing!

Marriott tried to pull himself together. With a great effort he found his voice and called his friend aloud by name!

"Field! Is that you? Where are you?"

There was no reply; but the breathing continued without interruption, coming directly from the bed. His voice had such an unfamiliar sound that Marriott did not care to repeat his questions, but he went down on his knees and examined the bed above and below, pulling the mattress off finally, and taking the coverings away separately one by one. But though the sounds continued there was no visible sign of Field, nor was there any space in which a human being, however small, could have concealed itself. He pulled the bed out from the wall, but the sound stayed where it was. It did not move with the bed.

Marriott, finding self-control a little difficult in his weary condition, at once set about a thorough search of the room. He went through the cupboard, the chest of drawers, the little alcove where the clothes hung—everything. But there was no sign of anyone. The small window near the ceiling was closed; and, anyhow, was not large enough to let a cat pass. The sitting-room door was locked on the inside; he could not have got out that way. Curious thoughts began to trouble Marriott's mind, bringing in their train unwelcome sensations. He grew more and more excited; he searched the bed again till it resembled the scene of a pillow fight; he searched both rooms, knowing all the time it was useless,—and then he searched again. A cold perspiration broke out all over his body; and the sound of heavy breathing, all this time, never ceased to come from the corner where Field had lain down to sleep.

Then he tried something else. He pushed the bed back exactly into its original position—and himself lay down upon it just where his guest had lain. But the same instant he sprang up again in a single bound. The breathing was close beside him, almost on his cheek, and between him and the wall! Not even a child could have squeezed into the space.

He went back into his sitting-room, opened the windows, welcoming all the light and air possible, and tried to think the whole matter over quietly and clearly. Men who read too hard, and slept too little, he knew were sometimes troubled with very vivid hallucinations. Again he calmly reviewed every incident of the night; his accurate sensations; the vivid details; the emotions stirred in him; the dreadful feast—no single hallucination could ever combine all these and cover so long a period of time. But with less satisfaction he thought of the recurring faintness, and curious sense of horror that had once or twice come over him, and then of the violent pains in his arm. These were quite unaccountable.

Moreover, now that he began to analyse and examine, there was one other thing that fell upon him like a sudden revelation: During the whole time Field had not actually uttered a single word! Yet, as though in mockery upon his reflections, there came ever from that inner room the sound of the breathing, long-drawn, deep, and regular. The thing was incredible. It was absurd.

Haunted by visions of brain fever and insanity, Marriott put on his cap and macintosh and left the house. The morning air on Arthur's Seat would blow the cobwebs from his brain; the scent of the heather, and above all, the sight of the sea. He roamed over the wet slopes above Holyrood for a couple of hours, and did not return until the exercise had shaken some of the horror out of his bones, and given him a ravening appetite into the bargain.

As he entered he saw that there was another man in the room, standing against the window with his back to the light. He recognised his fellow-student Greene, who was reading for the same examination.

"Read hard all night, Marriott," he said, "and thought I'd drop in here to compare notes and have some breakfast. You're out early?" he added, by way of a question. Marriott said he had a headache and a walk had helped it, and Greene nodded and said "Ah!" But when the girl had set the steaming porridge on the table and gone out again, he went on with rather a forced tone, "Didn't know you had any friends who drank, Marriott?"

This was obviously tentative, and Marriott replied drily that he did not know it either.

"Sounds just as if some chap were 'sleeping it off' in there, doesn't it, though?" persisted the other, with a nod in the direction of the bedroom, and looking curiously at his friend. The two men stared steadily at each other for several seconds, and then Marriott said earnestly—

"Then you hear it too, thank God!"

"Of course I hear it. The door's open. Sorry if I wasn't meant to."

"Oh, I don't mean that," said Marriott, lowering his voice. "But I'm awfully relieved. Let me explain. Of course, if you hear it too, then it's all right; but really it frightened me more than I can tell you. I thought I was going to have brain fever, or something, and you know what a lot depends on this exam. It always begins with sounds, or visions, or some sort of beastly hallucination, and I—"

"Rot!" ejaculated the other impatiently. "What are you talking about?"

"Now, listen to me, Greene," said Marriott, as calmly as he could, for the breathing was still plainly audible, "and I'll tell you what I mean, only don't interrupt." And thereupon he related exactly what had happened during the night, telling everything, even down to the pain in his arm. When it was over he got up from the table and crossed the room.

"You hear the breathing now plainly, don't you?" he said. Greene said he did. "Well, come with me, and we'll search the room together." The other, however, did not move from his chair.

"I've been in already," he said sheepishly; "I heard the sounds and thought it was you. The door was ajar—so I went in."

Marriott made no comment, but pushed the door open as wide as it would go. As it opened, the sound of breathing grew more and more distinct.

"Someone must be in there," said Greene under his breath.

"Someone is in there, but where?" said Marriott. Again he urged his friend to go in with him. But Greene refused point-blank; said he had been in once and had searched the room and there was nothing there. He would not go in again for a good deal.

They shut the door and retired into the other room to talk it all over with many pipes. Greene questioned his friend very closely, but without illuminating result, since questions cannot alter facts.

"The only thing that ought to have a proper, a logical, explanation is the pain in my arm," said Marriott, rubbing that member with an attempt at a smile. "It hurts so infernally and aches all the way up. I can't remember bruising it, though."

"Let me examine it for you," said Greene. "I'm awfully good at bones in spite of the examiners' opinion to the contrary." It was a relief to play the fool a bit, and Marriott took his coat off and rolled up his sleeve.

"By George, though, I'm bleeding!" he exclaimed. "Look here! What on earth's this?"

On the forearm, quite close to the wrist, was a thin red line. There was a tiny drop of apparently fresh blood on it. Greene came over and looked closely at it for some minutes. Then he sat back in his chair, looking curiously at his friend's face.

"You've scratched yourself without knowing it," he said presently.

"There's no sign of a bruise. It must be something else that made the arm ache."

Marriott sat very still, staring silently at his arm as though the solution of the whole mystery lay there actually written upon the skin.

"What's the matter? I see nothing very strange about a scratch," said Greene, in an unconvincing sort of voice. "It was your cuff links probably. Last night in your excitement—"

But Marriott, white to the very lips, was trying to speak. The sweat stood in great beads on his forehead. At last he leaned forward close to his friend's face.

"Look," he said, in a low voice that shook a little. "Do you see that red mark? I mean underneath what you call the scratch?"

Greene admitted he saw something or other, and Marriott wiped the place clean with his handkerchief and told him to look again more closely.

"Yes, I see," returned the other, lifting his head after a moment's careful inspection. "It looks like an old scar."

"It is an old scar," whispered Marriott, his lips trembling. "Now it all comes back to me."

"All what?" Greene fidgeted on his chair. He tried to laugh, but without success. His friend seemed bordering on collapse.

"Hush! Be quiet, and—I'll tell you," he said. "Field made that scar."

For a whole minute the two men looked each other full in the face without speaking.

"Field made that scar!" repeated Marriott at length in a louder voice.

"Field! You mean—last night?"

"No, not last night. Years ago—at school, with his knife. And I made a scar in his arm with mine." Marriott was talking rapidly now.

"We exchanged drops of blood in each other's cuts. He put a drop into my arm and I put one into his—"

"In the name of heaven, what for?"

"It was a boys' compact. We made a sacred pledge, a bargain. I remember it all perfectly now. We had been reading some dreadful book and we swore to appear to one another—I mean, whoever died first swore to show himself to the other. And we sealed the compact with each other's blood. I remember it all so well—the hot summer afternoon in the playground, seven years ago—and one of the masters caught us and confiscated the knives—and I have never thought of it again to this day—"

"And you mean—" stammered Greene.

But Marriott made no answer. He got up and crossed the room and lay down wearily upon the sofa, hiding his face in his hands.

Greene himself was a bit non-plussed. He left his friend alone for a little while, thinking it all over again. Suddenly an idea seemed to strike him. He went over to where Marriott still lay motionless on the sofa and roused him. In any case it was better to face the matter, whether there was an explanation or not. Giving in was always the silly exit.

"I say, Marriott," he began, as the other turned his white face up to him. "There's no good being so upset about it. I mean—if it's all an hallucination we know what to do. And if it isn't—well, we know what to think, don't we?"

"I suppose so. But it frightens me horribly for some reason," returned his friend in a hushed voice. "And that poor devil—"

"But, after all, if the worst is true and—and that chap has kept his promise—well, he has, that's all, isn't it?"

Marriott nodded.

"There's only one thing that occurs to me," Greene went on, "and that is, are you quite sure that—that he really ate like that—I mean that he actually ate anything at all?" he finished, blurting out all his thought.

Marriott stared at him for a moment and then said he could easily make certain. He spoke quietly. After the main shock no lesser surprise could affect him.

"I put the things away myself," he said, "after we had finished. They are on the third shelf in that cupboard. No one's touched 'em since."

He pointed without getting up, and Greene took the hint and went over to look.

"Exactly," he said, after a brief examination; "just as I thought. It was partly hallucination, at any rate. The things haven't been touched. Come and see for yourself."

Together they examined the shelf. There was the brown loaf, the plate of stale scones, the oatcake, all untouched. Even the glass of whisky Marriott had poured out stood there with the whisky still in it.

"You were feeding—no one," said Greene "Field ate and drank nothing. He was not there at all!"

"But the breathing?" urged the other in a low voice, staring with a dazed expression on his face.

Greene did not answer. He walked over to the bedroom, while Marriott followed him with his eyes. He opened the door, and listened. There was no need for words. The sound of deep, regular breathing came floating through the air. There was no hallucination about that, at any rate. Marriott could hear it where he stood on the other side of the room.

Greene closed the door and came back. "There's only one thing to do," he declared with decision. "Write home and find out about him, and meanwhile come and finish your reading in my rooms. I've got an extra bed."

"Agreed," returned the Fourth Year Man; "there's no hallucination about that exam; I must pass that whatever happens."

And this was what they did.

It was about a week later when Marriott got the answer from his sister. Part of it he read out to Greene—

"It is curious," she wrote, "that in your letter you should have enquired after Field. It seems a terrible thing, but you know only a short while ago Sir John's patience became exhausted, and he turned him out of the house, they say without a penny. Well, what do you think? He has killed himself. At least, it looks like suicide. Instead of leaving the house, he went down into the cellar and simply starved himself to death. . . . They're trying to suppress it, of course, but I heard it all from my maid, who got it from their footman. . . . They found the body on the 14th and the doctor said he had died about twelve hours before. . . . He was dreadfully thin. . . ."

"Then he died on the 13th," said Greene.

Marriott nodded.

"That's the very night he came to see you."

Marriott nodded again.

Learning to Ski

It is greatly to the advantage of ski-ing that you can get an immense amount of enjoyment from it without being an expert. There is more pure fun in learning how to ski than in any other form of sport I know. The slopes where first you practised remain in the memory longer than many a subsequent tour, for the big tours become a com- posite picture after a time, so that even the photographs you took are impossible to “place.” But that first slope is never forgotten. There you fell backwards, forwards, sideways ; there you wallowed, struggled, kicked ; and there, often enough, you simply stuck, jammed like a jigsaw puzzle, staring with sheer amazement into parts of your anatomy you had never seen before, feeling disentanglement of legs and arms a sheer impossibility. To be believed, these contortions must be seen. “You'll go like the wind in a day or two,” said the man who imagined he was helping me, the first time I stood on ski. Then wind goes backwards, was my silent rejoinder. There was no breath to speak. And the truth is, no one can help much, Beyond giving a general idea of how to stand, how to place the feet, and how to hold the guiding sticks, verbal advice is of comparatively small assistance. Example counts, of course ; and to observe a clever runner is an inspiration in itself. For the rest, a few days’ practice on a friendly slope near home, followed by half-day trips to give variety of steepness, angle, kinds of different snow, seems invariably the quickest way to learn.

The first winter I went to Switzerland, skating and toboggan- ning were the enjoyments I chiefly had in view ; but I thought I might just as well skia bit too, With others it may be different, but before a month was gone the skating-rink saw me no more. Grinding round and round a circumscribed space with the eve always upon a bilious-looking orange somehow lost its attractive- ness, and tobogganning was only worth considering when the condition of snow upon the open heights made ski-ing quite impossible. That upper world of dazzling white, in windless sunshine and beneath a cloudless sky, once tasted, becomes irresistible.

I followed the routine like most others. I went to the Bazaar de la Poste and hired a villainous pair of ski at ofr. for the season. I thought them perfect, the fastenings admirable, the length and weight and curve just right, and I used them almost daily for three months. Hundreds of miles they carried me, above the tree-line, into unknown silent valleys, over ridges innumerable, into what always seemed absolutely undiscovered country ; they did not break when | fell; they took the snow grandly, waxed or unwaxed; and I regarded them as cheap and glorious invitations into Fairy land, But in all this I was supremely lucky. Cheap they certainly were, but in all other respects I should regard them now as worthless, even dangerous. Reasonably good ski may, of course, be hired at a Bazaar de la Poste as well as at a recognised Sports-Arlikel Bureau in Geneva, but the chances are against it. ‘‘It’s a marvel they didn’t break the first time you put them on,” the expert told me afterwards ; ‘‘ you must have had a lot of unnecessary falls with them.” It is nice to have one's clumsiness explained in this way ; but his remarks were valuable as well. For he showed me how the grain must never run off the ski, but flow straight down its entire length, because where the grain runs off indicates a probable breaking place ; and he told me to choose the hard American hickory when posible and to use fastenings that make it quite easy ‘to kneel without hurting toes or ankles. “It’s a wonder to me,” he added. looking at the fastenings that had given me many a painil wrench when falling, “ that your toes are not all broken long ago.

Nowadays, in a Swiss winter hotel, there is always someon’ who will guide the novice in his selection and steer him away’ from needless danger; and it is unnecessray here to enter into endless detail on these very important points. Ther are books galore which indulge in this till the reader sinks exhausted and feels the art of ski-ing is entirely beyond him. Having got your instruments and having practised neat home sufficiently to be able to balance with a reasonable speed and steepness, able to turn a little too, in case a horrid tree rushes suddenly towards you (as a tree invariably does), it is time pack a knapsack with chicken and oranges, chocolate, and peppermint lozenges for the inevitable thirst—and start at dawn for a rousing trip among the lonely heights. You carn’ your big waterproof gauntlets for the descent, and you take @ extra pair of warm woollen gloves for the freezing ridges; ako a paper waistcoat or Shetland vest, or anything you can muster that you hope will keep the wind out. Nothing really keeps the et out, but the paper vests are best, weighing a few erase and taking up no roogt~but. costingg—some eighteen francs at that. Dawn, of course, is nice and late—somewhere about eight o’clock—and the valley is icy cold, for the sun rarely tops the summits before eleven. But as you rise to meet it, the heat increases, and by the time you do meet it, blazing down upon you in full dazzling splendour, you are probably perspiring as though you had played a single at tennis in the month of August. Off comes the coat then, and is tucked into the knap- sack straps. That the mercury stands probably rodeg. below freezing-point you simply cannot believe, for the air is soft and balmy, and the warmth is so pervading that the idea of bathing may even occur to you. Only the glittering icicles that hang without dripping from the branches, and the silence of the torrent beneath its lid of solid ice, persuade you that the cold is actually intense. This, and the sudden change of temperature on your skin when you pass through the shadows of the trees, remind you that you are climbing under almost Arctic conditions. The huge, fern-like crystals on the surface of the snow, gleaming with violet rays, may further convey a hint of the truth, and the moustaches of your companions (three in a party are better than two, in case of accident, and alone never, on even an hour’s expedition !) are most likely picturesque with little fringes of clear ice as well. If there is wind, of course, there is no chance of under-rating the actual cold ; but as a rule these cloudless days are, fortunately, also windless— until the ridge is reached.

And once the ridge is topped, after two or three hours of steady, grinding pull, you stand so delighted and amazed at the prospect of further valleys opening into a glory of white enchantment at your feet that you quite forget the moment has arrived to extract that paper waistcoat from your pocket— until the wind, rising from leagues of winter to remind you, makes you feel that your skin is bare and that you have no clothing on at all. In less than a minute you stand shivering to the bone. And now, according to endurance and desire, you climb still higher—there is always something higher that entices dreadfully, to many a man’s undoing—or else find a place for lunch. Of course, there is no water; but the oranges have their value, and by increasing their juice with snow stuffed into a small neat hole, prove generally sufficient, till water is found again on the way down. And the spot for lunch is usually the sheltered side of some deserted chalet, where reflected sunshine brings the temperature to over 7odeg., and where boards may often be loosened from their chains of ice and used as seats, even as sleeping-places for an after-luncheon doze. It is possible, however, that the chalets are snowed under, so that you stand on the roof without discovering the fact at all, in which case a stalwart pine tree makes an admirable back, and the dead branches, dry as touchwood, provide an easy and most comforting blaze. Lucky that man, though, and wonderful his circulation, who can keep his feet warm, even inside three pairs of socks, until the time comes for starting downwards. And numb toes cause many a fall in the first fifteen minutes of the descent, to say nothing of the abominable pain when the blood returns. Which latter detail applies to fingers too—and hence that extra pair of woollen gloves. In spite of the blazing sun, it is often a painful business fastening on your ski again.

The delights of that luncheon hour, I always think, are— next to the homeward speed—chief of the whole expedition. The scenery and the air intoxicate ; the lights are ever changing ; the wintry grandeur of the bigger peaks about you, and, above all, the peace and silence of these trackless fields of snow, com- bine in a memory of sheer joy and beauty. And the ski, stuck upright in deep snow (in shade, too, and after cleaning, lest you find ice upon the fastenings later), form slender, graceful lines that cast long shadows on the dazzling white carpet. No blemish anywhere. The world lies spotless pure in all directions. And the descent is so inviting that at the slightest word the camp is struck and the brief preparations finished. It is here that the novice generally makes his big mistake. He thinks his toil is over. Actually, it is just beginning. For the work involved in picking one’s self up after innumerable tumbles is about the most exhausting kind I know. It ends by sorely trying the temper into the bargain. Falls follow one another so inexcusably. They seem beyond all understand- ing or explanation. The speed, by its demoralising effect upon nerve and judgment, account for a hundred or so, but the other hundreds seem simply caused by the mountains out of pure spite. And the nearer you get home—just when you wish to make an effective arrival, too—your sense of balance has departed finally, and it seems impossible to stand upright for two minutes in succession. The explanation lies partly, however, in the fact that brain and muscles are both tired, and that slopes you could have easily negotiated earlier in the day now present insuperable difficulties. The prolonged effort to keep true balance is an exhausting business altogether, and the beginner is wise to restrain his ardour during the ascent and be content at first with a reasonable height. Later, of course, balance becomes automatic. You hardly think about it.

But the glory of the day remains in the memory. A hot bath takes away the stiffness. You have learned more than you perhaps imagine. And next morning, full of life and zest, you start off again upon another trip—and probably fall a little less, or possibly a little more. It all depends.